<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adverse-Possession on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/adverse-possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Adverse-Possession on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/adverse-possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Adverse Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/adverse-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/adverse-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adverse possession is an unusual common law doctrine. We have already emphasized the point that legal possession and legal title are distinctive concepts. In general, &amp;ldquo;mere possession&amp;rdquo; does not disturb the legal title of the landowner, but the doctrine of adverse possession creates a dramatic exception to this rule. Under the doctrine, when a person has been in possession of land for longer than a period established by statute (called the &lt;em&gt;limitation period&lt;/em&gt;), they may become the title holder—and the original title holder may end up with nothing. The ultimate effect of adverse possession is to take title out of the hands of the original owner and to put that title into the hands of the person in possession.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keefer v Arillotta</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/keefer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/keefer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wilson-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Wilson, J.A. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#wilson-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an appeal from an order of His Honour Judge Nicholls holding that the respondents had acquired a possessory title to a portion of the appellants’ land subject to an easement remaining in the appellants.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The facts are more fully set out in the reasons for judgment of the learned trial Judge but the more significant ones for purposes of this appeal may be summarized under the following headings:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kosicki v Toronto (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/kosicki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/kosicki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sossin-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Sossin J.A. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#sossin-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Overview&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#overview&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Can private landowners gain title over municipal parkland through&#xA;adverse possession? This is the central question raised on this appeal.&#xA;The application judge answered this question by finding that municipal&#xA;parkland is immune to adverse possession. While I would not accept such&#xA;an immunity arises at common law, I conclude the application judge was&#xA;correct in finding that the municipal parkland at issue in this case was&#xA;not available for adverse possession. For the reasons that follow, I&#xA;would dismiss the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessees of Lawson et al v Whitman</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/lawson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/lawson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;halliburton-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Halliburton, C.J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#halliburton-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appeared at the trial that the land in dispute was included in a grant which was made to Jonathan Belcher in 1773, which the lessees of the plaintiff claim by several mesne conveyances.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The case therefore rests upon the defendant&amp;rsquo;s claim under the statutes of Limitation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appears that in the year 1784 a grant passed to William Sutherland, and several other grantees bounded to the south upon the north line of the Belcher grant; but it is quite clear that instead of the south line of Sutherland&amp;rsquo;s grant, having been laid out upon the ground on the north line of the Belcher grant, it was placed upwards of a mile to the south of it, and that possession according to that line has been held by those claiming under Sutherland&amp;rsquo;s grant for more than double the number of years requisite to give a title under the statute. This was indeed so far admitted at the argument that the plaintiffs did not claim to dispossess the defendant of that part of the land which he had actually cultivated and occupied, but as he had defended for a portion of it which was still in a wilderness state, they contended that they were entitled to a verdict for that. The defendant, however, contends that as the deeds under which he claims, contain the uncultivated as well as the cultivated land, and he or those under whom he claims have held by those deeds for upwards of 50 years that he is entitled to retain both.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piper v Stevenson</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/piper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/piper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;clute-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Clute J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#clute-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff claims as owner and occupier of lots 28 and 29, block &amp;ldquo;A,&amp;rdquo; Marmot street, North Toronto, registered plan No. 722, and asks an injunction restraining the defendant from trespass and for damages for former trespass and forcible entry. The defendant denies that the plaintiff is the owner of the lots in question, and says that he purchased the same from the registered owner thereof, and thereupon entered into possession of the same and built a fence thereon and planted a crop, which are the trespasses complained of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
