<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nuisance on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/nuisance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nuisance on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/nuisance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Black v Canadian Copper Co.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/black/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/black/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;middleton-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Middleton J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#middleton-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A large number of actions were brought, and many others threatened against the Canadian Copper Company, for damages supposed to have been sustained from vapours contained in metallurgical smoke issuing from the roast beds and smelter stacks of that company at Copper Cliff, near Sudbury. A motion was made to consolidate these actions resulting in the choice of four cases which were to proceed and to be regarded as test actions, the others remaining in abeyance in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canada Paper Co v Brown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/canada-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/canada-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-chief-justice-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Chief Justice —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-chief-justice-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the reasons stated by my brother Anglin, I am of the opinion that this appeal should be dismissed with costs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;idington-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Idington J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#idington-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The respondent as the owner of property acquired some years before the appellant, in conducting its business as the manufacturers of pulp and paper, had ventured upon methods complained of herein, and had built thereon for himself an expensive home and surrounded it with everything to make that home comfortable and enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuisance in Property Law</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/nuisance-as-right-to-exclude/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/nuisance-as-right-to-exclude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One right in particular, some argue, is fundamental to private property: the &lt;em&gt;right to exclude&lt;/em&gt; others from interfering with the owner&amp;rsquo;s use and enjoyment of their land, other tangible things and even intangibles like knowledge goods. The common law has devised several remedies to enforce owners&amp;rsquo; right to exclude. We have already seen two examples of this. In &lt;em&gt;Harrison v Carswell&lt;/em&gt;, the mall owner brought an action in &lt;em&gt;trespass&lt;/em&gt; against the picketer Sophie Carswell to exclude her from the mall sidewalk, while the plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Moore&lt;/em&gt; made a claim in &lt;em&gt;conversion&lt;/em&gt; in his attempt to exclude the defendants from using his cells after they were extracted from his body. Both of these are causes of action in tort designed to protect the right to exclude.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shelfer v City of London Electrical Lighting Co.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/shelfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/shelfer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The defendant in this case, the City of London Electric Lighting Company, operated large engines and other heavy machinery that caused damage to the foundations of a pub, the Waterman&amp;rsquo;s Arms, leased by the plaintiff, Shelfer, as well as a lot of noise and other &amp;ldquo;annoyances&amp;rdquo;. There was no question about the existence of the nuisance—the only issue before the court was what type of remedy should be available to the plaintiff.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victoria Park Racing and Recreational Grounds Co Ltd v Taylor </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/victoriapark/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/victoriapark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;latham-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Latham C.J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#latham-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an appeal from a judgment for the defendants given by Nicholas J. in an action by the Victoria Park Racing and Recreation Grounds Co Ltd against Taylor and others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff company carries on the business of racing upon a racecourse known as Victoria Park. The defendant Taylor is the owner of land near the racecourse. He has placed an elevated platform on his land from which it is possible to see what takes place on the racecourse and to read the information which appears on notice boards on the course as to the starters, scratchings, etc, and the winners of the races. The defendant Angles stands on the platform and through a telephone comments upon and describes the races in a particularly vivid manner and announces the names of the winning horses. The defendant the Commonwealth Broadcasting Corporation holds a broadcasting licence under the regulations made under the &lt;em&gt;Wireless Telegraphy Act 1905-1936&lt;/em&gt; and carries on the business of broadcasting from station 2 UW. This station broadcasts the commentaries and descriptions given by Angles. The plaintiff wants to have the broadcasting stopped because it prevents people from going to the races and paying for admission. The evidence shows that some people prefer hearing about the races as seen by Angles to seeing the races for themselves. The plaintiff contends that the damage which it thus suffers gives, in all the circumstances, a cause of action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
