<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reserves on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/reserves/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reserves on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/reserves/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Framework Agreement on First Nation Land Management Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fafnlma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fafnlma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;8 On the coming into force of the land code of a First Nation, the rights and obligations of His Majesty in right of Canada as grantor in respect of the interests or land rights and the licences described in the First Nation’s individual agreement referred to in clause 6 of the Framework Agreement are transferred to the First Nation in accordance with that individual agreement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indian Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/indian-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/indian-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;18 (1) Subject to this Act, reserves are held by Her Majesty for the use and benefit of the respective bands for which they were set apart, and subject to this Act and to the terms of any treaty or surrender, the Governor in Council may determine whether any purpose for which lands in a reserve are used or are to be used is for the use and benefit of the band.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rise of the First Nations Land Management Regime in Canada: A Critical Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fnlma-yellowhead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fnlma-yellowhead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-i-first-nations-land-management-foundations&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Part I: First Nations Land Management Foundations&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#part-i-first-nations-land-management-foundations&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the 2015 federal election campaign, the Liberal Party of Canada&#xA;campaigned on a platform of significant commitments to Indigenous&#xA;peoples, including the promise to &amp;ldquo;renew the relationship between Canada&#xA;and Indigenous Peoples.&amp;rdquo; But tellingly, they framed their platform as&#xA;&amp;ldquo;both a right thing to do and a surefire way to economic growth.&amp;rdquo; In&#xA;the emerging era of sectoral self-governance, the First Nations Land&#xA;Management Regime has become a key feature not only in the federal&#xA;government&amp;rsquo;s notion  of the &amp;ldquo;right thing,&amp;rdquo; but also their plans to chip away at the &lt;em&gt;Indian&#xA;Act&lt;/em&gt; and make First Nations more &amp;ldquo;economically independent.&amp;rdquo; Of course,&#xA;this economic growth or independence does not include a redistribution&#xA;of land or resources, rather it is an expectation that First Nations&#xA;should support their members through economic activities exclusively on&#xA;reserve lands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
