<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trespass on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/trespass/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trespass on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/trespass/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bundle of Sticks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/sticks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/sticks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When trying to explain the common law&amp;rsquo;s particular (and sometimes idiosyncratic) understanding of &amp;ldquo;ownership&amp;rdquo;, lawyers and judges frequently invoke the &amp;ldquo;bundle of sticks&amp;rdquo; metapho&amp;ndash;as in, &amp;ldquo;ownership is like a bundle of sticks&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;the &amp;ldquo;sticks&amp;rdquo; being the various property rights that make up the ownership &amp;ldquo;bundle&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the metaphor is that ownership is not really a homogeneous collection of rights that one either holds (ownership) or does not hold (no ownership). Instead, ownership is a malleable legal concept, difficult to pin down to any particular arrangement or bundle. One landowner might have an unrestricted right to use their land in any way they like, while another might have certain use rights taken out of their ownership bundle—say, by a restrictive covenant that binds and runs with the land. We would likely call both an &amp;ldquo;owner&amp;rdquo;, even though they hold different sets of legal entitlements in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harrison v Carswell</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/harrison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/harrison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;dickson-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Dickson J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#dickson-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The respondent, Sophie Carswell, was charged under &lt;em&gt;The Petty Trespasses Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.M. 1970, c. P50, with four offences (one on each of four days) of unlawfully trespassing upon the premises of the Fairview Corporation Limited, trading under the firm name and style of Polo Park Shopping Centre, located in the City of Winnipeg, after having been requested by the owner not to enter on or come upon the premises. The appellant, Peter Harrison, manager of Polo Park Shopping Centre, swore the informations. The charges were dismissed by the Provincial Judge but on a trial de novo in the County Court Mrs. Carswell was convicted and fined $10 on each of the charges. The convictions were set aside by the Manitoba Court of Appeal [1974] 4 W.W.R. 394 (Freedman C.J.M. and Matas J.A., with Guy J.A. dissenting) and the present appeal followed by leave of this Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monsanto Canada Inc v Schmeiser</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/monsanto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/monsanto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mclachlin-cjc-and-fish-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McLachlin C.J.C. and Fish J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mclachlin-cjc-and-fish-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This case concerns a large scale, commercial farming operation that grew canola containing a patented cell and gene without obtaining licence or permission. The main issue is whether it thereby breached the &lt;em&gt;Patent Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.C. 1985, c. P-4. We believe that it did.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In reaching this conclusion, we emphasize from the outset that we are not concerned here with the innocent discovery by farmers of “blow-by” patented plants on their land or in their cultivated fields. Nor are we concerned with the scope of the respondents’ patent or the wisdom and social utility of the genetic modification of genes and cells — a practice authorized by Parliament under the &lt;em&gt;Patent Act&lt;/em&gt; and its regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patent as Exclusion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/patent-as-exclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/patent-as-exclusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/monsanto_patent.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Monsanto Patent for glyphosate-resistant plants (US version)&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Monsanto Patent for glyphosate-resistant plants (US version)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A patent is effectively a statutory right—created and enforced under the federal &lt;em&gt;Patent Act&lt;/em&gt;, RSC 1985, c P-4—to exclude others from the products of cultural, scientific and technological invention. Patents given their &amp;ldquo;owners&amp;rdquo; a time-limited, exclusive right to make, construct, use and sell the subject matter of the patent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The basic rationale behind patent rights is one about economic incentives. As an intangible good, the inventive idea or design that motivates a patent is by nature non-excludable: once the invention has been created and made public, it is essentially costless for others to reproduce that idea or design in order to make their own products. Because inventions often require considerable up-front and sometimes risky investments, the rationale goes, exclusive patent protections are needed in order provide creators with sufficient financial incentives to create in the first place. According to this argument, if the right to exclude via patent did not exists, creators would have no motivation to produce their intentions and society would suffer as a result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protection of Property Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/protection-property/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/protection-property/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2 In this Act,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) &amp;ldquo;occupier&amp;rdquo; includes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(i) a person who is in possession of premises, or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ii) a person who has responsibility for and control over the condition of premises or the activities there carried on, or control over persons allowed to enter the premises,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(d) &amp;ldquo;premises&amp;rdquo; means lands and structures, or either of them, and includes trailers and portable structures designed or used for residence, business or shelter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trespass to Land</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/trespass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/trespass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The name of the most familiar tort protecting real property, trespass, was originally the name of an entire family of actions that first emerged in the 12th and 13th centuries. A plaintiff would commence his case by going to the royal Chancery and purchasing a writ commanding the defendant to come before the courts and explain why he had done such-and-such a thing against the plaintiff’s rights. The Latin phrases used by the Chancery clerks who filled out the writs – and which the royal courts insisted on when hearing a case – came to define individual forms of action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
