<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chapter 1 on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chapter 1 on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Locke&#39;s Second Treatise on Government
</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/locke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/locke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether we consider natural reason, which tells us, that men, being once born, have a right to their preservation, and consequently to meat and drink, and such other things as nature affords for their subsistence: or revelation, which gives us an account of those grants God made of the world to Adam, and to Noah, and his sons, it is very clear, that God, as king David says, Psal. cxv. 16. has given the earth to the children of men; given it to mankind in common. But this being supposed, it seems to some a very great difficulty, how any one should ever come to have a property in any thing: I will not content myself to answer, that if it be difficult to make out property, upon a supposition that God gave the world to Adam, and his posterity in common, it is impossible that any man, but one universal monarch, should have any property upon a supposition, that God gave the world to Adam, and his heirs in succession, exclusive of all the rest of his posterity. But I shall endeavour to shew, how men might come to have a property in several parts of that which God gave to mankind in common, and that without any express compact of all the commoners.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on Relative Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/relativity-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/relativity-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our case study this week asks you to consider both conventional and critical perspectives on the significance of moving from possession to title, in the context of land in African Nova Scotian communities. To better understand the legal groundwork for this debate, we now return to the basic question of what rights are afforded to someone in possession of land but who lacks formal title. &lt;em&gt;Asher v Whitlock&lt;/em&gt;, below, engages the issue of what happens when two claimants—neither of whom hold title—make competing claims to land. In the course of answering that question, the Court elaborates on the rights of parties in possession. Because of the style in which some mid-nineteenth century law reports were written—presenting the lawyers at trial in dialogue with the judges, followed by the court&amp;rsquo;s final judgement—&lt;em&gt;Asher&lt;/em&gt; also provides an opportunity to reconnect with ideas about patterns of common law argument that we addressed in Unit 1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Armorie v Delamirie</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/armorie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/armorie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;pratt-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Pratt, C.J. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#pratt-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff, being a chimney sweeper&amp;rsquo;s boy, found a jewel, and carried it to the defendant&amp;rsquo;s shop, (who was a goldsmith,) to know what it was, and delivered it into the hands of an apprentice, who, under pretense of weighing it, took out the stones; and, calling to the master to let him know if it came to three half-pence, the master offered the boy the money, who refused to take it, and insisted to have the thing again; whereupon the apprentice delivered him back the socket without the stones. And now in trover against the master these points were ruled:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clift v Kane</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/clift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/clift/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;hoyles-cj--&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Hoyles C.J.  —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#hoyles-cj--&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was an action in trover brought to recover the value of a thousand seals, alleged by the plaintiffs to have been wrongfully taken from the crew of their vessel, the Brothers, at the ice in the spring of 1869, by the defendants, Kane and his crew, and subsequently sold by Kane to the other defendants, Baine, Johnston &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The facts of this case, so far as it is necessary to refer to them for the determination of the questions now under consideration, are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pierson v Post</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/pierson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/pierson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;tompkins-j-majority-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Tompkins, J. (majority) &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#tompkins-j-majority-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This cause comes before us on a return to a &lt;em&gt;certiorari&lt;/em&gt; directed to one&#xA;of the justices of &lt;em&gt;Queens&lt;/em&gt; county.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question submitted by the counsel in this cause for our&#xA;determination is, whether &lt;em&gt;Lodowick Post,&lt;/em&gt; by the pursuit with his&#xA;hounds in the manner alleged in his declaration, acquired such a right&#xA;to, or property in, the fox, as will sustain an action against &lt;em&gt;Pierson&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;for killing and taking him away?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Popov v Hayashi</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/popov/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/popov/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/af4dRPV_dUc?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mccarthy-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McCarthy J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mccarthy-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;facts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Facts&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#facts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1927, Babe Ruth hit sixty home runs. That record stood for thirty four years until Roger Maris broke it in 1961 with sixty one home runs. Mark McGwire hit seventy in 1998. On October 7, 2001, at PacBell Park in San Francisco, Barry Bonds hit number seventy three. That accomplishment set a record which, in all probability, will remain unbroken for years into the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Possession&#34; from an Indigenous Worldview</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/indigenous-worldview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/indigenous-worldview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The common law approach to possession and communicating possession is not a universal one. Notice how James (sákéj) Youngblood Henderson inverts the common law&amp;rsquo;s concept of &amp;ldquo;possession&amp;rdquo; as he describes an Indigenous conception of belonging &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; land. In addition, consider the way Henderson engages with some of the common law rationales for property rights regimes we looked at previously&amp;hellip; &lt;!--this idea probably needs to be expanded or made more specific but I wasn&#39;t sure how to do it without knowing how we&#39;ll describe the rationales.--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abandonment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/abandonment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/abandonment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just as it is possible to acquire property by first possession, property rights can also be &amp;ldquo;given up&amp;rdquo; through a processes called &lt;em&gt;abandonment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abandonment occurs when property&amp;ndash;once established by possession or other legal means&amp;ndash;is voluntarily given up by the owner. As the quoted passage above notes, abandonment requires the owner to demonstrate an express &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; to permanently abandon their property rights: they must have “the intention of terminating ownership, possession and control.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adverse Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/adverse-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/adverse-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adverse possession is an unusual common law doctrine. We have already emphasized the point that legal possession and legal title are distinctive concepts. In general, &amp;ldquo;mere possession&amp;rdquo; does not disturb the legal title of the landowner, but the doctrine of adverse possession creates a dramatic exception to this rule. Under the doctrine, when a person has been in possession of land for longer than a period established by statute (called the &lt;em&gt;limitation period&lt;/em&gt;), they may become the title holder—and the original title holder may end up with nothing. The ultimate effect of adverse possession is to take title out of the hands of the original owner and to put that title into the hands of the person in possession.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asher v Whitlock </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/asher/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/asher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the trial before Cockburn, C.J., at the last Bedfordshire Spring Assizes, the following facts appeared in evidence. About Michaelmas, in the year 1842, Thomas Williamson inclosed from the waste of a manor a piece of land by the side of the highway; and in 1850, he inclosed more land adjoining, and built a cottage; the whole being the land as described and claimed in the writ. He occupied the whole till his death in 1860. By his will he devised the whole property, describing it as &amp;ldquo;a cottage and garden, in Keysoe Row, in which I now dwell,&amp;rdquo; to his wife Lucy Williamson, for and during so much only of her natural life as she might remain his widow and unmarried; and from and after her decease, or second marriage, whichever event might first happen, to his only child Mary Ann Williamson, in fee. After the death of Thomas Williamson, his widow remained in possession with the daughter, and in April, 1861, married the defendant; and from that time they all three resided on the property till the death of the daughter, aged eighteen years, in February, 1863. On her death, the defendant and his wife, the widow of the testator, continued to reside on the premises; the widow died in May, 1863, and the defendant still continued to occupy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Interpretation of the 1752 Treaty</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/interpretation-1752-treaty/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/interpretation-1752-treaty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1928, Grand Chief Gabriel Syliboy was charged and ultimately convicted of hunting muskrats out of season on Unamaki (Cape Breton). Justice Patterson&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of the 1752 treaty in &lt;em&gt;R v Syliboy&lt;/em&gt;—though ultimately rejected by Canadian courts—would stand as an authoritative common law precedent for many years to come. The decision would influence relationships between Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq peoples and the Crown long after it was issued. As William Wicken notes:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In approaching treaties signed with Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq peoples, federal and provincial governments have ignored community perspectives and reinforced Judge Patterson&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint of treaty-making. Though treaty issues have been before the courts on numerous occasions over the past sixty years, scant attention has been focused on how the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq understood treaties both at their signing and afterward. A 1974 memorandum, for instance, sent by Nova Scotia&amp;rsquo;s deputy Attorney-General, to the president of the Union of Nova Scotia Indians noted that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Treaty Relationships</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaties-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaties-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week we studied the historical roots of the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title and saw, in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt;, how classical legal thought framed the courts&amp;rsquo; conclusion that Indigenous land rights were &amp;ldquo;personal&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;proprietary&amp;rdquo;. We left off with the observation that beneath the issue of Aboriginal title foregrounded in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt; was the doctrine of &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;ldquo;land belonging to no one&amp;rdquo;). Aspects of &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt;—paired with the doctrine of discovery—undergird courts&amp;rsquo; continued assumption of Crown sovereignty and the exclusion of Indigenous sovereignties up to the present day. One consequence of this doctrine has been to largely exclude Indigenous legal orders from the consciousness of the common law.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keefer v Arillotta</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/keefer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/keefer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wilson-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Wilson, J.A. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#wilson-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an appeal from an order of His Honour Judge Nicholls holding that the respondents had acquired a possessory title to a portion of the appellants’ land subject to an easement remaining in the appellants.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The facts are more fully set out in the reasons for judgment of the learned trial Judge but the more significant ones for purposes of this appeal may be summarized under the following headings:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kosicki v Toronto (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/kosicki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/kosicki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sossin-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Sossin J.A. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#sossin-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Overview&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#overview&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Can private landowners gain title over municipal parkland through&#xA;adverse possession? This is the central question raised on this appeal.&#xA;The application judge answered this question by finding that municipal&#xA;parkland is immune to adverse possession. While I would not accept such&#xA;an immunity arises at common law, I conclude the application judge was&#xA;correct in finding that the municipal parkland at issue in this case was&#xA;not available for adverse possession. For the reasons that follow, I&#xA;would dismiss the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessees of Lawson et al v Whitman</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/lawson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/lawson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;halliburton-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Halliburton, C.J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#halliburton-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appeared at the trial that the land in dispute was included in a grant which was made to Jonathan Belcher in 1773, which the lessees of the plaintiff claim by several mesne conveyances.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The case therefore rests upon the defendant&amp;rsquo;s claim under the statutes of Limitation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appears that in the year 1784 a grant passed to William Sutherland, and several other grantees bounded to the south upon the north line of the Belcher grant; but it is quite clear that instead of the south line of Sutherland&amp;rsquo;s grant, having been laid out upon the ground on the north line of the Belcher grant, it was placed upwards of a mile to the south of it, and that possession according to that line has been held by those claiming under Sutherland&amp;rsquo;s grant for more than double the number of years requisite to give a title under the statute. This was indeed so far admitted at the argument that the plaintiffs did not claim to dispossess the defendant of that part of the land which he had actually cultivated and occupied, but as he had defended for a portion of it which was still in a wilderness state, they contended that they were entitled to a verdict for that. The defendant, however, contends that as the deeds under which he claims, contain the uncultivated as well as the cultivated land, and he or those under whom he claims have held by those deeds for upwards of 50 years that he is entitled to retain both.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mi&#39;kmaw Land Tenure</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/mikmaw-land-tenure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/mikmaw-land-tenure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Court in &lt;em&gt;Syliboy&lt;/em&gt; deployed each of the core themes of colonialism in property law we introduced in Week 1 in order to interpret the 1752 Peace and Friendship Treaty. The &lt;em&gt;Syliboy&lt;/em&gt; decision provided a deeply problematic footing on which to set the common law&amp;rsquo;s understanding of treaty rights and in some significant ways tracked the developing common law doctrine of Aboriginal title. But despite the &lt;em&gt;Syliboy&lt;/em&gt; decision&amp;rsquo;s long influence on treaty interpretation in Mi&amp;rsquo;kma&amp;rsquo;ki, in its aftermath Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw jurists continued to offer alternative interpretations grounded in the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw legal order and worldview.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Netukulimk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/netukulimk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/netukulimk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw legal traditions and Netukulimk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq and the forest ecosystem is more intimate than suggested in court. It is foundational to their worldview, integral to their legal traditions, and constitutional rights. This evidence was not before the courts, but it would have been useful to the courts if properly presented as part of Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq constitutional law, as well as the foundation of aboriginal and treaty rights as constitutional law of Canada. The relationship between the forest and Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq people is deeply embodied in the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq knowledge system and legal traditions, a relationship beginning with the Creation story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peace and Friendship Treaties</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/peace-and-friendship-treaties/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/peace-and-friendship-treaties/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The early eighteenth-century in what is today Eastern Canada was characterized by political and military struggles and alliances between three powers in the region: the Wabanaki (a political alliance of Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw, Wolastoqiyik, and Passamaquoddy peoples, and a separate alliance of communities known as the Abenaki), the British, and the French. 1726 saw the end of a three-year war between New England and the Wabanaki, which had been grounded in concerns about colonial expansion northward (including incursions on Indigenous fishing territories and colonial land settlement). In turn, the British were becoming increasingly motivated to forge friendly relationships with the Wabanaki as counter-weight to French power. This period culminated in the signing of the Treaty of 1725 by various parties between that year and 1726.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peace and Friendship Treaty (1725)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1725/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1725/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;This treaty—the first in a line of treaties entered into by the British and Indigenous nations in the Atlantic region—was first signed in Boston in 1725. The same treaty was signed with different Indigenous parties one year later in 1726.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ratification-of-1725-treaty&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ratification of 1725 Treaty&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ratification-of-1725-treaty&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Articles of Submission &amp;amp; Agreements made at Boston in New England by Sanguaarum alias Loron, Arexus Francois Xavier and Meganumbe Delegates from Penobscott Naudgevaek S. Johns Cape Sables and Other Tribes Inhabiting within His Majesties Territories of Nova Scotia and New England __________&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peace and Friendship Treaty (1752)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1752/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1752/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-alert&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div&gt;&#xA;      &lt;em&gt;The following text is quoted in R v Simon, [1985] 2 SCR 387 at para 6.&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treaty or Articles of Peace and Friendship Renewed between His Excellency Peregrine Thomas Hopson Esquire Captain General and Governor in Chief in and over His Majesty&amp;rsquo;s Province of Nova Scotia or Acadie. Vice Admiral of the same &amp;amp; Colonel of one of His Majesty&amp;rsquo;s Regiments of Foot, and His Majesty&amp;rsquo;s Council on behalf of His Majesty and Major Jean Baptiste Cope, chief Sachem of the Tribe of Mick Mack Indians Inhabiting the Eastern Coast of the said Province, and Andrew Hadley Martin, Gabriel Martin &amp;amp; Francis Jeremiah, Members and Delegates of the said Tribe, for themselves and their said Tribe their Heirs, and the Heirs of their Heirs forever, Begun made and concluded in the manner, form and Tenor following, vizt:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piper v Stevenson</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/piper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/piper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;clute-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Clute J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#clute-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff claims as owner and occupier of lots 28 and 29, block &amp;ldquo;A,&amp;rdquo; Marmot street, North Toronto, registered plan No. 722, and asks an injunction restraining the defendant from trespass and for damages for former trespass and forcible entry. The defendant denies that the plaintiff is the owner of the lots in question, and says that he purchased the same from the registered owner thereof, and thereupon entered into possession of the same and built a fence thereon and planted a crop, which are the trespasses complained of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R v Syliboy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/syliboy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/syliboy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;patterson-acting-co-ct-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Patterson (Acting) Co. Ct. J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#patterson-acting-co-ct-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The defendant, who is the grand chief of the Mick Macks of Nova Scotia was convicted under the Lands and Forests Act, 1926 (N.S.), c. 4, of having in his possession at Askilton in the County of Inverness on November 4, last fifteen green pelts, fourteen muskrat and one fox. He made no attempt to deny having the pelts, indeed frankly admits having them, but claims that as an Indian he is not bound by the provisions of the Act, but has by Treaty the right to hunt and trap at all times. Every now and then for a number of years one has heard that our Indians were making these claims but, so far as I know, the matter has never been before a Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terra Nullius</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/terra-nullius/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/terra-nullius/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terra nullius&lt;/em&gt; is a term that refers to a “territory without a master.” It is a term used in public international law to describe a space that can be inhabited but that does not belong to a state, meaning the land is not owned by anyone. In fact, when a State or an entity describes a land as a &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt;, the land is in reality occupied – by a nation or a minority – but the term has oftentimes been used in order to legitimize state occupation and colonization. In international public law, when the definition &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt; is given to a land, it can legally legitimize its occupation and acquisition of sovereignty by another nation, under the doctrine of discovery, which the International Court of Justice (ICJ) has approved as a legal method of acquisition of territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wildlife Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/wildlife/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/wildlife/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--2(w) “fur-bearing animal” means beaver, muskrat, red squir- rel, mink, otter, skunk, weasel, fisher, marten, lynx, bobcat, cougar, fox, coyote, raccoon and any other non-domesticated animal which may be designated as a fur-bearing animal by the Governor in Coun- cil, and includes any part of such animal, but does not include bear or snowshoe hare;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4 (1) Subject to subsection (2), the property in all wildlife situate within the Province, while in a state of nature, is hereby declared to be vested in Her Majesty in right of the Province and no person shall acquire any right or property therein otherwise than in accordance with this Act and the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
