<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Possession on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/possession/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Possession on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/possession/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Locke&#39;s Second Treatise on Government
</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/locke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/locke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether we consider natural reason, which tells us, that men, being once born, have a right to their preservation, and consequently to meat and drink, and such other things as nature affords for their subsistence: or revelation, which gives us an account of those grants God made of the world to Adam, and to Noah, and his sons, it is very clear, that God, as king David says, Psal. cxv. 16. has given the earth to the children of men; given it to mankind in common. But this being supposed, it seems to some a very great difficulty, how any one should ever come to have a property in any thing: I will not content myself to answer, that if it be difficult to make out property, upon a supposition that God gave the world to Adam, and his posterity in common, it is impossible that any man, but one universal monarch, should have any property upon a supposition, that God gave the world to Adam, and his heirs in succession, exclusive of all the rest of his posterity. But I shall endeavour to shew, how men might come to have a property in several parts of that which God gave to mankind in common, and that without any express compact of all the commoners.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on Relative Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/relativity-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/relativity-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our case study this week asks you to consider both conventional and critical perspectives on the significance of moving from possession to title, in the context of land in African Nova Scotian communities. To better understand the legal groundwork for this debate, we now return to the basic question of what rights are afforded to someone in possession of land but who lacks formal title. &lt;em&gt;Asher v Whitlock&lt;/em&gt;, below, engages the issue of what happens when two claimants—neither of whom hold title—make competing claims to land. In the course of answering that question, the Court elaborates on the rights of parties in possession. Because of the style in which some mid-nineteenth century law reports were written—presenting the lawyers at trial in dialogue with the judges, followed by the court&amp;rsquo;s final judgement—&lt;em&gt;Asher&lt;/em&gt; also provides an opportunity to reconnect with ideas about patterns of common law argument that we addressed in Unit 1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clift v Kane</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/clift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/clift/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;hoyles-cj--&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Hoyles C.J.  —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#hoyles-cj--&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was an action in trover brought to recover the value of a thousand seals, alleged by the plaintiffs to have been wrongfully taken from the crew of their vessel, the Brothers, at the ice in the spring of 1869, by the defendants, Kane and his crew, and subsequently sold by Kane to the other defendants, Baine, Johnston &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The facts of this case, so far as it is necessary to refer to them for the determination of the questions now under consideration, are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pierson v Post</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/pierson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/pierson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;tompkins-j-majority-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Tompkins, J. (majority) &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#tompkins-j-majority-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This cause comes before us on a return to a &lt;em&gt;certiorari&lt;/em&gt; directed to one&#xA;of the justices of &lt;em&gt;Queens&lt;/em&gt; county.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question submitted by the counsel in this cause for our&#xA;determination is, whether &lt;em&gt;Lodowick Post,&lt;/em&gt; by the pursuit with his&#xA;hounds in the manner alleged in his declaration, acquired such a right&#xA;to, or property in, the fox, as will sustain an action against &lt;em&gt;Pierson&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;for killing and taking him away?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Popov v Hayashi</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/popov/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/popov/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/af4dRPV_dUc?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mccarthy-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McCarthy J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mccarthy-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;facts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Facts&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#facts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1927, Babe Ruth hit sixty home runs. That record stood for thirty four years until Roger Maris broke it in 1961 with sixty one home runs. Mark McGwire hit seventy in 1998. On October 7, 2001, at PacBell Park in San Francisco, Barry Bonds hit number seventy three. That accomplishment set a record which, in all probability, will remain unbroken for years into the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abandonment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/abandonment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/abandonment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just as it is possible to acquire property by first possession, property rights can also be &amp;ldquo;given up&amp;rdquo; through a processes called &lt;em&gt;abandonment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abandonment occurs when property&amp;ndash;once established by possession or other legal means&amp;ndash;is voluntarily given up by the owner. As the quoted passage above notes, abandonment requires the owner to demonstrate an express &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; to permanently abandon their property rights: they must have “the intention of terminating ownership, possession and control.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asher v Whitlock </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/asher/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/asher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the trial before Cockburn, C.J., at the last Bedfordshire Spring Assizes, the following facts appeared in evidence. About Michaelmas, in the year 1842, Thomas Williamson inclosed from the waste of a manor a piece of land by the side of the highway; and in 1850, he inclosed more land adjoining, and built a cottage; the whole being the land as described and claimed in the writ. He occupied the whole till his death in 1860. By his will he devised the whole property, describing it as &amp;ldquo;a cottage and garden, in Keysoe Row, in which I now dwell,&amp;rdquo; to his wife Lucy Williamson, for and during so much only of her natural life as she might remain his widow and unmarried; and from and after her decease, or second marriage, whichever event might first happen, to his only child Mary Ann Williamson, in fee. After the death of Thomas Williamson, his widow remained in possession with the daughter, and in April, 1861, married the defendant; and from that time they all three resided on the property till the death of the daughter, aged eighteen years, in February, 1863. On her death, the defendant and his wife, the widow of the testator, continued to reside on the premises; the widow died in May, 1863, and the defendant still continued to occupy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wildlife Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/wildlife/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/wildlife/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--2(w) “fur-bearing animal” means beaver, muskrat, red squir- rel, mink, otter, skunk, weasel, fisher, marten, lynx, bobcat, cougar, fox, coyote, raccoon and any other non-domesticated animal which may be designated as a fur-bearing animal by the Governor in Coun- cil, and includes any part of such animal, but does not include bear or snowshoe hare;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4 (1) Subject to subsection (2), the property in all wildlife situate within the Province, while in a state of nature, is hereby declared to be vested in Her Majesty in right of the Province and no person shall acquire any right or property therein otherwise than in accordance with this Act and the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
