<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Covenants on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/covenants/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Covenants on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/covenants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Noble et al v Alley</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/noble/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/noble/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This case addressed a discriminatory restrictive covenant attached to land forming part of a summer resort development called the Beach O&amp;rsquo;Pines. The covenant, in clause (f), prohibited the sale, transfer or lease of the land to, or use or occupancy by, individuals of Jewish &amp;ldquo;race or blood&amp;rdquo; or people of colour, and expressed an intention to restrict ownership of land in the resort development to &amp;ldquo;persons of the white or Caucasian race not excluded by this clause.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re Drummond Wren</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/drummond/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/drummond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mackay-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Mackay J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mackay-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an application brought by Drummond Wren, owner of certain lands registered in the Registry Office for the County of York, to have declared invalid a restrictive covenant assumed by him when he purchased these lands and which he agreed to exact from his assigns, namely, — “Land not to be sold to Jews or persons of objectionable nationality.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The application is made by way of special leave and pursuant to s. 60 of the &lt;em&gt;Conveyancing and Law of Property Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.O. 1937, c. 152, and Rules 603 and 604 of The Rules of Practice and Procedure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictive Covenants and Public Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/covenants-public-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/covenants-public-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Certain &amp;ldquo;private&amp;rdquo; forms of land-use regulation are still in widespread use. One of the most pervasive—but often least noticed—is the &lt;em&gt;restrictive covenant&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From one point of view, restrictive covenants look like a fairly straightforward promise by one landowner to another—a promise to refrain from doing something on one&amp;rsquo;s own land. One landowner might promise not to cut down the trees in their yard, for example, or promise not to paint their house a garish shade of bright green. But from a legal perspective, restrictive covenants are much more than this. Not only do covenants represent a sort of contractual promise between parties, they help to define the durable &amp;ldquo;bundle of rights&amp;rdquo; in the land itself—that is, covenants are said to &lt;em&gt;run with the land&lt;/em&gt; and can, at least in theory, long outlast the original parties to the covenant. This possibility raises some difficult questions for courts in how they define the basic character of covenants along with their consequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sources of Public Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/public-policy-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/public-policy-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the more remarkable aspects of the decision in &lt;em&gt;Re Drummond Wren&lt;/em&gt; is its reliance on different sources of domestic and international law to ground the Court&amp;rsquo;s finding that the restrictive covenant in issue was contrary to public policy. As you analyze the &lt;em&gt;3000 Funston Street&lt;/em&gt; problem for this week, consider what role the following sources might play.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Article 11 of the United Nations General Assembly&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights&lt;/em&gt; (1966) recognizes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tulk v Moxhay </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/tulk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/tulk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the year 1808 the Plaintiff, being then the owner in fee of the vacant piece of ground in Leicester Square, as well as of several of the houses forming the Square, sold the piece of ground by the description of &amp;ldquo;Leicester Square garden or pleasure ground, with the equestrian statue then standing in the centre thereof, and the iron railing and stone work round the same,&amp;rdquo; to one Elms in fee: and the deed of conveyance contained a covenant by Elms, for himself, his heirs, and assigns, with the Plaintiff, his heirs, executors, and administrators, &amp;ldquo;that Elms, his heirs, and assigns should, and would from time to time, and at all times thereafter at his and their own costs and charges, keep and maintain the said piece of ground and square garden, and the iron railing round the same in its then form, and in sufficient and proper repair as a square garden and pleasure ground, in an open state, uncovered with any buildings, in neat and ornamental order; and that it should be lawful for the inhabitants of Leicester Square, tenants of the Plaintiff, on payment of a reasonable rent for the same, to have keys at their own expense and the privilege of admission therewith at any time or times into the said square garden and pleasure ground.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
