<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About the Casebook on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About the Casebook on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Course Syllabus</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/admin/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/admin/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This document is the official course syllabus for &lt;em&gt;Property in its Historical Context&lt;/em&gt; (LAWS 1015/25), Section B, in the 2024-2025 academic year. The course is taught by Professor Jamie Baxter at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dal.ca/faculty/law.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;Schulich School of Law&lt;/a&gt;, Dalhousie University.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-information&#34;&gt;&#xA;  General Information&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#general-information&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;contact-details&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Contact Details&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#contact-details&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;strong&gt;contact me by e-mail&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:jamie.baxter@dal.ca&#34; &gt;jamie.baxter@dal.ca&lt;/a&gt;) about all matters related to the course. My office is &lt;strong&gt;Weldon 326&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;administration&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Administration&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#administration&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Information about course requirements and procedures can be found in this document and the in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/admin/schedule/&#34; &gt;Course Schedule&lt;/a&gt;. Both of these documents are available in the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/admin/&#34; &gt;Admin&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; section of the course website.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to the Course</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For first-year law students, &amp;ldquo;property&amp;rdquo; can be a kaleidoscopic subject: fragmentary, blinkered, disorienting. As one (among many) possible ways of mediating our relationships with and in respect of land and other &amp;ldquo;things&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;both corporeal and not&amp;ndash;property offers up a disorderly patchwork of principles, rules and norms. It is full of contradictions, real and apparent. It presents a space of dispossession and disadvantage for some, prosperity and security for others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are likewise many ways to teach and learn about property, to try to make sense of and bring some order within the kaleidoscope. In this course, we will approach the subject from a historical perspective–one that puts the critical emphasis on the role of land relationships in Canada’s political economy as the legal ground that determines so much about who benefits from the economic system and who does not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protest at West Eggleston</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/protest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/protest/</guid>
      <description>This hypothetical problem involves a group of protestors charged under section 4 of Nova Scotia&amp;rsquo;s Protection of Property Act, RSNS 1989, c 363. Please read the facts carefully, followed by the linked reading material, and think about whether or not a court would be likely to find that the protestors are &amp;lsquo;guilty of an offence&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;liable to a fine of not more than five hundred dollars.&amp;rsquo;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Course Schedule</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/admin/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/admin/schedule/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the official course schedule. Please note that the schedule is subject to change. Visit this page for the most recent course information.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Week&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Dates&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Lesson&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Readings&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recognition, Relationships and Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;animals&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Animals&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#animals&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Allen Greer suggests that early legal encounters between Indigenous peoples and European imperialists in North America were much more concerned with imperial and commercial concerns rather than land settlement per se. Central to this context was the hunting and trading of wild animals. Much of the property law of the time was shaped in this context of encounter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tina Loo observes that Blackstone&amp;rsquo;s view that wild animals were common property, open to anyone for the taking, was embraced by early colonists in North America, particularly in the Thirteen Colonies. Hunting was framed as an expression of fundamental freedom by colonists and contrasted with Old World restrictions. Colonists in British North America were more permissive of wildlife regulations that curbed hunting access [@loo2006StatesNature, 13-14].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wowkwis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/wowkwis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/wowkwis/</guid>
      <description>This hypothetical problem involves a dispute over legal entitlements to a wild animal pelt in the aftermath of fox hunt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAQ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/admin/faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/admin/faq/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This page addresses &amp;ldquo;Frequently Asked Questions&amp;rdquo; about using the &lt;em&gt;Land+Property&lt;/em&gt; casebook.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-i-need-to-read-the-material-online-using-my-computer&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Do I need to read the material online using my computer?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#do-i-need-to-read-the-material-online-using-my-computer&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to successfully review and prepare the weekly assigned readings, you will need to access the casebook via a browser on your computer. Because of the unique problem-based, hypertext model used in the casebook, this way of accessing the material allows you to draw connections between the readings by following different pathways (links).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Wolastoqey Title Claim</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/wolastoqey-claim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/wolastoqey-claim/</guid>
      <description>This problem addresses the ongoing title claim by the Wolastoqey Nation its traditional territory encompassing much of modern day New Brunswick, along with the Province&amp;rsquo;s developing response to that claim.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Title as Recognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-legal-imprimatur-of-title&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Legal Imprimatur of Title&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-legal-imprimatur-of-title&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So far in our course we have discussed the central role of possession in Anglo-Canadian law and its complex connections to ownership and title going back to early liberal theory. But to date, we have not talked much about what these terms of &amp;ldquo;ownership and &amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo; really mean. Our goal this week is a more thorough understanding of title and its various forms&amp;ndash;with a focus on the history and context surrounding the common law doctrine of &amp;ldquo;Aboriginal title&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GMOs in West Egg</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/gmos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/gmos/</guid>
      <description>This hypo concerns a market gardener&amp;rsquo;s attempts to prevent pollination of their crops from GMO varieties grown by a neighbouring farmer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuisance and the Right to Exclude</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;property-and-exclusion&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Property and Exclusion&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#property-and-exclusion&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks we have been focused on how classical legal thought addressed questions of possession and title. We now turn to a second prominent topic&amp;ndash;one that mainly addresses the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt; of property rights held by owners or those in possession.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One right in particular, some argue, is fundamental to private property: the &lt;em&gt;right to exclude&lt;/em&gt; others from interfering with the owner&amp;rsquo;s use and enjoyment of their land, other tangible things and even intangibles like knowledge goods. The common law has devised several remedies to enforce owners&amp;rsquo; right to exclude. We have already seen one example: in &lt;em&gt;Harrison v Carswell&lt;/em&gt;, the mall owner brought an action in &lt;em&gt;trespass&lt;/em&gt; against the picketer Sophie Carswell to exclude her from the mall sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excluding the State</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;property-and-exclusion-of-public-authority&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Property and &amp;ldquo;Exclusion&amp;rdquo; of Public Authority&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#property-and-exclusion-of-public-authority&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Last week, we saw that claims in nuisance are one legal tool used by property owners—with mixed success—to stop their neighbours from adversely affecting the use and enjoyment of the owner&amp;rsquo;s land. Nuisance, in other words, is one means to exclude others from doing something that limits owners&amp;rsquo; freedom related to property. This means of exclusion, however, unavoidably limits the freedom of others to use their land as they choose. In these cases, the courts must decide whose rights should win out and in doing so address the fundamental dilemma of conflicting freedoms inherent in legal liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>After the West Egg Protest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/protest-after/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/protest-after/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the events of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/problems/protest/&#34; &gt;protest at West Eggleston&lt;/a&gt;, some MLAs and their allies began to pressure the provincial government to expand access to places where members of the public can engage in peaceful protest and other forms of collective association. As a result of these efforts, the legislature passed an amendment to the &lt;em&gt;Public Highways Act&lt;/em&gt;, RSNS 1989, c 371 which reads:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;5A Where members of the public are exercising their freedom of collective association on roads, lanes, paths or highways, the provisions of the &lt;em&gt;Protection of Property Act&lt;/em&gt;, RSNS 1989, c 363 are of no force or effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alienation, Exit and Control</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having now studied some of the historical basis for problems of &lt;em&gt;recognition&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;exclusion&lt;/em&gt;, this week we move on to examine the context of &lt;em&gt;exit&lt;/em&gt;: how owners transfer their rights in land and thereby disentangle themselves (wholly or partially) from property relations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Central to this context are persistent tensions between an owner&amp;rsquo;s right to &lt;em&gt;alienate&lt;/em&gt; property and their power to place restrictions on future owners&amp;rsquo; rights to do the same. As we will see, courts often put a heavy emphasis on the free alienability of land. Any attempts to restrict free alienability are viewed with considerable skepticism in the classical style—consistent with the liberal ideal that property rights should support individuals to pursue their own ends. We will read cases in which the courts scrutinize clauses in a will that purport to limit how or when beneficiaries under that will can transfer the property interests they receive. We will also examine the context of restrictive covenants in land.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mid-Term Rapid Review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/review01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/review01/</guid>
      <description>We will use our time in class to do a help identify key gaps in your knowledge and understanding so far this term. To that end, I have provided a list of &amp;ldquo;rapid review&amp;rdquo; questions for you to read and consider. I don’t suggest that you address them all in full detail. Instead, read each and consider your answer for no more than a minute or two. You can come back to these questions in more detail as part of your exam preparation&amp;ndash;their purpose at this point is only to provide a check on what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far and to help you to discover where you can most effectively focus your studying.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restraining Alienation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/bequest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/bequest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recall from our first problem this term, &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/problems/protest/&#34; &gt;protest at West Eggleston&lt;/a&gt;, that the community has been experiencing significant changes in the past few years. Rising housing price across the province have increased demand for land in West Egg dramatically. With its idyllic setting along the coast, several of the co-operative&amp;rsquo;s founding members worried that their community had lost sight of its roots in affordable housing and would eventually become nothing more than another tony suburb for wealthy. As we saw in our earlier problem, these dynamics had already begun to fracture the community and raised mounting concerns about exclusion and discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trusts, Property, and Citizenship</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our final week of new material in the course for this term we will turn our minds to the concept of the &amp;ldquo;trust&amp;rdquo; and examine its features by looking at the history of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.project44.ca/japanese-canadian-internment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;dispossession and internment of Japanese Canadians&lt;/a&gt; during the second world war. The targeting of Japanese Canadians living in British Columbia as &amp;ldquo;enemy aliens&amp;rdquo; remains one of the least-discussed examples of state-executed systematic racism in Canada&amp;rsquo;s history. In exploring this history, we will also begin to encounter the mid-century transition toward a new grammar of Anglo-Canadian legal thought: the modern style. As we will see, this period of Canadian history also has something important to tell us about the connection between property, ownership and citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Letter to the Prime Minister</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/takahashi-letter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/takahashi-letter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1944, Toyo Takahashi, a Japanese Canadian woman, wrote the following letter to Prime Minister William Lyon Mackenzie King, protesting the forced sale of her home in Victoria, British Columbia under the wartime legal regime that had emerged to dispossess Japanese Canadians of their property and &amp;ldquo;liquidate&amp;rdquo; their belongings:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear Sir:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Director of the Office of the Custodian in Vancouver has notified us of your policy of liquidation of Japanese property. Because of this policy my property has now been catalogued for sale. This liquidation is against your promises, and my wishes, furthermore it is utterly undeserved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-of-Term Rapid Review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/review02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/review02/</guid>
      <description>We will use our time in class to do a help identify key gaps in your knowledge and understanding in the course this term, with an emphasis on the weeks since our last review. To that end, I have provided a list of &amp;ldquo;rapid review&amp;rdquo; questions for you to read and consider. I don’t suggest that you address them all in full detail. Instead, read each and consider your answer for no more than a minute or two. You can come back to these questions in more detail as part of your exam preparation&amp;ndash;their purpose at this point is only to provide a check on what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far and to help you to discover where you can most effectively focus your studying.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructive Takings and Acquired Rights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, will begin to revisit some of last term&amp;rsquo;s topics from the perspective of the modern style of Anglo-Canadian thought. Our primary focus this week will pick up on our discussion of constructive expropriation from the &lt;em&gt;McLaren v Caldwell&lt;/em&gt;. Recall that these cases involve claimed &amp;ldquo;takings&amp;rdquo; of property rights (or &amp;ldquo;sticks&amp;rdquo; from the ownership bundle) by the state, for which the owner would like to receive some form of compensation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flood on the Red River</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/flood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/flood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following hypothetical builds on a recent case before the Manitoba Court of Appeal,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which reports these facts:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A Maze in Corn Inc. operates a corn maze, petting zoo and haunted forest attraction (the business) on a property located on St. Mary&amp;rsquo;s Road, south of Winnipeg near St. Adolphe (the property). The property is located south of the gates of the Red River Floodway (the floodway).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Red River runs through the City of Winnipeg, which is located on the Red River flood plain. In years of unusually high water, the river overflows its banks and causes widespread flooding and sewer back-ups in Winnipeg, resulting in significant property damage and economic loss.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locke&#39;s Second Treatise on Government
</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/locke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/locke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether we consider natural reason, which tells us, that men, being once born, have a right to their preservation, and consequently to meat and drink, and such other things as nature affords for their subsistence: or revelation, which gives us an account of those grants God made of the world to Adam, and to Noah, and his sons, it is very clear, that God, as king David says, Psal. cxv. 16. has given the earth to the children of men; given it to mankind in common. But this being supposed, it seems to some a very great difficulty, how any one should ever come to have a property in any thing: I will not content myself to answer, that if it be difficult to make out property, upon a supposition that God gave the world to Adam, and his posterity in common, it is impossible that any man, but one universal monarch, should have any property upon a supposition, that God gave the world to Adam, and his heirs in succession, exclusive of all the rest of his posterity. But I shall endeavour to shew, how men might come to have a property in several parts of that which God gave to mankind in common, and that without any express compact of all the commoners.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Right to Shelter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/canada-homeless-population-health-data-halifax-1.6894448&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;accurate data&lt;/a&gt; on the circumstances of unhoused people can be difficult to get, Canada is clearly experiencing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://housing-infrastructure.canada.ca/homelessness-sans-abri/reports-rapports/data-shelter-2022-donnees-refuge-eng.html#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;rise in chronic homelessness&lt;/a&gt;, even as shelter capacity in many cities has increased following the COVID-19 pandemic. This has resulted in widespread sheltering in public spaces&amp;ndash;both temporary and longer-term&amp;ndash;in many Canadian cities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Addressing homelessness and access to housing engages a complex set of legal and policy issues, actors and decision-making networks. One aspect of this context in which Canadian courts have been especially active is the constitutional right of unhoused persons to access and shelter in public spaces&amp;ndash;namely, municipal &amp;ndash;in order to meet their immediate needs. The role of these rights and challenges to their realization have gained national attention from the circumstances in cities around the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sheltering in Public Spaces Bylaw</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/bylaw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/bylaw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the following model by-law regarding sheltering in public spaces:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Definitions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Unhoused Person&amp;rdquo; means a person who has neither a fixed address nor a predictable residence to return to on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“City Property” means any land located within the Municipality to which the Municipality holds title or to which the Municipality is otherwise in possession.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Temporary Shelter&amp;rdquo; means a tent, lean to or other form of shelter that is temporary and portable in nature that is constructed from nylon, plastic, cardboard or other similar non-rigid material, and that covers an area of less than ten (10) square meters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3000 Funston Street</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/funston-street/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/funston-street/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Please listen to this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kut.org/austin/2021-09-10/west-austin-affordable-housing-lawsuit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;NPR Radio documentary about 3000 Funston Street,&lt;/a&gt; a piece of vacant land in the Brykerwoods neighbourhood of Austin, Texas. The podcast tells the story of how a restrictive covenant is shaping urban development in the context of the city&amp;rsquo;s long-term strategy to improve access to affordable housing and achieve a more equitable distribution of that housing across the municipality. If you prefer, the website also contains a print version of the radio documentary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictive Covenants and Qualified Interests</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few weeks, we have emphasized that modern, forward-looking land use planning and zoning regimes emerged in Canada by the mid-20th century to replace more decentralized and reactive forms of land-use control, such as private nuisance actions adjudicated by the common law courts. But this story about the move from private enforcement to public land-use control needs to be complicated a little further. Certain conventional, “private” forms of land-use regulation are still in widespread use. One of the most pervasive—but often least noticed—is the restrictive covenant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mid-Term Rapid Review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/review03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/review03/</guid>
      <description>We will use our time in class to do a help identify key gaps in your knowledge and understanding in the course this term, with an emphasis on the weeks since our last review. To that end, I have provided a list of &amp;ldquo;rapid review&amp;rdquo; questions for you to read and consider. I don’t suggest that you address them all in full detail. Instead, read each and consider your answer for no more than a minute or two. You can come back to these questions in more detail as part of your exam preparation&amp;ndash;their purpose at this point is only to provide a check on what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far and to help you to discover where you can most effectively focus your studying.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shohei Ohtani&#39;s 50/50 Baseball</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/ohtani/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/ohtani/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Please review the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dal.brightspace.com/d2l/le/content/343528/viewContent/4794948/View&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&amp;ldquo;Complaint and Demand for Jury Trial&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;Maltus v Goldin&lt;/em&gt; litigation posted on Brigthspace, focusing on the background facts and on Counts I and II (the claims for an injunction and in conversion).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then watch the following excerpts of news coverage and video evidence from these events:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wNG82FcVhPc?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who has the better claim to Ohtani&amp;rsquo;s 50/50 baseball and what is the appropriate remedy in this case?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possession, Revisited</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we return, in part, to where we started our study of property law this year: the law of possession. Recall that John Locke&amp;rsquo;s labour theory of possession and property was an archetype of the classical style and has been a significant influence on common law principles in this area. We now want to understand how the common law&amp;rsquo;s approach to possession has evolved in the modern style.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Our Problem this Week&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our problem this week looks at how the law of possession continues to play a significant role in the world of major league baseball: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/problems/ohtani/&#34; &gt;Shohei Ohtani&amp;rsquo;s 50/50 Baseball&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Membertou&#39;s Transition to the First Nations Land Management Framework</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/membertou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/membertou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Please read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/indian-act-horrible-existence-senator-christmas-1.4149551&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;this CBC News article,&lt;/a&gt; in which former Senator Dan Christmas, the first Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw member of the Canadian Senate, describes challenges the Membertou First Nation has faced with respect to lands governance under the federal &lt;em&gt;Indian Act&lt;/em&gt; and how his community has responded to these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the article notes, Membertou has recently opted out of the lands-related provisions of the &lt;em&gt;Indian Act&lt;/em&gt; and opted into an alternative federal regime under the &lt;em&gt;First Nations Lands Management Act&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;FNLMA&lt;/em&gt;). This legislation was subsequently repealed in 2022 and replaced by the &lt;em&gt;Framework Agreement on First Nation Land Management Act&lt;/em&gt;, SC 2022, c 19 (&lt;em&gt;FAFNLMA&lt;/em&gt;). The &lt;em&gt;FAFNLMA&lt;/em&gt; gives effect to the Framework Agreement on First Nations Land Management, which empowers participating First Nations to create their own Land Code dealing with property and lands-related governance on their reserve lands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reserve Lands in Transition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the next two weeks, we return to the context of Indigenous lands and land relations. Last term, we began to understand the historical basis of treaty relationships and of the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title. We continue to these topics and start this week by focusing on the legal status of reserve lands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Our Problem this Week&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our problem this week looks at the adoption of a Land Code by the Membertou First Nation under the  the federal &lt;em&gt;Framework Agreement on First Nations Land Management&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/problems/membertou/&#34; &gt;Membertou&amp;rsquo;s Transition to the First Nations Land Management Framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Law Aboriginal Title</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, we complete our study of Indigenous land rights, with a focus on the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title. We have traced the evolution of that doctrine from the Royal Proclamation in 1763, through &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt; in the late nineteenth century and &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Guerin&lt;/em&gt; in the late twentieth century. The contemporary path of the Aboriginal title doctrine since those cases has been charted through a combination of constitutional reform, litigation in the courts, and negotiation between Indigenous nations and the Crown.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mi&#39;gmawe&#39;l Tplu&#39;taqnn Inc. Statement of Claim</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/mti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/mti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Please review this &lt;a href=&#34;https://dal.brightspace.com/d2l/le/content/343528/viewContent/4811532/View&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;Statement of Claim&lt;/a&gt; by Mi&amp;rsquo;gmawe&amp;rsquo;l Tplu&amp;rsquo;taqnn Inc. (MTI), representing eight Mi&amp;rsquo;gmaq First Nations in New Brunswick seeking a declaration of Mi&amp;rsquo;gmaq Title in their territorial lands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the legal framework under which the New Brunswick Court of Queen&amp;rsquo;s Bench will assess MTI&amp;rsquo;s claim? Based on the facts presented in the Statement of Claim, what key challenges or uncertainties might the claimants encounter under this framework?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The contemporary legal framework for &amp;ldquo;Aboriginal title&amp;rdquo; is complex and contains several elements that we have not yet encountered in our historical study of this area of law. Below is a map of the case materials to help you develop your understanding of this area of law with an eye toward addressing this week&amp;rsquo;s case study.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-of-Term Rapid Review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/review04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/review04/</guid>
      <description>We will use our time in class to do a help identify key gaps in your knowledge and understanding in the course this term, with an emphasis on the weeks since our last review. To that end, I have provided a list of &amp;ldquo;rapid review&amp;rdquo; questions for you to read and consider. I don’t suggest that you address them all in full detail. Instead, read each and consider your answer for no more than a minute or two. You can come back to these questions in more detail as part of your exam preparation&amp;ndash;their purpose at this point is only to provide a check on what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far and to help you to discover where you can most effectively focus your studying.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on Relative Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/relativity-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/relativity-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our case study this week asks you to consider both conventional and critical perspectives on the significance of moving from possession to title, in the context of land in African Nova Scotian communities. To better understand the legal groundwork for this debate, we now return to the basic question of what rights are afforded to someone in possession of land but who lacks formal title. &lt;em&gt;Asher v Whitlock&lt;/em&gt;, below, engages the issue of what happens when two claimants—neither of whom hold title—make competing claims to land. In the course of answering that question, the Court elaborates on the rights of parties in possession. Because of the style in which some mid-nineteenth century law reports were written—presenting the lawyers at trial in dialogue with the judges, followed by the court&amp;rsquo;s final judgement—&lt;em&gt;Asher&lt;/em&gt; also provides an opportunity to reconnect with ideas about patterns of common law argument that we addressed in Unit 1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Armorie v Delamirie</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/armorie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/armorie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;pratt-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Pratt, C.J. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#pratt-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff, being a chimney sweeper&amp;rsquo;s boy, found a jewel, and carried it to the defendant&amp;rsquo;s shop, (who was a goldsmith,) to know what it was, and delivered it into the hands of an apprentice, who, under pretense of weighing it, took out the stones; and, calling to the master to let him know if it came to three half-pence, the master offered the boy the money, who refused to take it, and insisted to have the thing again; whereupon the apprentice delivered him back the socket without the stones. And now in trover against the master these points were ruled:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clift v Kane</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/clift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/clift/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;hoyles-cj--&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Hoyles C.J.  —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#hoyles-cj--&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was an action in trover brought to recover the value of a thousand seals, alleged by the plaintiffs to have been wrongfully taken from the crew of their vessel, the Brothers, at the ice in the spring of 1869, by the defendants, Kane and his crew, and subsequently sold by Kane to the other defendants, Baine, Johnston &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The facts of this case, so far as it is necessary to refer to them for the determination of the questions now under consideration, are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pierson v Post</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/pierson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/pierson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;tompkins-j-majority-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Tompkins, J. (majority) &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#tompkins-j-majority-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This cause comes before us on a return to a &lt;em&gt;certiorari&lt;/em&gt; directed to one&#xA;of the justices of &lt;em&gt;Queens&lt;/em&gt; county.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question submitted by the counsel in this cause for our&#xA;determination is, whether &lt;em&gt;Lodowick Post,&lt;/em&gt; by the pursuit with his&#xA;hounds in the manner alleged in his declaration, acquired such a right&#xA;to, or property in, the fox, as will sustain an action against &lt;em&gt;Pierson&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;for killing and taking him away?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Popov v Hayashi</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/popov/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/popov/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/af4dRPV_dUc?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mccarthy-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McCarthy J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mccarthy-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;facts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Facts&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#facts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1927, Babe Ruth hit sixty home runs. That record stood for thirty four years until Roger Maris broke it in 1961 with sixty one home runs. Mark McGwire hit seventy in 1998. On October 7, 2001, at PacBell Park in San Francisco, Barry Bonds hit number seventy three. That accomplishment set a record which, in all probability, will remain unbroken for years into the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/didow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/didow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;haddad-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Haddad J.A. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#haddad-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The single issue in this appeal is to determine, on the particular facts which follow, whether the respondent has trespassed the air space above the appellants’ land.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The material facts are not in dispute. The respondent, an electrical utility company, constructed a power line on the municipal road allowance along the east side of the appellants’ land. The distance between the centre of the base of four power poles, each approximately 50 feet in height, to the boundary of the appellants’ land is two feet. The cross-arms conductors and attaching wires at the top of each pole (collectively called “the cross-arms”) protrude six feet into the air space above the appellants’ land.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/moore/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/moore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;panelli-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Panelli J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#panelli-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We granted review in this case to determine whether plaintiff has stated a cause of action against his physician and other defendants for using his cells in potentially lucrative medical research without his permission. Plaintiff alleges that his physician failed to disclose preexisting research and economic interests in the cells before obtaining consent to the medical procedures by which they were extracted. The superior court sustained all defendants’ demurrers to the third amended complaint, and the Court of Appeal reversed. We hold that the complaint states a cause of action for breach of the physician’s disclosure obligations, but not for conversion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/tenures-estates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/tenures-estates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-alert&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div&gt;&#xA;      &lt;em&gt;Excerpted from Jeremy Sheff, &amp;ldquo;Estates and Future Interests&amp;rdquo; in Stephen Clowney, James Grimmelmann, Michael Grynberg, Jeremy Sheff, and Rebecca Tushnet, eds., &lt;a href=&#34;https://opensourceproperty.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;Open Source Property: A Free Casebook&lt;/a&gt; (2015).&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;According to the common law doctrine of tenure all land under the dominion of the English crown is held “mediately or immediately, of the king”—that is, the crown has “radical title” to all land under its political dominion. William the Conqueror declared that all land in England was literally the king’s property; everyone else had to settle for the privilege of holding it for him—the privilege of &lt;em&gt;tenure&lt;/em&gt; (from the Norman French word “tenir”—to hold). Tenurial rights were intensely personal in early feudal society: the right to hold land was a privilege granted by the crown in exchange for an oath of allegiance and a promise of military service by the tenant—the oath of homage. The word homage derives from the French word &lt;em&gt;homme&lt;/em&gt;—literally “man”—precisely because the ceremony surrounding the oath created not only the right of tenure, but a political and military relationship between “lord and man.”  In exchange for the tenant’s loyal support, or &lt;em&gt;fealty&lt;/em&gt;, the lord warranted the tenant’s right to hold a plot of land, called a fief, or &lt;em&gt;fee&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/planning/description/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/planning/description/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this casebook is to teach 1L law students in Canada about (1) the historical formations of Canadian lawscapes and (2) the contemporary relevance of those formations to addressing disputes about land relations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lawscapes are a particular form of landscape&amp;ndash;socio-ecological structures of land relations, or spaces of natural and cultural interaction (Ellen N Chappell, John R Parkins and Kate Sherren, “Climax Thinking, Place Attachment, and Utilitarian Landscapes: Implications for Wind Energy Development” (2020) 199 Landscape and Urban Planning 103802 at 1)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/planning/doctrines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/planning/doctrines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;treaty-rights&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Treaty Rights&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#treaty-rights&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Idea is that &amp;ldquo;property&amp;rdquo; is not only established by taking animals from a &amp;ldquo;state of nature&amp;rdquo;, it is established&amp;ndash;or circumscribed&amp;ndash;by treaty relationship between sovereign entities&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First opportunity to explore the public/private theme&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;R v Syliboy&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;R v Badger&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;possession--rule-of-capture&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Possession / Rule of Capture&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#possession--rule-of-capture&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Locke&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pierson v Post&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Clift v Kane&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Popov v Hayashi?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;finders--relativity&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Finders / Relativity&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#finders--relativity&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Armorie v Delamire&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Other?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;gifts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Gifts?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#gifts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;doctrine-of-discovery&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Doctrine of Discovery&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#doctrine-of-discovery&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;allodialradical-title&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Allodial/Radical Title&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#allodialradical-title&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;relationship-between-possession-and-title&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Relationship between Possession and Title&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#relationship-between-possession-and-title&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Asher v Whitlock&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;adverse-possession&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Adverse Possession&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#adverse-possession&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Piper v Stevenson&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nelson (City) v Mowatt&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Beals / Downey&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Keefer&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kosicki&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;aboriginal-title&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Aboriginal Title&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#aboriginal-title&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Guerin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Delgamuukw&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;reserve-lands&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Reserve Lands&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#reserve-lands&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Substantive areas explored in the course:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/planning/encounters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/planning/encounters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Idea is to redesign the content around a series of &amp;ldquo;encounters&amp;rdquo; and to move further away from doctrinal focus each week. This emphasis on encounters tracks the historiographical approach charted by Ned Blackhawk in &amp;ldquo;rediscovering&amp;rdquo; American history [@blackhawk2023rediscovery]. &amp;ldquo;Rediscovery&amp;rdquo; also puts a subversive reinterpretation on the doctrine of discovery and terra nullius and locates this project at the heart of the coruse.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For example, the settlement of Halifax at K&amp;rsquo;jipuktuk was a watershed in inter-national relations between the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq, British and French. For the British, this was a settlement of a different kind: focused not on resource extraction or trade, but exclusively on establishing a military outpost to put Britain &amp;ldquo;on the map&amp;rdquo; as it were [@lennox2017homelands, 125-26]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/planning/objectives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/planning/objectives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SMART course objectives: specific, measurable, achievable, relevant, and time-bound (SMART)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;week-1-intro&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Week 1: Intro&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#week-1-intro&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tell students that they are specifically not being evaluated on this material&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Have a class discussion about who read the material, why and why not, and then a substantive discussion that is intended to be &amp;ldquo;pressure free&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;week-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Week 2:&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#week-2&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Week2 centres on the question, &amp;ldquo;who owns the fox?&amp;rdquo; In order to answer that question, we need to answer the question, &amp;ldquo;what are the relevant legal principles or rules?&amp;rdquo; One answer to that question is that dominium and possession-as-property was a well-grounded British legal concept that was forced onto British North American and has become the dominant set of rules for determining ownership of wild animals. An alternative answer is more complicated: rules for wild and domestic animals were produced and negotiated as part of early colonial encounters, drawing out the contingency and ambiguity of common law concepts like &amp;ldquo;possession&amp;rdquo;. This was particularly important in the early colonial period before settler colonialism specifically became more widespread.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/planning/themes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/planning/themes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Course themes include:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Law and language, legal style, grammar and structuralism, etc&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Public vs private&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Property and violence&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;animal-rights--legal-person&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Animal rights / legal person&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#animal-rights--legal-person&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Angela Fernandez, &amp;ldquo;Animals as Quasi-Property/Persons&amp;rdquo; in Andrew Linzey and Clair Linzey, Animal Ethics and Animal Law&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/case/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/case/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/concept/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/context/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/context/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/image/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/image/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/module/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/module/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/problem/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/secondary_sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/secondary_sources/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/types/statute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/types/statute/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Possession&#34; from an Indigenous Worldview</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/indigenous-worldview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/indigenous-worldview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The common law approach to possession and communicating possession is not a universal one. Notice how James (sákéj) Youngblood Henderson inverts the common law&amp;rsquo;s concept of &amp;ldquo;possession&amp;rdquo; as he describes an Indigenous conception of belonging &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; land. In addition, consider the way Henderson engages with some of the common law rationales for property rights regimes we looked at previously&amp;hellip; &lt;!--this idea probably needs to be expanded or made more specific but I wasn&#39;t sure how to do it without knowing how we&#39;ll describe the rationales.--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A &#34;Monkey Wrench in the Free Market&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/auto-insurance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/auto-insurance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In October 2003, the Government of Nova Scotia introduced a bill with proposed amendments to automobile insurance laws in the province. The bill was drafted to address the growing cost of automobile insurance for people who own and drive cars. In Nova Scotia, automobile insurance is provided by private firms. Some of the proposed amendments included a temporary cap on insurance rates, a requirement that the Nova Scotia Insurance Review Board approve the way that insurers classify risk (which determines how much individuals in each class pay for insurance), and a cap on the amount of non-monetary loss (such as for pain and suffering) that insured people can claim for minor injuries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Testamentary Bequest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/testementary-bequest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/testementary-bequest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/y02jEX_B0O0&#34;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/will.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Source: Aaron Burden on Unsplash&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Source: Aaron Burden on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A testator, recently deceased, has two surviving adult children who are the sole beneficiaries of the testator&amp;rsquo;s will. The will establishes a private trust whose terms stipulate that, in order for the eldest of the two children to receive their share of the estate property they must divorce and cease to cohabitate with their spouse. If the eldest child fails to meet this condition within five years of the testator&amp;rsquo;s decease, the whole residue of the estate will pass to the other beneficiary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abandonment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/abandonment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/abandonment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just as it is possible to acquire property by first possession, property rights can also be &amp;ldquo;given up&amp;rdquo; through a processes called &lt;em&gt;abandonment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abandonment occurs when property&amp;ndash;once established by possession or other legal means&amp;ndash;is voluntarily given up by the owner. As the quoted passage above notes, abandonment requires the owner to demonstrate an express &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; to permanently abandon their property rights: they must have “the intention of terminating ownership, possession and control.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aboriginal Title at the End of the 19th Century</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/aboriginal-title-after-stcatherines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/aboriginal-title-after-stcatherines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At this point, you have read three different judgements in the &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt; case: the judgement at trial by Chancellor Boyd, Justice Strong&amp;rsquo;s dissent at the Supreme Court of Canada, and Lord Watson&amp;rsquo;s final decision for the Privy Council. As you try to make sense of the different interpretations and rationales offered by the judges with respect to common law Aboriginal title, consider their different answers to the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acknowledging Wolastoqey Territory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/land-acknowledgement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/land-acknowledgement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To better understand some of the challenges associated with creating a meaningful land acknowledgement, consider a recent controversy in Wolastoqey territory. In October of 2021, New Brunswick&amp;rsquo;s Attorney General issued a memo to provincial employees called &amp;ldquo;First Nation Protocol on Acknowledging Ancestral Territory.&amp;rdquo; The memo was purportedly a response to the Wolastoqey Nation&amp;rsquo;s ongoing claim, in the Canadian courts, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/new-brunswick/wolastoqey-nation-filing-for-title-claim-against-new-brunswick-1.5750955&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;for recognition of Aboriginal title to land that covers about half of present day New Brunswick&lt;/a&gt; (we will examine the details of this kind of claim later in the course). In the memo, provincial employees were instructed not to give territorial or title acknowledgements in the context of their work. Instead, they were to use only an approved &amp;ldquo;ancestral acknowledgement&amp;rdquo; as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adverse Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/adverse-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/adverse-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adverse possession is an unusual common law doctrine. We have already emphasized the point that legal possession and legal title are distinctive concepts. In general, &amp;ldquo;mere possession&amp;rdquo; does not disturb the legal title of the landowner, but the doctrine of adverse possession creates a dramatic exception to this rule. Under the doctrine, when a person has been in possession of land for longer than a period established by statute (called the &lt;em&gt;limitation period&lt;/em&gt;), they may become the title holder—and the original title holder may end up with nothing. The ultimate effect of adverse possession is to take title out of the hands of the original owner and to put that title into the hands of the person in possession.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>African Nova Scotian Settlement</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/ans-settlement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/ans-settlement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although African Nova Scotians have lived in Nova Scotia since 17th century (many of them enslaved by British settlers), the major waves of African Nova Scotian migration occured in the 18th and 19th centuries. First the Black Loyalists, who sided with Britain during the American Revolutionary War in the 1780s; then the Jamaican Maroons in 1796, formerly-enslaved Africans deported to Nova Scotia after they fought for their freedom in Jamaica; and finally the Black Refugees, who were incited by British offers of freedom and land during the War of 1812.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Airspace Rights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/airspace-rights/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/airspace-rights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, possession plays a key role in establishing property in both things (i.e. chattels) and in the surface of land. The surface owner or possessor of land will, of course, often want to do things that extend well into the airspace above the surface. But the sky is a long way up. How high do rights of possession extend—and more importantly, how are such rights established? Are they a natural extension of surface rights, or is there more a surface owner needs to do in order to establish their rights to such airspace?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anishinabek Law and Terra Nullius</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/anishnabek-law-terra-nullius/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/anishnabek-law-terra-nullius/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A McNeil points out in his historical study of the &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt; case, one of the most glaring aspects at every level of court is the lack of reliance on any evidence from Indigenous peoples regarding &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; interpretation of Indigenous land rights before and after Treaty 3 was signed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This absence was not merely from lack of historical or contemporary evidence. McNeil cites the following quote attributed to Chief Ma-we-do-pe-nais on the third day of negotiations around Treaty 3, included in Alexander Morris&amp;rsquo; book on the Numbered Treaties: &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annapolis Group Inc. v Halifax Regional Municipality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/annapolis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/annapolis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;côté-brown-jj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Côté, Brown JJ. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#c%c3%b4t%c3%a9-brown-jj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-overview&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Overview&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-overview&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This appeal calls upon the Court to clarify the circumstances in which state regulation of land use may effect a &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; or (as we will refer to it) “constructive” taking of private property.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The appellant, Annapolis Group Inc., contends that the respondent, Halifax Regional Municipality, improperly used its regulatory powers to effectively seize Annapolis’ land for use as a public park without compensation. Halifax says that Annapolis’ claim is a veiled attempt to make taxpayers foot the bill for a decades-long development gamble. It sought summary dismissal of this part of Annapolis’ claim, while permitting other claims (for misfeasance in public office and unjust enrichment) to proceed to trial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asher v Whitlock </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/asher/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/asher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the trial before Cockburn, C.J., at the last Bedfordshire Spring Assizes, the following facts appeared in evidence. About Michaelmas, in the year 1842, Thomas Williamson inclosed from the waste of a manor a piece of land by the side of the highway; and in 1850, he inclosed more land adjoining, and built a cottage; the whole being the land as described and claimed in the writ. He occupied the whole till his death in 1860. By his will he devised the whole property, describing it as &amp;ldquo;a cottage and garden, in Keysoe Row, in which I now dwell,&amp;rdquo; to his wife Lucy Williamson, for and during so much only of her natural life as she might remain his widow and unmarried; and from and after her decease, or second marriage, whichever event might first happen, to his only child Mary Ann Williamson, in fee. After the death of Thomas Williamson, his widow remained in possession with the daughter, and in April, 1861, married the defendant; and from that time they all three resided on the property till the death of the daughter, aged eighteen years, in February, 1863. On her death, the defendant and his wife, the widow of the testator, continued to reside on the premises; the widow died in May, 1863, and the defendant still continued to occupy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bamberger v Vancouver</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/bamberger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/bamberger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;kirchner-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Kirchner J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#kirchner-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. INTRODUCTION&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1984, an encampment of some 60 tents was established at the site of what would become CRAB Park at Portside in Vancouver. The encampment was a protest designed to pressure government authorities into creating a public park at the site. The name of the park is taken from the acronym for the activist group—Create a Real Available Beach Committee—that envisioned the establishment of a waterfront public park in an area of the city short of green space. The community activism and the camp protest had its desired effect and, in 1987, CRAB Park at Portside (“CRAB Park” or the “Park”) was established as a Vancouver public park on federal port land leased by the City. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basic Estates and Future Interests</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/basic-estates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/basic-estates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will begin by examining two possessory estates—the &lt;strong&gt;fee simple absolute&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;life estate&lt;/strong&gt;—and two future interests &amp;hellip; —the &lt;strong&gt;reversion&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;remainder&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fee-simple-absolute&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Fee Simple Absolute&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-fee-simple-absolute&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fee simple absolute is the most complete interest in land that the law will recognize. When we say that “O owns Greenacre without any further qualification, what we actually mean is that O owns a presently possessory fee simple absolute in Greenacre. The key distinguishing characteristic of the fee simple absolute is that it has no inherent end—it is an estate of indefinite duration. It is descendible, devisable, and alienable inter vivos; so it can be transferred to a new owner, but it cannot be destroyed. At most, it can be carved up into lesser estates and interests for a while, and we will spend most of the rest of this chapter understanding how that happens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beals v Nova Scotia (AG)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/beals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/beals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;bodurtha-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Bodurtha J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#bodurtha-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Community Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt;, the predecessor to the &lt;em&gt;LTCA&lt;/em&gt;, was assented to on March 18, 1964. On second reading of the proposed legislation, the Honourable W. S. Kennedy Jones stated:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this legislation is to provide a simpler and less expensive machinery for the clarification of titles within areas or communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The second section of the Act is the definition section, and therein the minister is defined as being the Minister of Lands and Forests, and I perhaps should point out that my particular interest in the preparation and presentation of the present legislation is as the chairman of the Interdepartmental Committee on Human Rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Belfast Corporation v OD Cars LTD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/belfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/belfast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;viscount-simonds-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Viscount Simonds &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#viscount-simonds-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--&#xA;&#xA; My Lords, the facts in this case, which give rise to some difficult questions, can be shortly stated. The respondents, a limited company registered in Belfast, own in fee farm certain land at Alexandra Park, Belfast. On buildings erected on that land, they have for many years carried on the business of garage proprietors and general motor engineers. On Feb. 9, 1954, they made an application to the appellants. the Belfast Corporation, for permission to erect on the land further industrial and commercial premises, viz., lock-up shops on Antrim Road and factories or warehouses on the back portion. The application was made pursuant to the provisions of s. 2 of the Planning (Interim Development) Act (Northern Ireland), 1944, to the appellants as the interim development authority. Such an application is known as an interim development application. I will refer later to this Act. On Mar. 2, 1954, the appellants refused the application on the ground (a) as to the lock-up shops, that the height and character of the proposed development would not be in accordance with their requirements for the site, namely, development to be in shops with dwellings over minimum height twenty-five feet, and (b) as to the industrial or commercial use of remainder of site, that the site was zoned as residential and that the character and user of the proposed development would be incompatible with such zoning. This refusal led to a claim for compensation for injurious affection under the Act which, in accordance with its provisions, was referred to the official arbitrator appointed thereunder. Before I narrate the proceedings which led to this appeal, I must refer to the relevant statutory provisions of the Planning and Housing Act (Northern Ireland), 1931, and the Planning (Interim Development) Act (Northern Ireland), 1944, which I will call the Act of 1931 and the Act of 1944. The former Act, after providing for the making of planning schemes to be prepared and adopted by local authorities and to be approved by the Minister and sundry other relevant matters, by s. 9 (1) enacted that any person whose property is injuriously affected by the coming into operation of a planning scheme shall, if he makes a claim for the purpose within the time therein mentioned, be entitled to obtain compensation in respect thereof from the responsible authority. But this right is subject to the limitation contained in s. 10, which provides, by sub-s. (1), that where property is alleged to be injuriously affected by reason of any provisions contained in a planning scheme, no compensation shall be paid in respect thereof if or so far as the provisions are also contained in any public, general or local Act in force in the area or otherwise as therein mentioned and, by sub-s. (2) (which is the subsection relevant to this appeal and must be set out verbatim), as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&gt; Property shall not be deemed to be injuriously affected by reason of the coming into operation of any provisions inserted in a planning scheme, which prescribe the space about buildings or limit the number of buildings to be erected, or prescribe the height or character or user of buildings, or prescribe a standard of net annual value for buildings, and which the Ministry, having regard to the nature and situation of the land affected by the provisions, considers reasonable for the purpose:&#xA;&#xA;Development under the Act of 1931 made slow progress and was in due course supplemented by the Act of 1944. Section 1 (1) of that Act deems all land which was not the subject of a planning scheme under the earlier Act, or of a resolution to prepare and adopt such a scheme, to be subject to a resolution to prepare a planning scheme under the Act. Section 2 directs the Ministry to make a general interim development order with respect to land to which such a resolution applies, and provides that such an order may empower any local authority specified therein to permit the development of land in accordance with the provisions thereof. In accordance with the duty thus placed on it, the Ministry, on July 10, 1944, made the Planning (General Interim Development) Order (Northern Ireland), 1944 (S.R. &amp; O. 1944 No. 58), which empowered the appellants to grant permission for the development of land within the county borough of Belfast. I need refer no more to the Act of 1944 except to set out the section, i.e., s. 6, under which, as I have already said, the respondents made the claim for compensation now under review. That section provided, by sub-s. (4), so far as material, as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&gt; Where ... an interim development application is refused ... then, the applicant ... shall, if he makes a claim for the purpose be entitled to obtain from the local authority such compensation in respect of any injurious affection of his property by reason of the aforesaid decision as he would be entitled to obtain under the principal Act [the Act of 1931] if such injurious affection had been suffered as a consequence of the coming into operation of a planning scheme...&#xA;&#xA;The claim for compensation having been made and refused on the grounds that I have stated, a number of questions were raised before the arbitrator which led him without proceeding to an award to state a consultative case for the opinion of the court in which he posed two questions as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&#34;(i) Whether I am entitled to award compensation to the claimant for injurious affection of the said land.&#34;&#xA;&#xA;&#34;(ii) Whether the evidence of Mr. A. P. Fitzgerald is suffcient to satisfy the requirements of s. 10 (2) of the Planning and Housing Act (Northern Ireland), 1931.&#34;&#xA;&#xA;The second question must appear at the present stage of my narrative somewhat cryptic. It is, in my opinion, of a formal character, and I will defer consideration of it until I have disposed of the important matters that arise under the first question. These are, first, a question arising on the construction of the Act of 1944, viz., whether s. 6 (4) of that Act incorporates a reference to s. 10 (2) of the Act of 1831 as well as to the compensatory provisions of s. 9, and, secondly, whether s. 10(2) is a valid enactment having regard to the provisions of s. 5 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920. The far-reaching importance of the second question is obvious.&#xA;&#xA;My Lords, on the first of these questions I entertain no doubt, and I cannot state the answer to it in a manner more clear and comprehensive than the learned Lord Chief Justice (Lord MacDermott) has done. Section 6 (4) of the later Act does incorporate s. 10 (2) of the earlier Act. I will not occupy your Lordships&#39; time by further reference to it.&#xA;&#xA;On the second question, viz., the constitutional validity of s. 10 (2) of the Act of 1931, I must say something more. For, though I agree with much that the Lord Chief Justice has said on this topic, there comes a point at which I must with great respect diverge from him. The issue turns on the true meaning and effect of s. 5 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920. Subsection (1) of that section is as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&gt; In the exercise of their power to make laws under this Act neither the Parliament of Southern Ireland nor the Parliament of Northern Ireland shall make a law so as either directly or indirectly to establish or endow any religion, or prohibit or restrict the free exercise thereof, or give a preference, privilege, or advantage, or impose any disability or disadvantage, on account of religious belief or religious or ecclesiastical status, or make any religious belief or religious ceremony a condition of the validity of any marriage, or affect prejudicially the right of any child to attend a school receiving public money without attending the religious instruction at that school, or alter the constitution of any religious body except where the alteration is approved on behalf of the religious body by the governing body thereof, or divert from any religious denomination the fabric of cathedral churches, or, except for the purpose of roads, railways, lighting. water, or drainage works, or other works of public utility upon payment of compensation, any other property, or take any property without compensation.&#xA;&#xA;&gt; Any law made in contravention of the restrictions imposed by this subsection shall, so far as it contravenes those restrictions, be void.&#xA;&#xA;It was first urged on behalf of the appellants that the last five words of the first paragraph of this subsection referred only to the property of religious bodies or institutions. This point was decided against them twenty years ago in *O&#39;Neill v. Northern Ireland Road Transport Board*, and I do not doubt that that case was rightly decided. An argument founded on the historical genesis of these words, which was in any case of little weight, could not prevail against their plain meaning. Next, I must refer to an argument (though I am not clear which side could be assisted by it) that the words &#34;either directly or indirectly &#34; do not govern the last five words. But grammatically they clearly do, and I see no reason for not allowing grammatical laws to prevail. In any view, it is of no importance to this case.&#xA;&#xA;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black v Canadian Copper Co.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/black/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/black/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;middleton-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Middleton J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#middleton-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A large number of actions were brought, and many others threatened against the Canadian Copper Company, for damages supposed to have been sustained from vapours contained in metallurgical smoke issuing from the roast beds and smelter stacks of that company at Copper Cliff, near Sudbury. A motion was made to consolidate these actions resulting in the choice of four cases which were to proceed and to be regarded as test actions, the others remaining in abeyance in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blackburn v McCallum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/blackburn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/blackburn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;davies-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Davies J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#davies-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question raised for our decision in this case is whether a general prohibition on alienation attached to a devise in fee of lands which prohibition would, if unlimited, be bad by the rules of Common Law, is made good by being limited as to time. I am of opinion that it is not. The will of Donald Chisholm after devising his farm of 100 acres to his two sons William and Hugh in fee and equally dividing it between them, contained the following provision:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/blue-mountain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/blue-mountain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/blue_mountain.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Irwin Barrett - Ecology Action Centre&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Irwin Barrett - Ecology Action Centre&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Lakes is a stunning wilderness area located minutes from downtown Halifax. Attempts by the Halifax Regional Municipality (HRM) to prevent development on private lands next to the wilderness area have made landowners unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Blue Mountain-Birch Cove was designated as a provincially-protected wilderness area in 2009. It started as 1,316 hectares of Crown land and was later expanded, in 2015, to 1,767 hectares. Several private landowners own undeveloped lands adjacent to the protected area. One of those landowners is the Annapolis Group Inc. (Annapolis), whose undeveloped lands have remained essentially wilderness since Annapolis began to acquire them sometime in the middle of the last century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>British North America Act, s 92</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/bna-s9213/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/bna-s9213/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;exclusive-powers-of-provincial-leglislatures&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Exclusive Powers of Provincial Leglislatures&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#exclusive-powers-of-provincial-leglislatures&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;92&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In each Province the Legislature may exclusively make Laws in relation to Matters coming within the Classes of Subjects next hereinafter enumerated, that is to say,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Property and Civil Rights in the Province.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bundle of Sticks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/sticks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/sticks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When trying to explain the common law&amp;rsquo;s particular (and sometimes idiosyncratic) understanding of &amp;ldquo;ownership&amp;rdquo;, lawyers and judges frequently invoke the &amp;ldquo;bundle of sticks&amp;rdquo; metapho&amp;ndash;as in, &amp;ldquo;ownership is like a bundle of sticks&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;the &amp;ldquo;sticks&amp;rdquo; being the various property rights that make up the ownership &amp;ldquo;bundle&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the metaphor is that ownership is not really a homogeneous collection of rights that one either holds (ownership) or does not hold (no ownership). Instead, ownership is a malleable legal concept, difficult to pin down to any particular arrangement or bundle. One landowner might have an unrestricted right to use their land in any way they like, while another might have certain use rights taken out of their ownership bundle—say, by a restrictive covenant that binds and runs with the land. We would likely call both an &amp;ldquo;owner&amp;rdquo;, even though they hold different sets of legal entitlements in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canada Paper Co v Brown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/canada-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/canada-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-chief-justice-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Chief Justice —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-chief-justice-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the reasons stated by my brother Anglin, I am of the opinion that this appeal should be dismissed with costs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;idington-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Idington J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#idington-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The respondent as the owner of property acquired some years before the appellant, in conducting its business as the manufacturers of pulp and paper, had ventured upon methods complained of herein, and had built thereon for himself an expensive home and surrounded it with everything to make that home comfortable and enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canada Trust Co v Ontario (Human Rights Commission)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/canada-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/canada-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;robins-ja--&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Robins J.A.  —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#robins-ja--&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The principal question in this appeal is whether the terms of a scholarship trust established in 1923 by the late Reuben Wells Leonard are now contrary to public policy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[…]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-facts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Facts&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-facts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h5 id=&#34;a-the-trust-document&#34;&gt;&#xA;  A. The Trust Document&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#a-the-trust-document&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By Indenture dated December 28, 1923, (the “Indenture” or “trust document”) Reuben Wells Leonard (the “settlor”) created a trust to be known as “The Leonard Foundation” (the “trust” or the “scholarship trust” or the “Foundation”). He directed that the income from the property transferred and assigned by him to the trust (the “trust property” or “trust fund”) be used for the purpose of educational scholarships, to be called “The Leonard Scholarships”. The Canada Trust Company has been appointed successor trustee of the Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canada-United States-Mexico Agreement, Article 14</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cusma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cusma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;article-148-expropriation-and-compensation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Article 14.8: Expropriation and Compensation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#article-148-expropriation-and-compensation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 No Party shall expropriate or nationalize a covered investment either directly or indirectly through measures equivalent to expropriation or nationalization (expropriation), except:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) for a public purpose;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) in a non-discriminatory manner;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(c) on payment of prompt, adequate, and effective compensation in accordance with paragraphs 2, 3, and 4; and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(d) in accordance with due process of law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;annex-14-6-expropriation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Annex 14-6 Expropriation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#annex-14-6-expropriation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Parties confirm their shared understanding that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canadian Pacific Railway Co. v Vancouver (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cpr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McLachlin C.J.C. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over a century ago, in 1886, the provincial Crown granted the Canadian Pacific Railway Company (”CPR”) a corridor of land for the construction of a railway line from False Creek, in the City of Vancouver (”City”), south to Steveston, on Lulu Island (named after Miss Lulu Sweet, a young actress in the first theatrical company to visit British Columbia). It is this corridor of land, now known as the “Arbutus Corridor”, that lies at the heart of this appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>City of Toronto v Board of Trustees of R.C. Separate Schools for City of Toronto</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/schoolboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/schoolboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;viscount-cave-lc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Viscount Cave L.C. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#viscount-cave-lc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This appeal raises some important questions as to the relative rights of a School Board acting under the Separate Schools Act of Ontario and a City Council acting under the &lt;em&gt;Municipal Act&lt;/em&gt; of that Province. By virtue of the &lt;em&gt;Separate Schools Act&lt;/em&gt;, the Board of Trustees of the Roman Catholic Separate Schools for the city of Toronto (who will be referred to in this judgment as the “School Board”) have power to acquire or rent school sites and to build and carry on schools. By virtue of the &lt;em&gt;Municipal Act&lt;/em&gt;, the Corporation of the city of Toronto is empowered to prohibit by by-law the use of land or the erection or use of buildings within any defined area for any purpose other than that of a private residence. The question is whether, in the circumstances of this case, a by-law made by the Corporation under the latter statute is enforceable in respect of a site purchased by the School Board for school purposes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cobalt (Town) v Coleman (Township)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cobalt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cobalt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;trotter-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Trotter J.A. –&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#trotter-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  A. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#a-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This appeal concerns a tract of land (“the property”) situated in the Township of Coleman (“Coleman”), in the District of Timiskaming. The property is owned by the nearby Town of Cobalt (“Cobalt”). Recently, Cobalt has been using the property to conduct a large-scale aggregate extraction operation. Coleman objects to this use, alleging that it is not compliant with its current zoning by-law.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Committee for the Commonwealth of Canada v Canada</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;The following case dealt with the issue of whether restrictions on political activity (distributing leaflets) at an airport as public property were in violation of the applicants&amp;rsquo; freedom of expression protected by the Charter. In the course of their decisions, the judges discussed broader principles applicable to understanding limitations on government ownership of property.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;lheureux-dubé-j-concurring-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  L&amp;rsquo;Heureux-Dubé J. (concurring) &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#lheureux-dub%c3%a9-j-concurring-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The appellant takes a hard line in urging this Court to allow the appeal, submitting that as owner of property, the government has the right to exclude whomever it wants, and to impose conditions on invitees to its property without limitation by the Charter:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constitution Act, 1982</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/constitution-act-s35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/constitution-act-s35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;section-35&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Section 35&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#section-35&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(1) The existing aboriginal and treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada are hereby recognized and affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(2) In this Act, “aboriginal peoples of Canada” includes the Indian, Inuit and Métis peoples of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(3) For greater certainty, in subsection (1) “treaty rights” includes rights that now exist by way of land claims agreements or may be so acquired. […]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contemporary Style</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/contemporary-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/contemporary-style/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/nRd4uayGSK8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/baseball.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Source: Damir Spanic on Unsplash&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Source: Damir Spanic on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This week we begin the last unit of the course, Unit 4.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our final unit offers an opportunity to revisit not only some of the substantive legal concepts we&amp;rsquo;ve studied throughout the course, but also to ask the question: &lt;em&gt;How can we make sense of our current moment in common law thought? Is there a &amp;ldquo;contemporary&amp;rdquo; legal style, and if so what are its features?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conveyancing Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/conveyancing-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/conveyancing-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;13 Except where a contrary intention appears by the conveyance,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) where words of limitation are not used, the conveyance conveys the whole property right that the party conveying had power to dispose of by the conveyance, including, in the case of real property, the fee simple;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covenants Running in Equity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/covenants-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/covenants-running/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&#xA;          style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;iframe&#xA;          src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/671486180?dnt=0&#34;&#xA;            style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allow=&#34;fullscreen&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De Facto Expropriation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/de-facto-expropriation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/de-facto-expropriation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;constructive-expropriation-in-canadian-law&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Constructive Expropriation in Canadian Law&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#constructive-expropriation-in-canadian-law&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Path of Law&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mahon&lt;/em&gt; are both American sources but they—like others we have seen in the course—exerted a significant influence over the thinking of Canadian jurists during the twentieth century. The American law loomed large in this area because of its especially strong protections for private property against uncompensated takings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, other than a small handful of cases prior to the 1990s, the domestic jurisprudence around &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; expropriation remained all but ignored by Canadian judges. It was not until the Nova Scotia Court of Appeal&amp;rsquo;s decision in &lt;em&gt;Mariner Real Estate Ltd.&lt;/em&gt; that anything like a recognizable legal test for &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; expropriation began to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delgamuukw v British Columbia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/delgamuukw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/delgamuukw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lamer-cjc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Lamer C.J.C &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#lamer-cjc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ii-facts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  II. Facts&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ii-facts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-the-claim-at-trial&#34;&gt;&#xA;  A. The Claim at Trial&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#a-the-claim-at-trial&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This action was commenced by the appellants, who are all Gitksan or Wet&amp;rsquo;suwet&amp;rsquo;en hereditary chiefs, who, both individually and on behalf of their &amp;ldquo;Houses&amp;rdquo; claimed separate portions of 58,000 square kilometres in British Columbia. For the purpose of the claim, this area was divided into 133 individual territories, claimed by the 71 Houses. This represents all of the Wet&amp;rsquo;suwet&amp;rsquo;en people, and all but 12 of the Gitksan Houses. Their claim was originally for &amp;ldquo;ownership&amp;rdquo; of the territory and &amp;ldquo;jurisdiction&amp;rdquo; over it. (At this Court, this was transformed into, primarily, a claim for aboriginal title over the land in question.) The province of British Columbia counterclaimed for a declaration that the appellants have no right or interest in and to the territory or alternatively, that the appellants&amp;rsquo; cause of action ought to be for compensation from the Government of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Downey v Nova Scotia (Attorney General)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/downey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/downey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;campbell-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Campbell J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#campbell-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-land-titles-clarification-act&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The &lt;em&gt;Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-land-titles-clarification-act&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On November 24, 2017 Mr. Downey filed an application for land titles clarification under the &lt;em&gt;Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt; with respect to a property at 39 Beals Crescent in North Preston. The history, context and purpose of that legislation has been reviewed in detail by my colleague Justice Bodurtha in &lt;em&gt;Beals v. Nova Scotia (Attorney General)&lt;/em&gt;, 2020 NSSC 60 (N.S. S.C.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duchman v Oakland Dairy (1928), 63 OLR 111 (CA)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/duchman-v-oakland/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/duchman-v-oakland/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing over a decade after his decision in &lt;em&gt;Black v Canadian Copper Co.&lt;/em&gt;, Justice Middleton&amp;ndash;now at the Ontario Court of Appeal&amp;ndash;took a different approach to the question of remedy for nuisance in &lt;em&gt;Duchman v Oakland Dairy&lt;/em&gt;. In Duchman, the plaintiffs brought an action against a neighbouring dairy operation in Toronto, claiming that the noise caused in the early mornings interfered with plaintiffs&amp;rsquo; and their families&amp;rsquo; sleep. The plaintiffs complained of &amp;ldquo;the constant noise resulting from the loading and unloading of the defendants&amp;rsquo; wagons and motor-trucks; the stamping and kicking of the defendants&amp;rsquo; horses; the rattling of the wagons and trucks and their contents; and the yelling of the defendant company&amp;rsquo;s servants and employees while engaged in their duties.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duthie v Gallagher &amp; Duthie</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/duthie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/duthie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;fisher-j--&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Fisher, J. -&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#fisher-j--&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiffs, who are beneficiaries under the will of William Duthie, deceased, complain, &lt;em&gt;inter alia&lt;/em&gt;, of a breach of trust on the part of the defendants as executors and trustees under the will in omitting to sell the testamentary property when it might have been sold at a good price and retaining it and paying taxes thereon for a while until part of it (some eleven acres) was finally lost at a tax sale and the rest or the portion thereof unsold has become so depreciated in value that the estate, which was estimated to have had a net value of approximately, $21,000 at the time of the death of the testator in September, 1911, is now apparently at best little more than solvent. In reply the defendant Gallagher, who has been the active executor (the co-executor being now a man over 80 years of age), first calls attention to a fact which I think should be taken into consideration under the circumstances here where such a devastavit as aforesaid is alleged, &lt;em&gt;viz.&lt;/em&gt;, that since the death of the deceased, the plaintiffs, being the widow (who married again in 1912) and the children while infants, have lived rent free on the most salable part of the estate being one of the Burnaby properties consisting of about five acres and have also had certain rents from time to time therefrom. Attention has also been called to the fact admitted by the plaintiffs that the widow did not wish this part of the property sold and apparently the other plaintiffs since coming of age have all approved of the use being made of this portion of the estate though in the last paragraph of the will the testator directs that in the event of his wife marrying again his trustees should use the income for the benefit of the daughters (only).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duty to Consult</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/duty-to-consult/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/duty-to-consult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You will note that in the final paragraphs excerpted from &lt;em&gt;Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation&lt;/em&gt;, the Supreme Court found that the Province of British Columbia breached its duty to consult with the Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation prior to granting forestry licences to third parties on territorial lands. That duty was engaged when the Province began the planning process for removing timber on the land.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An important point here is that the Crown owed and breached its duty to consult with the Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation well &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; to the Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation  successfully proving their claim in the courts. This is a central purpose of the consultation doctrine: it engages the Crown&amp;rsquo;s fiduciary duty and the honour of the Crown in advance of litigation or negotiations to address claims to title, and therefore offers some measure of protection for title lands in light of the several legal and other barriers to successfully resolving such claims.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Interpretation of the 1752 Treaty</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/interpretation-1752-treaty/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/interpretation-1752-treaty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1928, Grand Chief Gabriel Syliboy was charged and ultimately convicted of hunting muskrats out of season on Unamaki (Cape Breton). Justice Patterson&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of the 1752 treaty in &lt;em&gt;R v Syliboy&lt;/em&gt;—though ultimately rejected by Canadian courts—would stand as an authoritative common law precedent for many years to come. The decision would influence relationships between Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq peoples and the Crown long after it was issued. As William Wicken notes:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In approaching treaties signed with Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq peoples, federal and provincial governments have ignored community perspectives and reinforced Judge Patterson&amp;rsquo;s viewpoint of treaty-making. Though treaty issues have been before the courts on numerous occasions over the past sixty years, scant attention has been focused on how the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq understood treaties both at their signing and afterward. A 1974 memorandum, for instance, sent by Nova Scotia&amp;rsquo;s deputy Attorney-General, to the president of the Union of Nova Scotia Indians noted that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elsipogtog First Nation&#39;s Claim to Aboriginal Title </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/aboriginal-title-elsipogtog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/aboriginal-title-elsipogtog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November 2016, Elsipogtog First Nation filed a Notice of Action and Statement of Claim in the New Brunswick Court of Queen&amp;rsquo;s Bench. The following quotes from the press release issued by Elsipogtog in advance of that filing:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On November 9, 2016 Elsipogtog First Nation is filing a claim on behalf of the Mi’kmaq Nation for Aboriginal title to the Mi’kma’ki district of Sikniktuk in New Brunswick.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“This claim is about protecting our lands and waters for our children and our future generations,” said Elsipogtog Chief Arren Sock. “We cannot stand by while the government ignores us and makes decisions that threaten the traditional lands of the Mi’kmaq people. It’s time for us to exercise our rights and responsibilities to protect our territory.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expropriation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Remedies in nuisance are one legal tool used by property owners—with mixed success—to stop their neighbours from adversely affecting use and enjoyment of the owner&amp;rsquo;s land. Nuisance, in other words, is one means to exclude others from doing something that limits owners&amp;rsquo; freedom related to property. This means of exclusion, however, unavoidably limits the freedom of others to use their land as they choose. In these cases, the courts must choose not only whose rights should win out but also find some way to address the fundamental dilemma of conflicting freedoms inherent in legal liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expropriation Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--2(w) “fur-bearing animal” means beaver, muskrat, red squir- rel, mink, otter, skunk, weasel, fisher, marten, lynx, bobcat, cougar, fox, coyote, raccoon and any other non-domesticated animal which may be designated as a fur-bearing animal by the Governor in Coun- cil, and includes any part of such animal, but does not include bear or snowshoe hare;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3(1)(c) “expropriate” means the taking of land without the consent of the owner by an expropriating authority in the exercise of its statutory powers;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Possession and Wild Animals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/first-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/first-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;classical-first-possession-locke-and-wild-animals&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Classical First Possession: Locke and Wild Animals&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#classical-first-possession-locke-and-wild-animals&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Locke&amp;rsquo;s argument for possession (by means of one&amp;rsquo;s labour) as the basis for establishing property rights in &amp;ldquo;unowned&amp;rdquo; things and land has had a lasting influence on common law property. More important still, the way in which Locke justified his principle of first possession laid much of the groundwork for the style of classical legal thought that would come to dominate in the nineteenth century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Framework Agreement on First Nation Land Management Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fafnlma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fafnlma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;8 On the coming into force of the land code of a First Nation, the rights and obligations of His Majesty in right of Canada as grantor in respect of the interests or land rights and the licences described in the First Nation’s individual agreement referred to in clause 6 of the Framework Agreement are transferred to the First Nation in accordance with that individual agreement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guerin v R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/guerin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/guerin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;This case concerns the lease of reserve lands situated within the geographical boundaries of the City of Vancouver. In 1957, members of the Musqueam Indian Band voted to surrender 162 acres of their reserve lands to the federal Crown on the understanding that these lands would in turn be leased by the Crown to the Shaughnessy Heights Golf Club for use as a golf course. Rents and other benefits from this lease were to be paid to Band. The final terms on which the Crown ultimately leased the lands to Shaughnessy Heights, however, were very unfavourable to the Band. The Chief and Councillors of the Musqueam Indian Band sued the Crown for breach of trust and damages in the amount of $10,000,000.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harrison v Carswell</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/harrison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/harrison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;dickson-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Dickson J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#dickson-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The respondent, Sophie Carswell, was charged under &lt;em&gt;The Petty Trespasses Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.M. 1970, c. P50, with four offences (one on each of four days) of unlawfully trespassing upon the premises of the Fairview Corporation Limited, trading under the firm name and style of Polo Park Shopping Centre, located in the City of Winnipeg, after having been requested by the owner not to enter on or come upon the premises. The appellant, Peter Harrison, manager of Polo Park Shopping Centre, swore the informations. The charges were dismissed by the Provincial Judge but on a trial de novo in the County Court Mrs. Carswell was convicted and fined $10 on each of the charges. The convictions were set aside by the Manitoba Court of Appeal [1974] 4 W.W.R. 394 (Freedman C.J.M. and Matas J.A., with Guy J.A. dissenting) and the present appeal followed by leave of this Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heegsma v. Hamilton (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/heegsma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/heegsma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ramsay-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ramsay J. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ramsay-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The applicants are 14 homeless individuals who apply for a&#xA;declaration that the City of Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s enforcement of its Parks by-law&#xA;during the period from August 2021 to August 2023 breached their right&#xA;under the Charter to life, liberty and security of the person (s.7) and&#xA;to equal benefit of the law (s.15). They seek damages from the City.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The applicants say that they were evicted from encampments during&#xA;the period from August 2021 to August 2023 in breach of the Charter, and&#xA;that they suffered harm as a result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hodge v the Queen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/hodge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/hodge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;judgement-of-the-lords-of-the-judicial-committee-of-the-privy-council&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Judgement of the Lords of the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#judgement-of-the-lords-of-the-judicial-committee-of-the-privy-council&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Appellant, Archibald Hodge, the proprietor of a tavern known as the St. James Hotel, in the city of Toronto, and who, on the 7th May 1881, was the holder of a license for the retail of spirituous liquors in his tavern, and also licensed to keep a billiard saloon, was summoned before the Police Magistrate of Toronto, for a breach of the Resolutions of the License Commissioners of Toronto, and was convicted on evidence sufficient to sustain the conviction if the magistrate had authority in law to make it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holmes&#39; Modernism in Practice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/holmes-modernism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/holmes-modernism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We now want to see how Holmes&amp;rsquo; ideas about the modern style play out in a case about &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; expropriation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After he wrote &lt;em&gt;The Path of Law&lt;/em&gt;, Holmes became a leading member of the United States Supreme Court. In 1922, he penned the majority decision in one of the first major U.S. cases about regulatory takings, &lt;em&gt;Pennsylvania Coal Co. v Mahon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why we&amp;rsquo;re reading it:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mahon&lt;/em&gt; is an early example of two judges—Holmes for the majority, and Brandeis in dissent—embracing the modern style, despite their disagreement on the outcome of the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House of Commons Debate (Rivers and Streams Bill)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/house-debates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/house-debates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mr-mccarthy-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Mr. McCarthy —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mr-mccarthy-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the House rose at six o&amp;rsquo;clock, I was proceeding to consider that part of the Bill which deals with compensation. Perhaps I might first be permitted to state, however, what I understand to be the meaning of the word &amp;ldquo;compensation,&amp;rdquo; when applied to the sovereign right of expropriation. Now, I do not pretend to dispute, and I am quite willing to admit in the amplest possible manner, so far as my judgement goes, that this &lt;em&gt;Act&lt;/em&gt; of Parliament was, subject to one consideration, within the power of the Local Legislature. If the one consideration be overlooked there is power in the Local Legislature as in every other sovereign body&amp;ndash;and the Local Legislature is sovereign so far as its jurisdiction extends&amp;ndash;to expropriate property for public purposes. But, Sir, as I understand the doctrine of expropriation, as we call it, or as it is better known on the other side of the line, the exercise of its power of &lt;em&gt;eminent domain&lt;/em&gt;, there are two limitations to the exercise of that power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indian Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/indian-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/indian-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;18 (1) Subject to this Act, reserves are held by Her Majesty for the use and benefit of the respective bands for which they were set apart, and subject to this Act and to the terms of any treaty or surrender, the Governor in Council may determine whether any purpose for which lands in a reserve are used or are to be used is for the use and benefit of the band.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indigenous Legal Orders and Housing on Reserve Lands</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/reserve-housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/reserve-housing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Professors Val Napoleon and Emily Snyder have recently published a study of housing on reserve and the role of Indigenous property laws in four Indigenous communities in northwestern British Columbia. As Napoleon and Snyder describe in the introduction to that study:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Paul Nadasdy has observed that in the negotiation of their land claim agreement, the Kluane First Nation in the Yukon &amp;ldquo;translate their complex reciprocal relationship with the land into an equally complex but very different language of ‘property.’&amp;rdquo; According to Indigenous political science scholar Glen Coulthard, the negotiation of land rights has reoriented &amp;ldquo;Indigenous struggle from one that was once deeply informed by the land as a system of reciprocal relations and obligations … to a struggle that is now largely for land, understood here as some material resource to be exploited in the capital-accumulation process.&amp;rdquo; While Coulthard is not addressing reserve land, the questions concerning relationships to land, economies, and governance, along with competing legal orders, are the not-so-deep undercurrents beneath the property-on-reserve debate. This larger political frame is usually ignored and replaced with debates about Indigenous property on reserve land that mainly start and remain inside unquestioned Western property constructs and ongoing colonial structures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Treaty Relationships</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaties-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaties-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week we studied the historical roots of the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title and saw, in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt;, how classical legal thought framed the courts&amp;rsquo; conclusion that Indigenous land rights were &amp;ldquo;personal&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;proprietary&amp;rdquo;. We left off with the observation that beneath the issue of Aboriginal title foregrounded in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt; was the doctrine of &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;ldquo;land belonging to no one&amp;rdquo;). Aspects of &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt;—paired with the doctrine of discovery—undergird courts&amp;rsquo; continued assumption of Crown sovereignty and the exclusion of Indigenous sovereignties up to the present day. One consequence of this doctrine has been to largely exclude Indigenous legal orders from the consciousness of the common law.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Trusts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/trusts-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/trusts-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The origin of the trust lies in medieval tax estate planning and tax evasion. (Arguably, nothing has changed in the last six hundred years.) Imagine Osbert, a minor lord in the 15th century, who holds Greenacre as a tenant of Leonard, a slightly less minor lord. Osbert is getting on in years and has started to worry about the future of his family. His elder son, Aylwin, is not showing promising signs of maturity, and Osbert has come to think that Aylwin may be better suited to religious orders than the duties of managing a great estate. But Osbert’s younger son Bartholomew appears to be a fine young gentleman: athletic, patient, and wise in the ways of men. Osbert would like to provide for Aylwin, but would prefer to have Greenacre go to Bartholomew. Osbert’s problem is that the available conveyancing devices don’t work for him. If he does nothing, then Greenacre goes to Alywin at Osbert’s death under the rule of primogeniture in effect in England at the time, according to which the eldest son receives any land his father owned at his death (was “seised of,” in contemporary terminology). A will leaving Greenacre to Bartholomew doesn’t work because land could not be devised by will until the Statute of Wills in 1540. And Osbert doesn’t want to convey Greenacre (or a future interest in Greenacre) to Bartholomew now, because Bartholomew might die before him, or Aylwin might get his act together, or something else could come along to force a change in plan.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iwasaki v R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/iwasaki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/iwasaki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;sheppard-dj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Sheppard, D.J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#sheppard-dj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The suppliant, Torazo Iwasaki, alleges by petition that the Custodian as trustee for the suppliant as evacuee committed a breach of trust in selling land of the suppliant without any power of sale, or by selling to the specific grantee, Salt Spring Lands Limited, and for such acts of the Custodian the Crown is liable by &lt;em&gt;respondeat superior&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Crown in defence says: &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(1) That there was no trust; &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keefer v Arillotta</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/keefer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/keefer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wilson-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Wilson, J.A. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#wilson-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an appeal from an order of His Honour Judge Nicholls holding that the respondents had acquired a possessory title to a portion of the appellants’ land subject to an easement remaining in the appellants.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The facts are more fully set out in the reasons for judgment of the learned trial Judge but the more significant ones for purposes of this appeal may be summarized under the following headings:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kosicki v Toronto (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/kosicki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/kosicki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sossin-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Sossin J.A. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#sossin-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Overview&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#overview&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Can private landowners gain title over municipal parkland through&#xA;adverse possession? This is the central question raised on this appeal.&#xA;The application judge answered this question by finding that municipal&#xA;parkland is immune to adverse possession. While I would not accept such&#xA;an immunity arises at common law, I conclude the application judge was&#xA;correct in finding that the municipal parkland at issue in this case was&#xA;not available for adverse possession. For the reasons that follow, I&#xA;would dismiss the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land Title and Possession in African Nova Scotian Communities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/ans-title-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/ans-title-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;general-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  General Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#general-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://novascotia.ca/natr/titles-clarification/pdf/NovaScotiaLTCA.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/ltca.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Excerpted from Plan Showing LTCA Land Title Clarification Areas in Nova Scotia&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Excerpted from &lt;em&gt;Plan Showing LTCA Land Title Clarification Areas&lt;/em&gt; in Nova Scotia&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This week, we continue to build our understanding of the relationship between possession and title that is so foundational to common law property. Our overarching question in Week 6 is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-question&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div&gt;&#xA;      &lt;em&gt;Why&lt;/em&gt; is title in land&amp;ndash;as distinguished from possession of land&amp;ndash;important? What are the justifications and consequences of the move from possession to title as part of the basic structure of a liberal market economy?&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We start by taking up this question in a particular place and context: recent movements to &amp;ldquo;clarify&amp;rdquo; land titles in African Nova Scotian communities as a means to address economic disadvantage and an unequal distribution of land as a consequence of discriminatory land policies in the province. These movements have placed heavy emphasis on the regularization and formalization of land titles for individuals and families who have long been in possession of land, and can help us to understand&amp;ndash;and develop a critical perspective on&amp;ndash;the social and economic role of legal title.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land Title Clarification in African Nova Scotian Communities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/ans-title-clarification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/ans-title-clarification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The context for our case study this week is described in two excerpts below from recent decisions of the Nova Scotia Supreme Court. Both cases address provincial legislation called the &lt;em&gt;Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt;, RSNS 1989, c 250, through which individuals in possession of land can apply to have their land title &amp;ldquo;clarified&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;that is, given formal legal recognition&amp;ndash;where title does not exist or is uncertain. The excerpts from &lt;em&gt;Downey&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Beals&lt;/em&gt;, below, sketch the basic features of this legislation and its connection to the historical settlement of African Nova Scotians.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land Title versus Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/title-vs-possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/title-vs-possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://novascotia.ca/natr/titles-clarification/pdf/NovaScotiaLTCA.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/ltca.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Edited from Plan Showing LTCA Land Title Clarification Areas&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Edited from &lt;em&gt;Plan Showing LTCA Land Title Clarification Areas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The act of physical control—as a crucial element of legal possession—is afforded special priority by the common law. In the case of &amp;ldquo;unowned&amp;rdquo; things, showing physical control (plus an intention to control) amounts not only to legal possession for a period of time but also to absolute ownership—at least, if the animal can no longer &amp;ldquo;escape&amp;rdquo;. Exactly &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; one can show sufficient physical control is, as we saw, often difficult to define and heavily dependent on the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land Titles Clarification Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/ltca/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/ltca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3(1) Where the residents of an area of a municipality are in necessitous circumstances as a result of lack of property development in the area and where there appears to be confusion as to the ownership of land, the Governor in Council may designate the area as a land titles clarification area. [..]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4(1) A person who claims to own land in a land titles clarification area may apply to the Minister for a certificate of claim in respect of a lot of land in the area which he claims to own.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land, Property and Colonialism in this Course</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/anticolonialism-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/anticolonialism-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the year we will examine several features of Canada&amp;rsquo;s liberal market economy in order to address our central question in the course. One of those features is the economy&amp;rsquo;s foundation in the colonial dispossession of Indigenous peoples through the institution of property and we will have much more to discuss on this topic this term and next. But colonialism is not only a &lt;em&gt;feature&lt;/em&gt; or characteristic of the Canadian economy&amp;ndash;it also an ongoing reality that shapes how we learn about law and property, including the frameworks, theories and perspectives we use to make sense of legal rules and disputes. Colonialism shapes the interpretation and application of law, as well as the questions we tend to ask about these processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawrence v Maple Trust Company</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/lawrence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/lawrence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gillese-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Gillese J.A. –&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#gillese-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ownership of a person&amp;rsquo;s home is fraudulently transferred. The property is then mortgaged. In a contest between the two innocent parties–the homeowner and the lender of mortgage moneys–who wins? This appeal answers that question in favour of the homeowner.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Susan Lawrence lives in her home in Toronto (the &amp;ldquo;Property&amp;rdquo;). The Property was encumbered by a mortgage in favour of TD/Canada Trust (the &amp;ldquo;TD Bank mortgage&amp;rdquo;) in the approximate amount of $120,000.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessees of Lawson et al v Whitman</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/lawson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/lawson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;halliburton-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Halliburton, C.J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#halliburton-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appeared at the trial that the land in dispute was included in a grant which was made to Jonathan Belcher in 1773, which the lessees of the plaintiff claim by several mesne conveyances.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The case therefore rests upon the defendant&amp;rsquo;s claim under the statutes of Limitation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appears that in the year 1784 a grant passed to William Sutherland, and several other grantees bounded to the south upon the north line of the Belcher grant; but it is quite clear that instead of the south line of Sutherland&amp;rsquo;s grant, having been laid out upon the ground on the north line of the Belcher grant, it was placed upwards of a mile to the south of it, and that possession according to that line has been held by those claiming under Sutherland&amp;rsquo;s grant for more than double the number of years requisite to give a title under the statute. This was indeed so far admitted at the argument that the plaintiffs did not claim to dispossess the defendant of that part of the land which he had actually cultivated and occupied, but as he had defended for a portion of it which was still in a wilderness state, they contended that they were entitled to a verdict for that. The defendant, however, contends that as the deeds under which he claims, contain the uncultivated as well as the cultivated land, and he or those under whom he claims have held by those deeds for upwards of 50 years that he is entitled to retain both.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liberalism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/liberalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/liberalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As both a framework for and political tradition in Western legal thought, &amp;ldquo;liberalism&amp;rdquo; is core to the logic of Anglo-Canadian law and related legal orders in a globalized world.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As Ian McKay argues:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[T]he category &amp;lsquo;Canada&amp;rsquo; should &amp;hellip; denote a historically specific project of rule, rather than either an essence we must defend or an empty homogeneous space we must possess. Canada-as-project can be analyzed through the study of the implantation and expansion over a heterogeneous terrain of a certain politico-economic logic&amp;ndash;to wit, liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locke and Colonialism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/locke-colonialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/locke-colonialism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Several writers have explored and debated the ways in which Locke&amp;rsquo;s influential works sought to justify an expanding British colonialism at the time when the &lt;em&gt;Second Treatise&lt;/em&gt; was published. As part of that project, questions about property and possession of land were fundamental. While Locke appears to acknowledge that British law may recognize the possession of Indigenous peoples, he simultaneously lays down justifications for undermining any possessory entitlements&amp;ndash;or for ignoring them altogether.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mariner Real Estate Ltd v Nova Scotia (Attorney General)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mariner/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mariner/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;cromwell-ja-glube-cjns-concurring-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Cromwell J.A. (Glube C.J.N.S. concurring) —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#cromwell-ja-glube-cjns-concurring-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This case involves a collision of important interests. On one side, there are the interests of the respondents in the enjoyment of their privately owned land at Kingsburg Beach. On the other is the public interest in the protection and preservation of environmentally fragile and ecologically significant beach, dune and beach ridge resources. In the background of this case is the policy issue of how minutely government may control land without buying it. But in the foreground is the narrower issue of whether the stringent land use regulations applied by the Province to the respondents’ lands is an expropriation of them within the meaning of the &lt;em&gt;Expropriation Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.N.S. 1989, c. 156.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Market in Biological Cells</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/market-cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/market-cells/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/pwcKF7L4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/lab.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Source: Louis Reed on Unsplash&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Source: Louis Reed on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One or more of the arguments pairs constructed by Justice Panelli and Justice Mosk in &lt;em&gt;Moore&lt;/em&gt; relate directly to our &lt;a href=&#34;../week1#Market&#34; &gt;central question in the course&lt;/a&gt; regarding the relationship between law and markets. Consider in particular the judges&amp;rsquo; debate over &amp;ldquo;policy reasons&amp;rdquo; for extending conversion liability to biological cells (the &lt;a href=&#34;#green_1&#34; &gt;green argument pair&lt;/a&gt; in the decisions above).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To what extent does this debate rest on the three pervasive assumptions (natural, neutral and necessary) about law and markets (here, a market in biological cells) that we discussed in Week 1? Having identified the work of these assumptions in the case, how might you critique the judges&amp;rsquo; shared approach to the debate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>McCorkill v McCorkill (Estate)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/mccorkill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/mccorkill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harry McCorkill died in 2004, leaving his entire estate valued at over $200,000 as an unconditional gift to the National Alliance, a neo-Nazi group based in the United States. McCorkill&amp;rsquo;s sister challenged the bequest as contrary to public policy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;grant-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Grant J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#grant-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[…]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;applicants-grounds&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Applicant’s Grounds&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#applicants-grounds&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In her amended Notice of Application, Ms. McCorkill sets out the following as the grounds of her application:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;g. The payment or transfer of the residue of the estate to the National Alliance is against public policy and in contradiction with Canada’s own laws, undertakings and commitments in that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>McLaren v Caldwell et al</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mclaren/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mclaren/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background to the Case&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the nineteenth century, access to waterways in Upper Canada and elsewhere in the country became an integral part of the lumber industry and a primary means to bring timber from logging operations to sawmills and other points of market. From one perspective, these waterways were akin to other types of public infrastructure (like roads and railways) necessary for rapidly expanding natural resource extraction and, eventually,  industrialization. In 1847, provincial legislation was passed to help ensure access to waterways in Upper Canada by lumber workers. The legislation stated that:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metalclad Corporation v The United Mexican States</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/metalclad/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/metalclad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-tribunal-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Tribunal —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-tribunal-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;c-nafta-article-1110-expropriation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  C. NAFTA, Article 1110: Expropriation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#c-nafta-article-1110-expropriation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NAFTA Article 1110 provides that “[n]o party shall directly or indirectly … expropriate an investment … or take a measure tantamount to … expropriation … except: (a) for a public purpose; (b) on a non- discriminatory basis; (c) in accordance with due process of law and Article 1105(1); and (d) on payment of compensation …” “A measure” is defined in Article 201(1) as including “any law, regulation, procedure, requirement or practice”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mi&#39;kmaw Land Tenure</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/mikmaw-land-tenure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/mikmaw-land-tenure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Court in &lt;em&gt;Syliboy&lt;/em&gt; deployed each of the core themes of colonialism in property law we introduced in Week 1 in order to interpret the 1752 Peace and Friendship Treaty. The &lt;em&gt;Syliboy&lt;/em&gt; decision provided a deeply problematic footing on which to set the common law&amp;rsquo;s understanding of treaty rights and in some significant ways tracked the developing common law doctrine of Aboriginal title. But despite the &lt;em&gt;Syliboy&lt;/em&gt; decision&amp;rsquo;s long influence on treaty interpretation in Mi&amp;rsquo;kma&amp;rsquo;ki, in its aftermath Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw jurists continued to offer alternative interpretations grounded in the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw legal order and worldview.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monsanto Canada Inc v Schmeiser</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/monsanto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/monsanto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mclachlin-cjc-and-fish-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McLachlin C.J.C. and Fish J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mclachlin-cjc-and-fish-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This case concerns a large scale, commercial farming operation that grew canola containing a patented cell and gene without obtaining licence or permission. The main issue is whether it thereby breached the &lt;em&gt;Patent Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.C. 1985, c. P-4. We believe that it did.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In reaching this conclusion, we emphasize from the outset that we are not concerned here with the innocent discovery by farmers of “blow-by” patented plants on their land or in their cultivated fields. Nor are we concerned with the scope of the respondents’ patent or the wisdom and social utility of the genetic modification of genes and cells — a practice authorized by Parliament under the &lt;em&gt;Patent Act&lt;/em&gt; and its regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-juridical Canada and Jeremy Dutcher&#39;s Musical Dialogues</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/dutcher-multi-juridicalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/dutcher-multi-juridicalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have seen this week and last how judges in the style of classical common law thought largely foreclosed any genuine consideration of Indigenous laws or of a multi-juridical Canada. Later in the course, we will return to this idea and ask about possibilities for intersections between legal orders.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As you start to think about this question, consider the work and music of Wolastoqiyik artist Jeremy Dutcher, a member of the Tobique First Nation (Neqotkuk) who released his Juno and Polaris prize-winning album &lt;em&gt;Wolastoqiyik Lintuwakonawa&lt;/em&gt; in 2018. Dutcher, who trained as an operatic tenor at Dalhousie, recorded the album entirely in Wolastoqey as part of a project that brings the artist into a kind of musical dialogue with ancestral voices from his community singing traditional songs that were recorded by the anthropologist William Mechling on wax cylinders between 1907 and 1914.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nakashima v R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/nakashima/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/nakashima/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;thorson-p-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Thorson P. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#thorson-p-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In each of these proceedings it was ordered that the following question of law be set down for hearing and disposed of before the trial, namely,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assuming the allegations of fact contained in the Petition of Right to be true, does a petition of right lie against the respondent for any of the relief sought by the suppliant in the said Petition.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The suppliants are all persons of Japanese origin who resided and owned property in Vancouver, British Columbia, prior to their compulsory evacuation therefrom in 1942. The first suppliant is a British subject by naturalization, the second a British subject by birth, and the suppliants in the third petition are Japanese nationals. The questions of law were heard together, the circumstances being such that the answer in any one case will be equally applicable in the others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Netukulimk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/netukulimk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/netukulimk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw legal traditions and Netukulimk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq and the forest ecosystem is more intimate than suggested in court. It is foundational to their worldview, integral to their legal traditions, and constitutional rights. This evidence was not before the courts, but it would have been useful to the courts if properly presented as part of Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq constitutional law, as well as the foundation of aboriginal and treaty rights as constitutional law of Canada. The relationship between the forest and Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq people is deeply embodied in the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq knowledge system and legal traditions, a relationship beginning with the Creation story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noble et al v Alley</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/noble/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/noble/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This case addressed a discriminatory restrictive covenant attached to land forming part of a summer resort development called the Beach O&amp;rsquo;Pines. The covenant, in clause (f), prohibited the sale, transfer or lease of the land to, or use or occupancy by, individuals of Jewish &amp;ldquo;race or blood&amp;rdquo; or people of colour, and expressed an intention to restrict ownership of land in the resort development to &amp;ldquo;persons of the white or Caucasian race not excluded by this clause.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>North American Free Trade Agreement, Article 1110</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/nafta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/nafta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;article-1110-expropriation-and-compensation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Article 1110: Expropriation and Compensation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#article-1110-expropriation-and-compensation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 No Party may directly or indirectly nationalize or expropriate an investment of an investor of another Party in its territory or take a measure tantamount to nationalization or expropriation of such an investment (&amp;ldquo;expropriation&amp;rdquo;), except:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) for a public purpose;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) on a non-discriminatory basis;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(c) in accordance with due process of law and Article 1105(1); and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(d) on payment of compensation in accordance with paragraphs 2 through 6.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuisance in Property Law</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/nuisance-as-right-to-exclude/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/nuisance-as-right-to-exclude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One right in particular, some argue, is fundamental to private property: the &lt;em&gt;right to exclude&lt;/em&gt; others from interfering with the owner&amp;rsquo;s use and enjoyment of their land, other tangible things and even intangibles like knowledge goods. The common law has devised several remedies to enforce owners&amp;rsquo; right to exclude. We have already seen two examples of this. In &lt;em&gt;Harrison v Carswell&lt;/em&gt;, the mall owner brought an action in &lt;em&gt;trespass&lt;/em&gt; against the picketer Sophie Carswell to exclude her from the mall sidewalk, while the plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Moore&lt;/em&gt; made a claim in &lt;em&gt;conversion&lt;/em&gt; in his attempt to exclude the defendants from using his cells after they were extracted from his body. Both of these are causes of action in tort designed to protect the right to exclude.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuisance Law in an Industrializing Canada </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/nuisance-industrial-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/nuisance-industrial-canada/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/canada_paper.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Canada Paper Company, Windsor Mills, QC, 1909. Source: McCord Museum, Montreal.&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://collections.musee-mccord.qc.ca/en/collection/artifacts/VIEW-4677/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;Canada Paper Company, Windsor Mills, QC, 1909. Source: McCord Museum, Montreal.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Widespread industrialization came somewhat late in Canada compared to England and the United States, where nuisance law was addressed earlier by the courts as a potential impediment to economic &amp;ldquo;progress&amp;rdquo;. As Jennifer Nedelsky explains:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the late nineteenth century, industrialization and urbanization were changing the shape of Canadian society: between 1880 and 1920 the population doubled from 3,689,257 to 8,788,483; 74.35 per cent of the population were classified as rural by the census of Canada in 1881; by 1921 the percentage had decreased to 50.48. Capital investment in manufactures increased from $165,302,632 in 1880 to $2,923,667,011 in 1920 and the gross value of all manufactured products from $469,847,886 in 1880 to $3,706,544,997 in 1920. Manufacturing, once diffused, was concentrating in industrial towns. Factories increasingly replaced small workshops, and steam-powered engines brought noise as well as productivity. As the nuisances of industrialization increased, so did the costs of eliminating them. Manufacturing establishments, for example, were becoming sufficiently large and important to local economies that ordering them to take their nuisances elsewhere would have had serious consequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obligations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/obligations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/obligations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For this exercise, start by taking some time to think about the obligations you bring to this property law course. You might want to start by thinking about what obligations have confront by coming to class each week. What gets you out of your home and into the law school? What responsibilities do you encounter as you try to understanding and complete your weekly readings (and to whom)? Below are some further questions to help guide your reflections. Take around ten minutes to make a list of all the relevant obligations that come to your mind in this context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overview - The St. Catherine&#39;s Milling Case</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/overview-st-catherines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/overview-st-catherines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For more than a hundred years after it was enacted, the Royal Proclamation of 1763 stood as the British Crown&amp;rsquo;s most authoritative statement on Aboriginal title. But during this period the Proclamation itself received little to no scrutiny in the common law courts. This changed dramatically when the Chancery Division of the High Court of Ontario issued its decision in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling and Lumber Co. v R&lt;/em&gt; in 1886, followed by subsequent appeals all the way to the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council—at that time, Canada&amp;rsquo;s highest court of appeal. The case would chart the course for the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title in Canada for well into the next century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parking Chairs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/parking-chairs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/parking-chairs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:20000128_02_Chairs_protecting_parking_place,_Chicago_%286897447742%29.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/parking_chairs.jpg&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was undisputed in &lt;em&gt;Asher&lt;/em&gt; that Thomas Williamson had come into possession of the land at issue by &amp;ldquo;inclosing&amp;rdquo; it—presumably, by building a fence or erecting some other sort of boundary marker (as well as constructing a cottage on it). Erecting a fence is a quintessential  way of marking something as &amp;ldquo;mine&amp;rdquo;, and generally sends a clear message to others to &amp;ldquo;keep out&amp;rdquo;. What other practices do we understand as signalling possession? Are these practices always meant to be recognized in the eyes of the law, or do they have other audiences?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patent as Exclusion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/patent-as-exclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/patent-as-exclusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/monsanto_patent.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Monsanto Patent for glyphosate-resistant plants (US version)&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Monsanto Patent for glyphosate-resistant plants (US version)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A patent is effectively a statutory right—created and enforced under the federal &lt;em&gt;Patent Act&lt;/em&gt;, RSC 1985, c P-4—to exclude others from the products of cultural, scientific and technological invention. Patents given their &amp;ldquo;owners&amp;rdquo; a time-limited, exclusive right to make, construct, use and sell the subject matter of the patent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The basic rationale behind patent rights is one about economic incentives. As an intangible good, the inventive idea or design that motivates a patent is by nature non-excludable: once the invention has been created and made public, it is essentially costless for others to reproduce that idea or design in order to make their own products. Because inventions often require considerable up-front and sometimes risky investments, the rationale goes, exclusive patent protections are needed in order provide creators with sufficient financial incentives to create in the first place. According to this argument, if the right to exclude via patent did not exists, creators would have no motivation to produce their intentions and society would suffer as a result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peace and Friendship Treaties</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/peace-and-friendship-treaties/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/peace-and-friendship-treaties/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The early eighteenth-century in what is today Eastern Canada was characterized by political and military struggles and alliances between three powers in the region: the Wabanaki (a political alliance of Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaw, Wolastoqiyik, and Passamaquoddy peoples, and a separate alliance of communities known as the Abenaki), the British, and the French. 1726 saw the end of a three-year war between New England and the Wabanaki, which had been grounded in concerns about colonial expansion northward (including incursions on Indigenous fishing territories and colonial land settlement). In turn, the British were becoming increasingly motivated to forge friendly relationships with the Wabanaki as counter-weight to French power. This period culminated in the signing of the Treaty of 1725 by various parties between that year and 1726.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peace and Friendship Treaty (1725)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1725/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1725/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;This treaty—the first in a line of treaties entered into by the British and Indigenous nations in the Atlantic region—was first signed in Boston in 1725. The same treaty was signed with different Indigenous parties one year later in 1726.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ratification-of-1725-treaty&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ratification of 1725 Treaty&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ratification-of-1725-treaty&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Articles of Submission &amp;amp; Agreements made at Boston in New England by Sanguaarum alias Loron, Arexus Francois Xavier and Meganumbe Delegates from Penobscott Naudgevaek S. Johns Cape Sables and Other Tribes Inhabiting within His Majesties Territories of Nova Scotia and New England __________&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peace and Friendship Treaty (1752)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1752/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/treaty1752/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-alert&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div&gt;&#xA;      &lt;em&gt;The following text is quoted in R v Simon, [1985] 2 SCR 387 at para 6.&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Treaty or Articles of Peace and Friendship Renewed between His Excellency Peregrine Thomas Hopson Esquire Captain General and Governor in Chief in and over His Majesty&amp;rsquo;s Province of Nova Scotia or Acadie. Vice Admiral of the same &amp;amp; Colonel of one of His Majesty&amp;rsquo;s Regiments of Foot, and His Majesty&amp;rsquo;s Council on behalf of His Majesty and Major Jean Baptiste Cope, chief Sachem of the Tribe of Mick Mack Indians Inhabiting the Eastern Coast of the said Province, and Andrew Hadley Martin, Gabriel Martin &amp;amp; Francis Jeremiah, Members and Delegates of the said Tribe, for themselves and their said Tribe their Heirs, and the Heirs of their Heirs forever, Begun made and concluded in the manner, form and Tenor following, vizt:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pennsylvania Coal Co. v Mahon</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/pennsylvania-coal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/pennsylvania-coal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holmes-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Holmes J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#holmes-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a bill in equity brought by the defendants in error to prevent the Pennsylvania Coal Company from mining under their property in such way as to remove the supports and cause a subsidence of the surface and of their house. The bill sets out a deed executed by the Coal Company in 1878, under which the plaintiffs claim. The deed conveys the surface, but, in express terms, reserves the right to remove all the coal under the same, and the grantee takes the premises with the risk, and waives all claim for damages that may arise from mining out the coal. But the plaintiffs say that, whatever may have been the Coal Company&amp;rsquo;s rights, they were taken away by an Act of Pennsylvania, approved May 27, 1921, P.L. 1198, commonly known there as the Kohler Act. The Court of Common Pleas found that, if not restrained, the defendant would cause the damage to prevent which the bill was brought, but denied an injunction, holding that the statute, if applied to this case, would be unconstitutional. On appeal, the Supreme Court of the State agreed that the defendant had contract and property rights protected by the Constitution of the United States, but held that the statute was a legitimate exercise of the police power, and directed a decree for the plaintiffs. A writ of error was granted bringing the case to this Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perry v Clissold</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/perry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/perry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PRIVY COUNCIL&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perry Appellant; and Clissold and Others Respondents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On appeal from the High Court of Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;14 December 1906&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Lord Chancellor, The Earl of Halsbury, Lord Macnaghten, Lord Davey, Lord Robertson, Lord Atkinson, Sir Ford North, Sir Arthur Wilson.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The judgment of their Lordships was delivered by&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;lord-macnaghten-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Lord Macnaghten –&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#lord-macnaghten-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was an appeal from a judgment of the High Court of Australia, dated the 20th of June 1904, reversing a judgment of the Supreme Court of New South Wales. It raised a question under the Lands for Public Purposes Acquisition Act 1880 (44 Vict. No. 16), now superseded by the Public Works Act 1900, which consolidates the law on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piper v Stevenson</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/piper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/piper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;clute-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Clute J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#clute-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff claims as owner and occupier of lots 28 and 29, block &amp;ldquo;A,&amp;rdquo; Marmot street, North Toronto, registered plan No. 722, and asks an injunction restraining the defendant from trespass and for damages for former trespass and forcible entry. The defendant denies that the plaintiff is the owner of the lots in question, and says that he purchased the same from the registered owner thereof, and thereupon entered into possession of the same and built a fence thereon and planted a crop, which are the trespasses complained of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planning Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/planning-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/planning-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuance of lawfully existing non-conformities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;86(1) Subject to sections 88 to 91, the enactment of a new zoning by-law does not affect any of the following that lawfully existed before the enactment of the new zoning by-law:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) a building;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) a parcel of land;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(c) the use of land, or the intensity of a use of land.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Problems of Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/possession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/possession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In class this week, we will focus on two short problems:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h3 id=&#34;problem-1-first-possession&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Problem 1: First Possession&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#problem-1-first-possession&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Two children are playing on a beach and see an old abandoned boat washed up on shore. They both run for it. The faster one nearly reaches the vessel but trips on a piece of driftwood and sprains their ankle. The second child then overtakes the first, jumps on board and declares the boat &amp;ldquo;mine!&amp;rdquo;. Who owns the boat?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Property in Your Cells</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/property-cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/property-cells/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://imagebank.nih.gov/details.cfm?imageid=1463&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/hela.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Source: National Institutes of Health, 2013&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Source: National Institutes of Health, 2013&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This week, as we continue to study basic patterns of common law argument, we will look at the issue of whether or not individuals can or should hold legally-recognized property rights in their biological cells. Various legal rules, from criminal law statutes to tort principles, aim to protect a person&amp;rsquo;s bodily integrity from harm or intrusion. But in some circumstances, a person&amp;rsquo;s biological cells might be removed or become detached from their body. Once those cells are separated from the body of a living person, this opens up the possibility that the law might regard them as the subject of property.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Property Law: Making the Market</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/making-market/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/making-market/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, we will study several controversies, concepts and legal doctrines that normally make up the field of property law in most Canadian law schools. As in your other courses, you will gain a solid understanding of legal rules &amp;ldquo;on the books&amp;rdquo; that address a range of issues (local, national and global) and you will see how those rules have changed and been adapted over time. But we will also address legal rules with a specific goal in mind&amp;ndash;one that goes beyond a basic proficiency in the common law or legislation. Our goal is to understand and develop a thoughtful answer to the following question:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protection of Property Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/protection-property/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/protection-property/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2 In this Act,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) &amp;ldquo;occupier&amp;rdquo; includes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(i) a person who is in possession of premises, or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ii) a person who has responsibility for and control over the condition of premises or the activities there carried on, or control over persons allowed to enter the premises,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(d) &amp;ldquo;premises&amp;rdquo; means lands and structures, or either of them, and includes trailers and portable structures designed or used for residence, business or shelter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Public Perceptions of Squatters</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/squatters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/squatters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Read this &lt;a href=&#34;&#34; &gt;HuffPost new article&lt;/a&gt; on &amp;ldquo;squatters&amp;rsquo; rights&amp;rdquo; and the housing crisis in Detroit. What assumptions and pre-conceptions about adverse possession are contained in the article?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Public Policy Revisited</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/public-policy-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/public-policy-revisited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of Week 14, we discussed the Supreme Court&amp;rsquo;s resistance in &lt;em&gt;Noble and Wolf v Alley&lt;/em&gt; to apply the public policy doctrine to invalidate a discriminatory restrictive covenant. Despite Justice Mackay&amp;rsquo;s robust engagement with this doctrine in &lt;em&gt;Re Drummond Wren&lt;/em&gt;, it would not receive sustained attention by the Canadian courts until more than three decades later. The Ontario Court of Appeal returned to the challenge of applying the public policy doctrine to &amp;ldquo;private&amp;rdquo; property arrangements in &lt;em&gt;Canada Trust Co v Ontario (Human Rights Commission)&lt;/em&gt;, in the context of a testamentary bequest via a charitable trust.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R v Cappy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cappy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cappy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;henderson-ja-dissenting-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Henderson J.A. (dissenting) &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#henderson-ja-dissenting-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On 15th February 1951 the respondents purchased the lands known as Oakwood Stadium and on 19th May 1951, they began to promote and conduct in the stadium stock car races.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Oakwood Stadium consists of an oval open space upon which there is sitting accommodation partly in open stands and partly in a covered stand. This stadium at the time of the passing of the by-law in 1948 and prior to the occupation of the respondents in February 1951 was suitable for permitting members of the public to witness various kinds of sport contests including the playing of soccer, rugby and track and field events. Prior to February 1951 there was a cinder track 18 feet wide around the perimeter of the playing field suitable for foot-races.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R v Syliboy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/syliboy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/syliboy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;patterson-acting-co-ct-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Patterson (Acting) Co. Ct. J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#patterson-acting-co-ct-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The defendant, who is the grand chief of the Mick Macks of Nova Scotia was convicted under the Lands and Forests Act, 1926 (N.S.), c. 4, of having in his possession at Askilton in the County of Inverness on November 4, last fifteen green pelts, fourteen muskrat and one fox. He made no attempt to deny having the pelts, indeed frankly admits having them, but claims that as an Indian he is not bound by the provisions of the Act, but has by Treaty the right to hunt and trap at all times. Every now and then for a number of years one has heard that our Indians were making these claims but, so far as I know, the matter has never been before a Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re Drummond Wren</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/drummond/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/drummond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mackay-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Mackay J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mackay-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an application brought by Drummond Wren, owner of certain lands registered in the Registry Office for the County of York, to have declared invalid a restrictive covenant assumed by him when he purchased these lands and which he agreed to exact from his assigns, namely, — “Land not to be sold to Jews or persons of objectionable nationality.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The application is made by way of special leave and pursuant to s. 60 of the &lt;em&gt;Conveyancing and Law of Property Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.O. 1937, c. 152, and Rules 603 and 604 of The Rules of Practice and Procedure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re Walker</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/walker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/walker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;middleton-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Middleton J.A. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#middleton-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An appeal from the judgment of Mr. Justice Riddell pronounced on the 27th September, 1924, declaring that the estate of the late Ellen Fitze Walker does not include any part of the estate of the late John Walker undisposed of by her at the time of her death.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;John Walker died on the 27th March, 1903, and first made his will, bearing date the 17th November, 1902, which was in due course admitted to probate, his widow being his sole executrix. At the time of his death his estate amounted to approximately $16,000. By his will he provided as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reading Harrison</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/reading-and-rereading-harrison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/reading-and-rereading-harrison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading-harrison&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Reading &lt;em&gt;Harrison&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#reading-harrison&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/polo_park.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;By Elyse Loewen, CC BY NC SA 4.0&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;By Elyse Loewen, CC BY NC SA 4.0&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first case we’ll read in this course&amp;ndash;the Supreme Court of Canada’s decision in &lt;em&gt;Harrison v Carswell&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;is about a labour dispute at the Polo Park shopping mall in Winnipeg in the mid-1970s. That setting may not strike you as obviously important or exciting, but &lt;em&gt;Harrison&lt;/em&gt; is arguably one of the Supreme Court&amp;rsquo;s most important decisions for what it reveals about the central problems and debates in property law, and&amp;ndash;more important still&amp;ndash;for what it shows us about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; judges and lawyers engage in those debates using the patterns and practices of common law legal argument.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regional Municipality of Waterloo v Persons Unknown and to be Ascertained</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/waterloo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/waterloo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;valente-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Valente J. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#valente-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The issue in this application of The Regional Municipality of Waterloo (the ‘Region’) concerns the prohibition against erecting any type of structure, including a tent, on the Region-owned property, municipally known as 100 Victoria Street North, in the city of Kitchener (the ‘Property’). More generally, however, the Region’s application touches on the unfortunate, complex and nationwide social issue of homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-by-law&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;strong&gt;The By-Law&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-by-law&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is undisputed that the &lt;em&gt;Municipal Act&lt;/em&gt; gives the Region the express authority to pass by-laws respecting its public assets and the protection of persons and property (see , 9, and 11(2)). It is also acknowledged that the &lt;em&gt;Trespass to Property Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.O. 1990, c.T21, as amended, ss. 3 to 8 (the &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;TPA&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;) allows an occupier of premises to prohibit or regulate entry onto premises and that the Courts have recognized municipalities as occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restraints on Alienation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/restraints-on-alienation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/restraints-on-alienation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having now studied the roles of &lt;em&gt;possession&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;exclusion&lt;/em&gt; in common law property, this week we move on to examine the context of &lt;em&gt;exit&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;that is, how it is that owners extract themselves from property relations. Central to this context is the right to &lt;em&gt;alienate&lt;/em&gt; property and the power of owners to place restrictions on alienability. Recall that we have already encountered alienation and restraints on alienation in the context of Aboriginal title going back to the Royal Proclamation in 1763. As we learn this week, the extent to which landowners can and should be able transfer their property rights to others and to place limits on alienation has long raised some pervasive controversies in common law property.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictive Covenants </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/restrictive-covenants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/restrictive-covenants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/housing_sign.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Sign on a traffic post at the Robie Street / Willow Tree intersection in Halifax.&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Sign on a traffic post at the Robie Street / Willow Tree intersection in Halifax.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please listen to this recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kut.org/austin/2021-09-10/west-austin-affordable-housing-lawsuit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;NPR Radio documentary about 3000 Funston Street,&lt;/a&gt; a piece of vacant land in the Brykerwoods neighbourhood of Austin, Texas. The podcast tells the story of how a restrictive covenant is shaping urban development in the context of the city&amp;rsquo;s long-term strategy to improve access to affordable housing and achieve a more equitable distribution of that housing across the municipality. If you prefer, the website also contains a print version of the radio documentary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictive Covenants and Public Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/covenants-public-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/covenants-public-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Certain &amp;ldquo;private&amp;rdquo; forms of land-use regulation are still in widespread use. One of the most pervasive—but often least noticed—is the &lt;em&gt;restrictive covenant&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From one point of view, restrictive covenants look like a fairly straightforward promise by one landowner to another—a promise to refrain from doing something on one&amp;rsquo;s own land. One landowner might promise not to cut down the trees in their yard, for example, or promise not to paint their house a garish shade of bright green. But from a legal perspective, restrictive covenants are much more than this. Not only do covenants represent a sort of contractual promise between parties, they help to define the durable &amp;ldquo;bundle of rights&amp;rdquo; in the land itself—that is, covenants are said to &lt;em&gt;run with the land&lt;/em&gt; and can, at least in theory, long outlast the original parties to the covenant. This possibility raises some difficult questions for courts in how they define the basic character of covenants along with their consequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Blue Mountain-Birch Cove</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/blue-mountain-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/blue-mountain-revisited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Briefly review the facts of the &lt;a href=&#34;../week12/#problem-blue-mountain-birch-cove-lakes&#34; &gt;Blue Mountain-Birch Cove Case study we explored in Week 12&lt;/a&gt;, then consider the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Does the decision in &lt;em&gt;Canadian Pacific Railway v Vancouver&lt;/em&gt; strengthen the Annapolis Group&amp;rsquo;s claim in &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; expropriation against the Halifax Regional Municipality? Why or why not?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What changed in &lt;em&gt;Annapolis Group Inc v Halifax Regional Municipality&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Suppose that Annapolis Group Inc. is a land development company incorporated in the United States or Mexico. How might the results of its claim to &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; (or &amp;ldquo;indirect&amp;rdquo;) expropriation differ if it were to make a claim under Article 1110 of &lt;em&gt;NAFA&lt;/em&gt; rather than in Canada&amp;rsquo;s domestic courts (which it could still do as a legacy claim until July 2022)? How would it differ under &lt;em&gt;CUSMA&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Riparian Rights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/water-rights/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/water-rights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;riparian owner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the owner of land bounding upon a river or other watercourse. The traditional presumption of English common law is that a riparian owner owns the bed of a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-navigable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; river or stream to the centre of the watercourse: &lt;em&gt;ad medium filum aquae&lt;/em&gt;. Consequently, a riparian owner who holds land on both sides of a river considered &amp;ldquo;non-navigable&amp;rdquo; owns the entire riverbed and has exclusive rights to the river&amp;rsquo;s use .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rivers and Streams Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/rivers-and-streams-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/rivers-and-streams-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1. All persons shall, subject to the provisions in this Act contained, have, and are hereby declared always to have had, floating down during the spring, summer and autumn freshets, the right to, and may float and transmit saw-logs and all other timber of every kind, and all rafts and crafts, down all rivers, creeks and streams; and no person shall by felling trees or placing any other obstruction in or across any such river, creek or stream, prevent the passage thereof; and in case it may be necessary to remove any obstruction from such river, creek or stream, or construct any apron, dam, slide, gate-lock, boom, or other work therein or thereon, necessary to facilitate the floating and transmitting such saw-logs and other timber, rafts or crafts, down the same, then it shall be lawful for the person requiring so to float and transmit such saw-logs and other timber, rafts and crafts, and it is hereby declared always to have been lawful to remove such obstruction, and to construct such apron, dam, slide, gate-lock, boom or other work necessary for the purposes aforesaid, doing no unnecessary damage to the said river, creek or stream, or to the banks thereof.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Royal Proclamation (1763)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/royal-proclamation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/royal-proclamation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/imgs/rp1763.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And whereas it is just and reasonable, and essential to our Interest, and the Security of our Colonies, that the several Nations or Tribes of Indians with whom We are connected, and who live under our Protection, should not be molested or disturbed in the Possession of such Parts of Our Dominions and Territories as, not having been ceded to or purchased by Us, are reserved to them, or any of them, as their Hunting Grounds,&amp;ndash;We do therefore, with the Advice of our Privy Council, declare it to be our Royal Will and Pleasure, that no Governor or Commander in Chief in any of our Colonies of Quebec, East Florida, or West Florida, do presume, upon any Pretence whatever, to grant Warrants of Survey, or pass any Patents for Lands beyond the Bounds of their respective Governments, as described in their Commissions: as also that no Governor or Commander in Chief in any of our other Colonies or Plantations in America do presume for the present, and until our further Pleasure be known, to grant Warrants of Survey, or pass Patents for any Lands beyond the Heads or Sources of any of the Rivers which fall into the Atlantic Ocean from the West and North West, or upon any Lands whatever, which, not having been ceded to or purchased by Us as aforesaid, are reserved to the said Indians, or any of them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Saint-Romuald (City) v Olivier</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/saintromuald/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/saintromuald/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;binnie-j--&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Binnie J.  —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#binnie-j--&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Court’s objective on this appeal is to find the proper balance between an individual’s right to the continued use and enjoyment of his or her property and the power of the community, expressed through the local municipality, to enhance, by changing the land use regulations, the amenities of surrounding and other affected landowners. As the case arises in Quebec, the specific issue raised is the limitation of previously acquired rights under the &lt;em&gt;Civil Code&lt;/em&gt;. However, as this is a &lt;em&gt;public&lt;/em&gt; law matter, the principles of land use regulation applicable in the common law provinces concerning legal non-conforming uses are also relevant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Section 7 and the Evolving Right to Shelter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/intro-section7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/intro-section7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our discussion of acquired rights and the problem of regulating short-term rentals last week, we touched on the idea that a central issue for the Halifax Regional Municipality (HRM) and other municipal governments in Canada is access to affordable housing. There is growing awareness that Halifax is facing a crisis in housing affordability and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/homeless-report-2020-covid-19-affordable-housing-association-of-nova-scotia-1.5805458&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;dramatic rise in the number of people who experience chronic homelessness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Addressing homelessness and access to housing engages a complex set of legal and policy issues, actors and decision-making networks. One aspect of this context in which Canadian courts have been especially active is the constitutional right of homeless persons to access and shelter in public spaces—namely, municipal parks—in order to meet their immediate needs. As the problem below describes, the role of these rights and challenges to their realization gained national attention in Halifax in summer 2021, after a series of forced evictions of people living in temporary and emergency shelters on municipal lands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shelfer v City of London Electrical Lighting Co.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/shelfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/shelfer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The defendant in this case, the City of London Electric Lighting Company, operated large engines and other heavy machinery that caused damage to the foundations of a pub, the Waterman&amp;rsquo;s Arms, leased by the plaintiff, Shelfer, as well as a lot of noise and other &amp;ldquo;annoyances&amp;rdquo;. There was no question about the existence of the nuisance—the only issue before the court was what type of remedy should be available to the plaintiff.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-Term Rentals in HRM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/short-term-rentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/short-term-rentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/B0aCvAVSX8E&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/apartment.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Source: Étienne Beauregard-Riverin on Unsplash&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Source: Étienne Beauregard-Riverin on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As in many cities across Canada, short-term retals have become a hot button issue in the Halifax Regional Municipality (HRM). According to the HRM website:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Short-Term Rentals (STRs) are temporary overnight accommodations rented out for a few nights or weeks at a time. In recent years, the prevalence and popularity of STRs has grown through online platforms like Airbnb, VRBO and HomeAway. While STRs provide a unique form of a tourist accommodation and can have benefits for the local economy, their recent popularity raises concerns about their impact on residential neighborhoods and the availability of properties for long-term rental [i.e. the rental housing supply].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sources of Public Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/public-policy-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/public-policy-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the more remarkable aspects of the decision in &lt;em&gt;Re Drummond Wren&lt;/em&gt; is its reliance on different sources of domestic and international law to ground the Court&amp;rsquo;s finding that the restrictive covenant in issue was contrary to public policy. As you analyze the &lt;em&gt;3000 Funston Street&lt;/em&gt; problem for this week, consider what role the following sources might play.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Article 11 of the United Nations General Assembly&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights&lt;/em&gt; (1966) recognizes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Southwind v Canada</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/southwind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/southwind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;karakatsanis-j&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Karakatsanis J.&amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#karakatsanis-j&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the twentieth century, Canada needed more&#xA;electricity to fuel Winnipeg&amp;rsquo;s economic growth. The governments of&#xA;Canada, Manitoba, and Ontario decided to create a water reservoir in&#xA;northern Ontario to power hydroelectricity generation. They settled on&#xA;Lac Seul, which flows into both Ontario and Manitoba, and determined&#xA;that if they raised the water level of Lac Seul by 10 feet, or&#xA;approximately 3 metres, they could generate substantial electricity.&#xA;Construction of the dam was completed in 1929 and the water steadily&#xA;rose through the 1930s. The project was a success for the three&#xA;governments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>St. Catherine&#39;s Milling and Lumber Co. v R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stcatherines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stcatherines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background to the Case&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For more than a hundred years after it was enacted, the Royal Proclamation of 1763 stood as the British Crown&amp;rsquo;s most authoritative statement on Aboriginal title. But during this period the Proclamation itself received little to no scrutiny in the common law courts. This changed dramatically when the Chancery Division of the High Court of Ontario issued its decision in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling and Lumber Co. v R&lt;/em&gt; in 1886, followed by subsequent appeals all the way to the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council—at that time, Canada&amp;rsquo;s highest court of appeal. The case would chart the course for the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title in Canada for well into the next century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stuartburn (Municipality) v Kiansky</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stuartburn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stuartburn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wright-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Wright J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#wright-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an application by the Rural Municipality of Stuartburn (”the Municipality”) for a declaration that its Reeve, the respondent David Theodore Kiansky (”Kiansky”) is disqualified from holding office.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Municipality alleges Kiansky does not meet the election requirements as set forth in &lt;em&gt;The Municipal Act&lt;/em&gt;, S.M. 1996, c. 58 - Chap. M225 and &lt;em&gt;The Local Authorities Election Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.M. 1987, c. L180 (”the &lt;em&gt;LAE Act&lt;/em&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Styles of Argument</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/style/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/style/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What makes a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;persuasive&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; legal argument? An answer to the question is often fundamental to resolving a dispute in court or convincing a political decision-maker to make some kind of legal or policy change.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One way to answer this question is to focus on &amp;ldquo;style&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This idea of style will seem pretty wishy-washy to some people at first. Aren&amp;rsquo;t legal arguments clear, logical, and rational? Knowing enough about the law and the facts, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t we always be able to determine the correct legal answer to a problem?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tenure and Estates</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tenure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tenure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the common law doctrine of tenure all land under the dominion of the English crown is held “mediately or immediately, of the king”—that is, the crown has “radical title” to all land under its political dominion. William the Conqueror declared that all land in England was literally the king’s property; everyone else had to settle for the privilege of holding it for him—the privilege of &lt;em&gt;tenure&lt;/em&gt; (from the Norman French word “tenir”—to hold). Tenurial rights were intensely personal in early feudal society: the right to hold land was a privilege granted by the crown in exchange for an oath of allegiance and a promise of military service by the tenant—the oath of homage. The word homage derives from the French word &lt;em&gt;homme&lt;/em&gt;—literally “man”—precisely because the ceremony surrounding the oath created not only the right of tenure, but a political and military relationship between “lord and man.”  In exchange for the tenant’s loyal support, or &lt;em&gt;fealty&lt;/em&gt;, the lord warranted the tenant’s right to hold a plot of land, called a fief, or &lt;em&gt;fee&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terra Nullius</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/terra-nullius/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/terra-nullius/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terra nullius&lt;/em&gt; is a term that refers to a “territory without a master.” It is a term used in public international law to describe a space that can be inhabited but that does not belong to a state, meaning the land is not owned by anyone. In fact, when a State or an entity describes a land as a &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt;, the land is in reality occupied – by a nation or a minority – but the term has oftentimes been used in order to legitimize state occupation and colonization. In international public law, when the definition &lt;em&gt;terra nullius&lt;/em&gt; is given to a land, it can legally legitimize its occupation and acquisition of sovereignty by another nation, under the doctrine of discovery, which the International Court of Justice (ICJ) has approved as a legal method of acquisition of territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The British Settlement of Halifax (1749)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/context/british-settlement-halifax/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/context/british-settlement-halifax/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/media/halifax_1749.jpg&#34;&#xA;    alt=&#34;Halifax, 1749.&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;p&gt;Halifax, 1749.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Halifax was settled by the British in Mi&amp;rsquo;kma&amp;rsquo;ki without lawful authority or consent from the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq, on land the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq call K’jipuktuk. Like other places in Canada, Halifax&amp;rsquo;s colonial origins are rooted in the violent displacement and dispossession of Indigenous peoples. This legacy forms a central piece of the legal context for the city today.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Britain&amp;rsquo;s settlement of Halifax in 1749 was interposed between and closely linked with the Peace and Friendship Treaties signed by the British and Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq in 1725 and then in 1752 and 1760-61. As noted above, interpreting the terms of these treaties is a complicated exercise, but it is unambiguous that, as nation-to-nation agreements, they are based on the ideas of building ongoing relationships and of reciprocity. Just as Halifax was settled in apparent breach of the 1725 treaty, the 1752 treaty and subsequent treaties might be seen as a direct response and attempt to repair the relationship between the Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq and the British in the aftermath.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Path of Law</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/holmes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/holmes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we study law we are not studying a mystery but a well-known profession. We are studying what we shall want in order to appear before judges, or to advise people in such a way as to keep them out of court. The reason why it is a profession, why people will pay lawyers to argue for them or to advise them, is that in societies like ours the command of the public force is intrusted to the judges in certain cases, and the whole power of the state will be put forth, if necessary, to carry out their judgments and decrees. People want to know under what circumstances and how far they will run the risk of coming against what is so much stronger than themselves, and hence it becomes a business to find out when this danger is to be feared. The object of our study, then, is prediction, the prediction of the incidence of the public force through the instrumentality of the courts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Right to Shelter in Halifax </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/problems/halifax-right-to-shelter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/problems/halifax-right-to-shelter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our applied problem this week asks you to engage directly with events surrounding the right to shelter in Halifax over the past few years, including attempts by unhoused people to create shelters in public parks around the city during the pandemic and responses by neighbours, police, and the HRM Council.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please start by reviewing the following sources:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A CBC News article entitled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/what-a-b-c-court-ruling-could-mean-for-halifax-park-evictions-1.6319104&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;What a B.C. court ruling could mean for Halifax park evictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, published soon after the British Columbia Supreme Court released its decision in &lt;em&gt;Bamberger&lt;/em&gt;, below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rise of the First Nations Land Management Regime in Canada: A Critical Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fnlma-yellowhead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/fnlma-yellowhead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-i-first-nations-land-management-foundations&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Part I: First Nations Land Management Foundations&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#part-i-first-nations-land-management-foundations&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the 2015 federal election campaign, the Liberal Party of Canada&#xA;campaigned on a platform of significant commitments to Indigenous&#xA;peoples, including the promise to &amp;ldquo;renew the relationship between Canada&#xA;and Indigenous Peoples.&amp;rdquo; But tellingly, they framed their platform as&#xA;&amp;ldquo;both a right thing to do and a surefire way to economic growth.&amp;rdquo; In&#xA;the emerging era of sectoral self-governance, the First Nations Land&#xA;Management Regime has become a key feature not only in the federal&#xA;government&amp;rsquo;s notion  of the &amp;ldquo;right thing,&amp;rdquo; but also their plans to chip away at the &lt;em&gt;Indian&#xA;Act&lt;/em&gt; and make First Nations more &amp;ldquo;economically independent.&amp;rdquo; Of course,&#xA;this economic growth or independence does not include a redistribution&#xA;of land or resources, rather it is an expectation that First Nations&#xA;should support their members through economic activities exclusively on&#xA;reserve lands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unlawful Dispossession of Japanese Canadians</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/adams-stangerross/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/adams-stangerross/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While interning Japanese Canadians, the federal government seized control of all of their real and personal property within the &amp;ldquo;protected area in British Columbia.&amp;rdquo; In the spring of 1943, federal officials began to sell virtually everything that the government had taken, often below market value. Families lost heirlooms, vibrant businesses, and everyday possessions. They lost cars, boats, books, toys, furniture, and cameras. They lost homes and farms. Beyond the tangible, Canadians of Japanese descent lost opportunities, neighbourhoods, and communities. They lost connections to place. They lost retirements, livelihoods, and educations. They lost agency over their property and life choices. They lost, as Rikizo Yoneyama poignantly expressed in a defiant letter to the Minister of Justice, &amp;ldquo;more than just a home.&amp;rdquo; Japanese Canadians, he lamented, lost &amp;ldquo;the foundation of security and freedom as Canadian citizens.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Assumptions About Law and the Economy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/law-and-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/other/law-and-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-assumptions-about-law-and-the-economy&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Three assumptions about law and the economy&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#three-assumptions-about-law-and-the-economy&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The three key assumptions sketched below are pervasive in court cases, in public policy forums, and in the media when people are debating and discussing the relationship between law and the economy. They run so deep that we often fail to notice them. The problem with these three assumptions&amp;ndash;and a failure to treat them as such&amp;ndash;is that they tend to view &amp;ldquo;law&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;economy&amp;rdquo; as separate and distinct phenomena, instead of two aspects of social life that constitute one another. These assumptions draw our attention away from the central idea that economies and economic exchange cannot exist without some underlying legal rules or norms. What forms of economic exchange exist&amp;ndash;and who benefits from those exchanges&amp;ndash;are therefore determined in large part by those who shape the law and the choices they make.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trespass to Land</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/trespass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/trespass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The name of the most familiar tort protecting real property, trespass, was originally the name of an entire family of actions that first emerged in the 12th and 13th centuries. A plaintiff would commence his case by going to the royal Chancery and purchasing a writ commanding the defendant to come before the courts and explain why he had done such-and-such a thing against the plaintiff’s rights. The Latin phrases used by the Chancery clerks who filled out the writs – and which the royal courts insisted on when hearing a case – came to define individual forms of action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tsilhqot’in Nation v. British Columbia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tsilhqotin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tsilhqotin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McLachlin C.J.C. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is the test for Aboriginal title to land? If title is established, what rights does it confer? Does the British Columbia &lt;em&gt;Forest Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.B.C. 1996, c. 157, apply to land covered by Aboriginal title? What are the constitutional constraints on provincial regulation of land under Aboriginal title? Finally, how are broader public interests to be reconciled with the rights conferred by Aboriginal title? These are among the important questions raised by this appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tulk v Moxhay </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/tulk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/tulk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the year 1808 the Plaintiff, being then the owner in fee of the vacant piece of ground in Leicester Square, as well as of several of the houses forming the Square, sold the piece of ground by the description of &amp;ldquo;Leicester Square garden or pleasure ground, with the equestrian statue then standing in the centre thereof, and the iron railing and stone work round the same,&amp;rdquo; to one Elms in fee: and the deed of conveyance contained a covenant by Elms, for himself, his heirs, and assigns, with the Plaintiff, his heirs, executors, and administrators, &amp;ldquo;that Elms, his heirs, and assigns should, and would from time to time, and at all times thereafter at his and their own costs and charges, keep and maintain the said piece of ground and square garden, and the iron railing round the same in its then form, and in sufficient and proper repair as a square garden and pleasure ground, in an open state, uncovered with any buildings, in neat and ornamental order; and that it should be lawful for the inhabitants of Leicester Square, tenants of the Plaintiff, on payment of a reasonable rent for the same, to have keys at their own expense and the privilege of admission therewith at any time or times into the said square garden and pleasure ground.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victoria (City) v Adams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/victoria-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/victoria-city/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ross-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ross J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ross-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This litigation arises from what Senior District Judge Atkins in &lt;em&gt;Pottinger v. Miami (City)&lt;/em&gt;, 810 F. Supp. 1551 (U.S. Dist. Ct. S.D. Fla. 1992) at 1554 described as:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; an inevitable conflict between the need of homeless individuals to perform essential, life-sustaining acts in public and the responsibility of the government to maintain orderly, aesthetically pleasing public parks and streets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The particular issue in this litigation concerns the prohibition against erecting temporary shelter on public property that is contained in the Parks Regulation Bylaw and the Streets and Traffic Bylaw (the “Bylaws”) of the City of Victoria (the “City”). Natalie Adams, Yann Chartier, Amber Overall, Alymanda Wawai, Conrad Fletcher, Sebastien Matte, Simon Ralph, Heather Turnquist and David Arthur Johnston (the “Defendants”), who are all homeless people living in the City, contend that this prohibition infringes the rights of homeless people to life, liberty and security of the person in a manner not in accordance with the principles of fundamental justice, contrary to s. 7 of the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms, Part I of the Constitution Act, 1982&lt;/em&gt;, [&lt;em&gt;Charter&lt;/em&gt;] being Schedule B to the &lt;em&gt;Canada Act 1982&lt;/em&gt;, (U.K.), 1982, c. 11. The intervener, the British Columbia Civil Liberties Association (the “BCCLA”), supports the defendants in this contention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victoria Park Racing and Recreational Grounds Co Ltd v Taylor </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/victoriapark/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/victoriapark/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;latham-cj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Latham C.J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#latham-cj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an appeal from a judgment for the defendants given by Nicholas J. in an action by the Victoria Park Racing and Recreation Grounds Co Ltd against Taylor and others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff company carries on the business of racing upon a racecourse known as Victoria Park. The defendant Taylor is the owner of land near the racecourse. He has placed an elevated platform on his land from which it is possible to see what takes place on the racecourse and to read the information which appears on notice boards on the course as to the starters, scratchings, etc, and the winners of the races. The defendant Angles stands on the platform and through a telephone comments upon and describes the races in a particularly vivid manner and announces the names of the winning horses. The defendant the Commonwealth Broadcasting Corporation holds a broadcasting licence under the regulations made under the &lt;em&gt;Wireless Telegraphy Act 1905-1936&lt;/em&gt; and carries on the business of broadcasting from station 2 UW. This station broadcasts the commentaries and descriptions given by Angles. The plaintiff wants to have the broadcasting stopped because it prevents people from going to the races and paying for admission. The evidence shows that some people prefer hearing about the races as seen by Angles to seeing the races for themselves. The plaintiff contends that the damage which it thus suffers gives, in all the circumstances, a cause of action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Land Title Clarification?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/land-title-clarification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/land-title-clarification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Downey&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Beals&lt;/em&gt;, above, discuss some of the history behind African Nova Scotian settlement in the province and describe how the &lt;em&gt;LTCA&lt;/em&gt; and its predecessor legislation was enacted to transform possessory rights into formal land titles. One prominent idea in these cases is that the lack of clear land title is a central cause of economic underdevelopment in African Nova Scotian communities&amp;ndash;and is one that can be adequately remedied through legal processes designed to recognize and formalize longstanding possessory rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wildlife Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/wildlife/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/relationships/wildlife/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--2(w) “fur-bearing animal” means beaver, muskrat, red squir- rel, mink, otter, skunk, weasel, fisher, marten, lynx, bobcat, cougar, fox, coyote, raccoon and any other non-domesticated animal which may be designated as a fur-bearing animal by the Governor in Coun- cil, and includes any part of such animal, but does not include bear or snowshoe hare;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4 (1) Subject to subsection (2), the property in all wildlife situate within the Province, while in a state of nature, is hereby declared to be vested in Her Majesty in right of the Province and no person shall acquire any right or property therein otherwise than in accordance with this Act and the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wills Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/wills-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/wills-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;27 Where any real property is devised to any person without any words of limitation, such devise shall be construed to pass the fee simple or the whole estate or interest which the testator had the power to dispose of by will in such real property, unless a contrary intention appears by the will.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
