<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Estates on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/estates/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Estates on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/estates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Basic Estates and Future Interests</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/basic-estates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/basic-estates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will begin by examining two possessory estates—the &lt;strong&gt;fee simple absolute&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;life estate&lt;/strong&gt;—and two future interests &amp;hellip; —the &lt;strong&gt;reversion&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;remainder&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fee-simple-absolute&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Fee Simple Absolute&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-fee-simple-absolute&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fee simple absolute is the most complete interest in land that the law will recognize. When we say that “O owns Greenacre without any further qualification, what we actually mean is that O owns a presently possessory fee simple absolute in Greenacre. The key distinguishing characteristic of the fee simple absolute is that it has no inherent end—it is an estate of indefinite duration. It is descendible, devisable, and alienable inter vivos; so it can be transferred to a new owner, but it cannot be destroyed. At most, it can be carved up into lesser estates and interests for a while, and we will spend most of the rest of this chapter understanding how that happens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conveyancing Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/conveyancing-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/conveyancing-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;13 Except where a contrary intention appears by the conveyance,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) where words of limitation are not used, the conveyance conveys the whole property right that the party conveying had power to dispose of by the conveyance, including, in the case of real property, the fee simple;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re Walker</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/walker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/walker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;middleton-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Middleton J.A. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#middleton-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An appeal from the judgment of Mr. Justice Riddell pronounced on the 27th September, 1924, declaring that the estate of the late Ellen Fitze Walker does not include any part of the estate of the late John Walker undisposed of by her at the time of her death.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;John Walker died on the 27th March, 1903, and first made his will, bearing date the 17th November, 1902, which was in due course admitted to probate, his widow being his sole executrix. At the time of his death his estate amounted to approximately $16,000. By his will he provided as follows:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stuartburn (Municipality) v Kiansky</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stuartburn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stuartburn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wright-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Wright J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#wright-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an application by the Rural Municipality of Stuartburn (”the Municipality”) for a declaration that its Reeve, the respondent David Theodore Kiansky (”Kiansky”) is disqualified from holding office.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Municipality alleges Kiansky does not meet the election requirements as set forth in &lt;em&gt;The Municipal Act&lt;/em&gt;, S.M. 1996, c. 58 - Chap. M225 and &lt;em&gt;The Local Authorities Election Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.M. 1987, c. L180 (”the &lt;em&gt;LAE Act&lt;/em&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tenure and Estates</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tenure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tenure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the common law doctrine of tenure all land under the dominion of the English crown is held “mediately or immediately, of the king”—that is, the crown has “radical title” to all land under its political dominion. William the Conqueror declared that all land in England was literally the king’s property; everyone else had to settle for the privilege of holding it for him—the privilege of &lt;em&gt;tenure&lt;/em&gt; (from the Norman French word “tenir”—to hold). Tenurial rights were intensely personal in early feudal society: the right to hold land was a privilege granted by the crown in exchange for an oath of allegiance and a promise of military service by the tenant—the oath of homage. The word homage derives from the French word &lt;em&gt;homme&lt;/em&gt;—literally “man”—precisely because the ceremony surrounding the oath created not only the right of tenure, but a political and military relationship between “lord and man.”  In exchange for the tenant’s loyal support, or &lt;em&gt;fealty&lt;/em&gt;, the lord warranted the tenant’s right to hold a plot of land, called a fief, or &lt;em&gt;fee&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wills Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/wills-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/wills-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;27 Where any real property is devised to any person without any words of limitation, such devise shall be construed to pass the fee simple or the whole estate or interest which the testator had the power to dispose of by will in such real property, unless a contrary intention appears by the will.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
