<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chapter 4 on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chapter 4 on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bamberger v Vancouver</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/bamberger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/bamberger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;kirchner-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Kirchner J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#kirchner-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. INTRODUCTION&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1984, an encampment of some 60 tents was established at the site of what would become CRAB Park at Portside in Vancouver. The encampment was a protest designed to pressure government authorities into creating a public park at the site. The name of the park is taken from the acronym for the activist group—Create a Real Available Beach Committee—that envisioned the establishment of a waterfront public park in an area of the city short of green space. The community activism and the camp protest had its desired effect and, in 1987, CRAB Park at Portside (“CRAB Park” or the “Park”) was established as a Vancouver public park on federal port land leased by the City. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Committee for the Commonwealth of Canada v Canada</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;The following case dealt with the issue of whether restrictions on political activity (distributing leaflets) at an airport as public property were in violation of the applicants&amp;rsquo; freedom of expression protected by the Charter. In the course of their decisions, the judges discussed broader principles applicable to understanding limitations on government ownership of property.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;lheureux-dubé-j-concurring-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  L&amp;rsquo;Heureux-Dubé J. (concurring) &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#lheureux-dub%c3%a9-j-concurring-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The appellant takes a hard line in urging this Court to allow the appeal, submitting that as owner of property, the government has the right to exclude whomever it wants, and to impose conditions on invitees to its property without limitation by the Charter:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heegsma v. Hamilton (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/heegsma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/heegsma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ramsay-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ramsay J. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ramsay-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The applicants are 14 homeless individuals who apply for a&#xA;declaration that the City of Hamilton&amp;rsquo;s enforcement of its Parks by-law&#xA;during the period from August 2021 to August 2023 breached their right&#xA;under the Charter to life, liberty and security of the person (s.7) and&#xA;to equal benefit of the law (s.15). They seek damages from the City.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The applicants say that they were evicted from encampments during&#xA;the period from August 2021 to August 2023 in breach of the Charter, and&#xA;that they suffered harm as a result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indigenous Legal Orders and Housing on Reserve Lands</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/reserve-housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/reserve-housing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Professors Val Napoleon and Emily Snyder have recently published a study of housing on reserve and the role of Indigenous property laws in four Indigenous communities in northwestern British Columbia. As Napoleon and Snyder describe in the introduction to that study:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Paul Nadasdy has observed that in the negotiation of their land claim agreement, the Kluane First Nation in the Yukon &amp;ldquo;translate their complex reciprocal relationship with the land into an equally complex but very different language of ‘property.’&amp;rdquo; According to Indigenous political science scholar Glen Coulthard, the negotiation of land rights has reoriented &amp;ldquo;Indigenous struggle from one that was once deeply informed by the land as a system of reciprocal relations and obligations … to a struggle that is now largely for land, understood here as some material resource to be exploited in the capital-accumulation process.&amp;rdquo; While Coulthard is not addressing reserve land, the questions concerning relationships to land, economies, and governance, along with competing legal orders, are the not-so-deep undercurrents beneath the property-on-reserve debate. This larger political frame is usually ignored and replaced with debates about Indigenous property on reserve land that mainly start and remain inside unquestioned Western property constructs and ongoing colonial structures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regional Municipality of Waterloo v Persons Unknown and to be Ascertained</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/waterloo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/waterloo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;valente-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Valente J. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#valente-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The issue in this application of The Regional Municipality of Waterloo (the ‘Region’) concerns the prohibition against erecting any type of structure, including a tent, on the Region-owned property, municipally known as 100 Victoria Street North, in the city of Kitchener (the ‘Property’). More generally, however, the Region’s application touches on the unfortunate, complex and nationwide social issue of homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-by-law&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;strong&gt;The By-Law&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-by-law&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is undisputed that the &lt;em&gt;Municipal Act&lt;/em&gt; gives the Region the express authority to pass by-laws respecting its public assets and the protection of persons and property (see , 9, and 11(2)). It is also acknowledged that the &lt;em&gt;Trespass to Property Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.O. 1990, c.T21, as amended, ss. 3 to 8 (the &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;TPA&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;) allows an occupier of premises to prohibit or regulate entry onto premises and that the Courts have recognized municipalities as occupiers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Section 7 and the Evolving Right to Shelter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/intro-section7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/intro-section7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our discussion of acquired rights and the problem of regulating short-term rentals last week, we touched on the idea that a central issue for the Halifax Regional Municipality (HRM) and other municipal governments in Canada is access to affordable housing. There is growing awareness that Halifax is facing a crisis in housing affordability and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/homeless-report-2020-covid-19-affordable-housing-association-of-nova-scotia-1.5805458&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;dramatic rise in the number of people who experience chronic homelessness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Addressing homelessness and access to housing engages a complex set of legal and policy issues, actors and decision-making networks. One aspect of this context in which Canadian courts have been especially active is the constitutional right of homeless persons to access and shelter in public spaces—namely, municipal parks—in order to meet their immediate needs. As the problem below describes, the role of these rights and challenges to their realization gained national attention in Halifax in summer 2021, after a series of forced evictions of people living in temporary and emergency shelters on municipal lands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victoria (City) v Adams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/victoria-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/shelter/victoria-city/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ross-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ross J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ross-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This litigation arises from what Senior District Judge Atkins in &lt;em&gt;Pottinger v. Miami (City)&lt;/em&gt;, 810 F. Supp. 1551 (U.S. Dist. Ct. S.D. Fla. 1992) at 1554 described as:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; an inevitable conflict between the need of homeless individuals to perform essential, life-sustaining acts in public and the responsibility of the government to maintain orderly, aesthetically pleasing public parks and streets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The particular issue in this litigation concerns the prohibition against erecting temporary shelter on public property that is contained in the Parks Regulation Bylaw and the Streets and Traffic Bylaw (the “Bylaws”) of the City of Victoria (the “City”). Natalie Adams, Yann Chartier, Amber Overall, Alymanda Wawai, Conrad Fletcher, Sebastien Matte, Simon Ralph, Heather Turnquist and David Arthur Johnston (the “Defendants”), who are all homeless people living in the City, contend that this prohibition infringes the rights of homeless people to life, liberty and security of the person in a manner not in accordance with the principles of fundamental justice, contrary to s. 7 of the &lt;em&gt;Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms, Part I of the Constitution Act, 1982&lt;/em&gt;, [&lt;em&gt;Charter&lt;/em&gt;] being Schedule B to the &lt;em&gt;Canada Act 1982&lt;/em&gt;, (U.K.), 1982, c. 11. The intervener, the British Columbia Civil Liberties Association (the “BCCLA”), supports the defendants in this contention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
