<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Title-Registration on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/title-registration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Title-Registration on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/title-registration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Beals v Nova Scotia (AG)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/beals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/beals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;bodurtha-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Bodurtha J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#bodurtha-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Community Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt;, the predecessor to the &lt;em&gt;LTCA&lt;/em&gt;, was assented to on March 18, 1964. On second reading of the proposed legislation, the Honourable W. S. Kennedy Jones stated:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this legislation is to provide a simpler and less expensive machinery for the clarification of titles within areas or communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The second section of the Act is the definition section, and therein the minister is defined as being the Minister of Lands and Forests, and I perhaps should point out that my particular interest in the preparation and presentation of the present legislation is as the chairman of the Interdepartmental Committee on Human Rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Downey v Nova Scotia (Attorney General)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/downey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/downey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;campbell-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Campbell J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#campbell-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-land-titles-clarification-act&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The &lt;em&gt;Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-land-titles-clarification-act&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On November 24, 2017 Mr. Downey filed an application for land titles clarification under the &lt;em&gt;Land Titles Clarification Act&lt;/em&gt; with respect to a property at 39 Beals Crescent in North Preston. The history, context and purpose of that legislation has been reviewed in detail by my colleague Justice Bodurtha in &lt;em&gt;Beals v. Nova Scotia (Attorney General)&lt;/em&gt;, 2020 NSSC 60 (N.S. S.C.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land Titles Clarification Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/ltca/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/ltca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3(1) Where the residents of an area of a municipality are in necessitous circumstances as a result of lack of property development in the area and where there appears to be confusion as to the ownership of land, the Governor in Council may designate the area as a land titles clarification area. [..]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4(1) A person who claims to own land in a land titles clarification area may apply to the Minister for a certificate of claim in respect of a lot of land in the area which he claims to own.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawrence v Maple Trust Company</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/lawrence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/lawrence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gillese-ja-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Gillese J.A. –&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#gillese-ja-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ownership of a person&amp;rsquo;s home is fraudulently transferred. The property is then mortgaged. In a contest between the two innocent parties–the homeowner and the lender of mortgage moneys–who wins? This appeal answers that question in favour of the homeowner.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Susan Lawrence lives in her home in Toronto (the &amp;ldquo;Property&amp;rdquo;). The Property was encumbered by a mortgage in favour of TD/Canada Trust (the &amp;ldquo;TD Bank mortgage&amp;rdquo;) in the approximate amount of $120,000.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Land Title Clarification?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/land-title-clarification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/land-title-clarification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Downey&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Beals&lt;/em&gt;, above, discuss some of the history behind African Nova Scotian settlement in the province and describe how the &lt;em&gt;LTCA&lt;/em&gt; and its predecessor legislation was enacted to transform possessory rights into formal land titles. One prominent idea in these cases is that the lack of clear land title is a central cause of economic underdevelopment in African Nova Scotian communities&amp;ndash;and is one that can be adequately remedied through legal processes designed to recognize and formalize longstanding possessory rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
