<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lessons on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lessons on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/lessons/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to the Course</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For first-year law students, &amp;ldquo;property&amp;rdquo; can be a kaleidoscopic subject: fragmentary, blinkered, disorienting. As one (among many) possible ways of mediating our relationships with and in respect of land and other &amp;ldquo;things&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;both corporeal and not&amp;ndash;property offers up a disorderly patchwork of principles, rules and norms. It is full of contradictions, real and apparent. It presents a space of dispossession and disadvantage for some, prosperity and security for others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are likewise many ways to teach and learn about property, to try to make sense of and bring some order within the kaleidoscope. In this course, we will approach the subject from a historical perspective–one that puts the critical emphasis on the role of land relationships in Canada’s political economy as the legal ground that determines so much about who benefits from the economic system and who does not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recognition, Relationships and Possession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;animals&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Animals&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#animals&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Allen Greer suggests that early legal encounters between Indigenous peoples and European imperialists in North America were much more concerned with imperial and commercial concerns rather than land settlement per se. Central to this context was the hunting and trading of wild animals. Much of the property law of the time was shaped in this context of encounter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tina Loo observes that Blackstone&amp;rsquo;s view that wild animals were common property, open to anyone for the taking, was embraced by early colonists in North America, particularly in the Thirteen Colonies. Hunting was framed as an expression of fundamental freedom by colonists and contrasted with Old World restrictions. Colonists in British North America were more permissive of wildlife regulations that curbed hunting access [@loo2006StatesNature, 13-14].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Title as Recognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-legal-imprimatur-of-title&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Legal Imprimatur of Title&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-legal-imprimatur-of-title&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So far in our course we have discussed the central role of possession in Anglo-Canadian law and its complex connections to ownership and title going back to early liberal theory. But to date, we have not talked much about what these terms of &amp;ldquo;ownership and &amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo; really mean. Our goal this week is a more thorough understanding of title and its various forms&amp;ndash;with a focus on the history and context surrounding the common law doctrine of &amp;ldquo;Aboriginal title&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuisance and the Right to Exclude</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;property-and-exclusion&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Property and Exclusion&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#property-and-exclusion&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks we have been focused on how classical legal thought addressed questions of possession and title. We now turn to a second prominent topic&amp;ndash;one that mainly addresses the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt; of property rights held by owners or those in possession.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One right in particular, some argue, is fundamental to private property: the &lt;em&gt;right to exclude&lt;/em&gt; others from interfering with the owner&amp;rsquo;s use and enjoyment of their land, other tangible things and even intangibles like knowledge goods. The common law has devised several remedies to enforce owners&amp;rsquo; right to exclude. We have already seen one example: in &lt;em&gt;Harrison v Carswell&lt;/em&gt;, the mall owner brought an action in &lt;em&gt;trespass&lt;/em&gt; against the picketer Sophie Carswell to exclude her from the mall sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excluding the State</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;property-and-exclusion-of-public-authority&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Property and &amp;ldquo;Exclusion&amp;rdquo; of Public Authority&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#property-and-exclusion-of-public-authority&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Last week, we saw that claims in nuisance are one legal tool used by property owners—with mixed success—to stop their neighbours from adversely affecting the use and enjoyment of the owner&amp;rsquo;s land. Nuisance, in other words, is one means to exclude others from doing something that limits owners&amp;rsquo; freedom related to property. This means of exclusion, however, unavoidably limits the freedom of others to use their land as they choose. In these cases, the courts must decide whose rights should win out and in doing so address the fundamental dilemma of conflicting freedoms inherent in legal liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alienation, Exit and Control</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having now studied some of the historical basis for problems of &lt;em&gt;recognition&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;exclusion&lt;/em&gt;, this week we move on to examine the context of &lt;em&gt;exit&lt;/em&gt;: how owners transfer their rights in land and thereby disentangle themselves (wholly or partially) from property relations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Central to this context are persistent tensions between an owner&amp;rsquo;s right to &lt;em&gt;alienate&lt;/em&gt; property and their power to place restrictions on future owners&amp;rsquo; rights to do the same. As we will see, courts often put a heavy emphasis on the free alienability of land. Any attempts to restrict free alienability are viewed with considerable skepticism in the classical style—consistent with the liberal ideal that property rights should support individuals to pursue their own ends. We will read cases in which the courts scrutinize clauses in a will that purport to limit how or when beneficiaries under that will can transfer the property interests they receive. We will also examine the context of restrictive covenants in land.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trusts, Property, and Citizenship</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our final week of new material in the course for this term we will turn our minds to the concept of the &amp;ldquo;trust&amp;rdquo; and examine its features by looking at the history of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.project44.ca/japanese-canadian-internment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;dispossession and internment of Japanese Canadians&lt;/a&gt; during the second world war. The targeting of Japanese Canadians living in British Columbia as &amp;ldquo;enemy aliens&amp;rdquo; remains one of the least-discussed examples of state-executed systematic racism in Canada&amp;rsquo;s history. In exploring this history, we will also begin to encounter the mid-century transition toward a new grammar of Anglo-Canadian legal thought: the modern style. As we will see, this period of Canadian history also has something important to tell us about the connection between property, ownership and citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructive Takings and Acquired Rights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, will begin to revisit some of last term&amp;rsquo;s topics from the perspective of the modern style of Anglo-Canadian thought. Our primary focus this week will pick up on our discussion of constructive expropriation from the &lt;em&gt;McLaren v Caldwell&lt;/em&gt;. Recall that these cases involve claimed &amp;ldquo;takings&amp;rdquo; of property rights (or &amp;ldquo;sticks&amp;rdquo; from the ownership bundle) by the state, for which the owner would like to receive some form of compensation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Right to Shelter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/canada-homeless-population-health-data-halifax-1.6894448&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;accurate data&lt;/a&gt; on the circumstances of unhoused people can be difficult to get, Canada is clearly experiencing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://housing-infrastructure.canada.ca/homelessness-sans-abri/reports-rapports/data-shelter-2022-donnees-refuge-eng.html#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;rise in chronic homelessness&lt;/a&gt;, even as shelter capacity in many cities has increased following the COVID-19 pandemic. This has resulted in widespread sheltering in public spaces&amp;ndash;both temporary and longer-term&amp;ndash;in many Canadian cities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Addressing homelessness and access to housing engages a complex set of legal and policy issues, actors and decision-making networks. One aspect of this context in which Canadian courts have been especially active is the constitutional right of unhoused persons to access and shelter in public spaces&amp;ndash;namely, municipal &amp;ndash;in order to meet their immediate needs. The role of these rights and challenges to their realization have gained national attention from the circumstances in cities around the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictive Covenants and Qualified Interests</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few weeks, we have emphasized that modern, forward-looking land use planning and zoning regimes emerged in Canada by the mid-20th century to replace more decentralized and reactive forms of land-use control, such as private nuisance actions adjudicated by the common law courts. But this story about the move from private enforcement to public land-use control needs to be complicated a little further. Certain conventional, “private” forms of land-use regulation are still in widespread use. One of the most pervasive—but often least noticed—is the restrictive covenant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possession, Revisited</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we return, in part, to where we started our study of property law this year: the law of possession. Recall that John Locke&amp;rsquo;s labour theory of possession and property was an archetype of the classical style and has been a significant influence on common law principles in this area. We now want to understand how the common law&amp;rsquo;s approach to possession has evolved in the modern style.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Our Problem this Week&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our problem this week looks at how the law of possession continues to play a significant role in the world of major league baseball: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/problems/ohtani/&#34; &gt;Shohei Ohtani&amp;rsquo;s 50/50 Baseball&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reserve Lands in Transition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the next two weeks, we return to the context of Indigenous lands and land relations. Last term, we began to understand the historical basis of treaty relationships and of the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title. We continue to these topics and start this week by focusing on the legal status of reserve lands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Our Problem this Week&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#our-problem-this-week&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our problem this week looks at the adoption of a Land Code by the Membertou First Nation under the  the federal &lt;em&gt;Framework Agreement on First Nations Land Management&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/problems/membertou/&#34; &gt;Membertou&amp;rsquo;s Transition to the First Nations Land Management Framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Law Aboriginal Title</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lessons/week16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, we complete our study of Indigenous land rights, with a focus on the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title. We have traced the evolution of that doctrine from the Royal Proclamation in 1763, through &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling&lt;/em&gt; in the late nineteenth century and &lt;em&gt;Calder&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Guerin&lt;/em&gt; in the late twentieth century. The contemporary path of the Aboriginal title doctrine since those cases has been charted through a combination of constitutional reform, litigation in the courts, and negotiation between Indigenous nations and the Crown.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
