<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alienation on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/alienation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Alienation on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/alienation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Blackburn v McCallum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/blackburn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/blackburn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;davies-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Davies J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#davies-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question raised for our decision in this case is whether a general prohibition on alienation attached to a devise in fee of lands which prohibition would, if unlimited, be bad by the rules of Common Law, is made good by being limited as to time. I am of opinion that it is not. The will of Donald Chisholm after devising his farm of 100 acres to his two sons William and Hugh in fee and equally dividing it between them, contained the following provision:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restraints on Alienation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/restraints-on-alienation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/restraints-on-alienation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having now studied the roles of &lt;em&gt;possession&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;exclusion&lt;/em&gt; in common law property, this week we move on to examine the context of &lt;em&gt;exit&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;that is, how it is that owners extract themselves from property relations. Central to this context is the right to &lt;em&gt;alienate&lt;/em&gt; property and the power of owners to place restrictions on alienability. Recall that we have already encountered alienation and restraints on alienation in the context of Aboriginal title going back to the Royal Proclamation in 1763. As we learn this week, the extent to which landowners can and should be able transfer their property rights to others and to place limits on alienation has long raised some pervasive controversies in common law property.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
