<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aboriginal-Title on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/aboriginal-title/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Aboriginal-Title on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/aboriginal-title/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Constitution Act, 1982</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/constitution-act-s35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/constitution-act-s35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;section-35&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Section 35&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#section-35&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(1) The existing aboriginal and treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada are hereby recognized and affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(2) In this Act, “aboriginal peoples of Canada” includes the Indian, Inuit and Métis peoples of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(3) For greater certainty, in subsection (1) “treaty rights” includes rights that now exist by way of land claims agreements or may be so acquired. […]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delgamuukw v British Columbia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/delgamuukw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/delgamuukw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lamer-cjc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Lamer C.J.C &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#lamer-cjc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ii-facts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  II. Facts&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#ii-facts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-the-claim-at-trial&#34;&gt;&#xA;  A. The Claim at Trial&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#a-the-claim-at-trial&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This action was commenced by the appellants, who are all Gitksan or Wet&amp;rsquo;suwet&amp;rsquo;en hereditary chiefs, who, both individually and on behalf of their &amp;ldquo;Houses&amp;rdquo; claimed separate portions of 58,000 square kilometres in British Columbia. For the purpose of the claim, this area was divided into 133 individual territories, claimed by the 71 Houses. This represents all of the Wet&amp;rsquo;suwet&amp;rsquo;en people, and all but 12 of the Gitksan Houses. Their claim was originally for &amp;ldquo;ownership&amp;rdquo; of the territory and &amp;ldquo;jurisdiction&amp;rdquo; over it. (At this Court, this was transformed into, primarily, a claim for aboriginal title over the land in question.) The province of British Columbia counterclaimed for a declaration that the appellants have no right or interest in and to the territory or alternatively, that the appellants&amp;rsquo; cause of action ought to be for compensation from the Government of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duty to Consult</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/duty-to-consult/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/duty-to-consult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You will note that in the final paragraphs excerpted from &lt;em&gt;Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation&lt;/em&gt;, the Supreme Court found that the Province of British Columbia breached its duty to consult with the Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation prior to granting forestry licences to third parties on territorial lands. That duty was engaged when the Province began the planning process for removing timber on the land.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An important point here is that the Crown owed and breached its duty to consult with the Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation well &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; to the Tsilhqot&amp;rsquo;in Nation  successfully proving their claim in the courts. This is a central purpose of the consultation doctrine: it engages the Crown&amp;rsquo;s fiduciary duty and the honour of the Crown in advance of litigation or negotiations to address claims to title, and therefore offers some measure of protection for title lands in light of the several legal and other barriers to successfully resolving such claims.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guerin v R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/guerin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/guerin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;This case concerns the lease of reserve lands situated within the geographical boundaries of the City of Vancouver. In 1957, members of the Musqueam Indian Band voted to surrender 162 acres of their reserve lands to the federal Crown on the understanding that these lands would in turn be leased by the Crown to the Shaughnessy Heights Golf Club for use as a golf course. Rents and other benefits from this lease were to be paid to Band. The final terms on which the Crown ultimately leased the lands to Shaughnessy Heights, however, were very unfavourable to the Band. The Chief and Councillors of the Musqueam Indian Band sued the Crown for breach of trust and damages in the amount of $10,000,000.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overview - The St. Catherine&#39;s Milling Case</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/overview-st-catherines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/overview-st-catherines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For more than a hundred years after it was enacted, the Royal Proclamation of 1763 stood as the British Crown&amp;rsquo;s most authoritative statement on Aboriginal title. But during this period the Proclamation itself received little to no scrutiny in the common law courts. This changed dramatically when the Chancery Division of the High Court of Ontario issued its decision in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling and Lumber Co. v R&lt;/em&gt; in 1886, followed by subsequent appeals all the way to the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council—at that time, Canada&amp;rsquo;s highest court of appeal. The case would chart the course for the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title in Canada for well into the next century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Royal Proclamation (1763)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/royal-proclamation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/royal-proclamation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/imgs/rp1763.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And whereas it is just and reasonable, and essential to our Interest, and the Security of our Colonies, that the several Nations or Tribes of Indians with whom We are connected, and who live under our Protection, should not be molested or disturbed in the Possession of such Parts of Our Dominions and Territories as, not having been ceded to or purchased by Us, are reserved to them, or any of them, as their Hunting Grounds,&amp;ndash;We do therefore, with the Advice of our Privy Council, declare it to be our Royal Will and Pleasure, that no Governor or Commander in Chief in any of our Colonies of Quebec, East Florida, or West Florida, do presume, upon any Pretence whatever, to grant Warrants of Survey, or pass any Patents for Lands beyond the Bounds of their respective Governments, as described in their Commissions: as also that no Governor or Commander in Chief in any of our other Colonies or Plantations in America do presume for the present, and until our further Pleasure be known, to grant Warrants of Survey, or pass Patents for any Lands beyond the Heads or Sources of any of the Rivers which fall into the Atlantic Ocean from the West and North West, or upon any Lands whatever, which, not having been ceded to or purchased by Us as aforesaid, are reserved to the said Indians, or any of them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Southwind v Canada</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/southwind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/southwind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;karakatsanis-j&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Karakatsanis J.&amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#karakatsanis-j&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the twentieth century, Canada needed more&#xA;electricity to fuel Winnipeg&amp;rsquo;s economic growth. The governments of&#xA;Canada, Manitoba, and Ontario decided to create a water reservoir in&#xA;northern Ontario to power hydroelectricity generation. They settled on&#xA;Lac Seul, which flows into both Ontario and Manitoba, and determined&#xA;that if they raised the water level of Lac Seul by 10 feet, or&#xA;approximately 3 metres, they could generate substantial electricity.&#xA;Construction of the dam was completed in 1929 and the water steadily&#xA;rose through the 1930s. The project was a success for the three&#xA;governments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>St. Catherine&#39;s Milling and Lumber Co. v R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stcatherines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/stcatherines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background to the Case&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For more than a hundred years after it was enacted, the Royal Proclamation of 1763 stood as the British Crown&amp;rsquo;s most authoritative statement on Aboriginal title. But during this period the Proclamation itself received little to no scrutiny in the common law courts. This changed dramatically when the Chancery Division of the High Court of Ontario issued its decision in &lt;em&gt;St. Catherine&amp;rsquo;s Milling and Lumber Co. v R&lt;/em&gt; in 1886, followed by subsequent appeals all the way to the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council—at that time, Canada&amp;rsquo;s highest court of appeal. The case would chart the course for the common law doctrine of Aboriginal title in Canada for well into the next century.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tsilhqot’in Nation v. British Columbia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tsilhqotin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/title/tsilhqotin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McLachlin C.J.C. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is the test for Aboriginal title to land? If title is established, what rights does it confer? Does the British Columbia &lt;em&gt;Forest Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.B.C. 1996, c. 157, apply to land covered by Aboriginal title? What are the constitutional constraints on provincial regulation of land under Aboriginal title? Finally, how are broader public interests to be reconciled with the rights conferred by Aboriginal title? These are among the important questions raised by this appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
