<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Police-Power on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/doctrines/police-power/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Police-Power on Land &amp; Lawscapes: An Open Casebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/doctrines/police-power/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Annapolis Group Inc. v Halifax Regional Municipality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/annapolis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/annapolis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;côté-brown-jj-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Côté, Brown JJ. &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#c%c3%b4t%c3%a9-brown-jj-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-overview&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Overview&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-overview&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This appeal calls upon the Court to clarify the circumstances in which state regulation of land use may effect a &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; or (as we will refer to it) “constructive” taking of private property.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The appellant, Annapolis Group Inc., contends that the respondent, Halifax Regional Municipality, improperly used its regulatory powers to effectively seize Annapolis’ land for use as a public park without compensation. Halifax says that Annapolis’ claim is a veiled attempt to make taxpayers foot the bill for a decades-long development gamble. It sought summary dismissal of this part of Annapolis’ claim, while permitting other claims (for misfeasance in public office and unjust enrichment) to proceed to trial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Belfast Corporation v OD Cars LTD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/belfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/belfast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;viscount-simonds-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Viscount Simonds &amp;ndash;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#viscount-simonds-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--&#xA;&#xA; My Lords, the facts in this case, which give rise to some difficult questions, can be shortly stated. The respondents, a limited company registered in Belfast, own in fee farm certain land at Alexandra Park, Belfast. On buildings erected on that land, they have for many years carried on the business of garage proprietors and general motor engineers. On Feb. 9, 1954, they made an application to the appellants. the Belfast Corporation, for permission to erect on the land further industrial and commercial premises, viz., lock-up shops on Antrim Road and factories or warehouses on the back portion. The application was made pursuant to the provisions of s. 2 of the Planning (Interim Development) Act (Northern Ireland), 1944, to the appellants as the interim development authority. Such an application is known as an interim development application. I will refer later to this Act. On Mar. 2, 1954, the appellants refused the application on the ground (a) as to the lock-up shops, that the height and character of the proposed development would not be in accordance with their requirements for the site, namely, development to be in shops with dwellings over minimum height twenty-five feet, and (b) as to the industrial or commercial use of remainder of site, that the site was zoned as residential and that the character and user of the proposed development would be incompatible with such zoning. This refusal led to a claim for compensation for injurious affection under the Act which, in accordance with its provisions, was referred to the official arbitrator appointed thereunder. Before I narrate the proceedings which led to this appeal, I must refer to the relevant statutory provisions of the Planning and Housing Act (Northern Ireland), 1931, and the Planning (Interim Development) Act (Northern Ireland), 1944, which I will call the Act of 1931 and the Act of 1944. The former Act, after providing for the making of planning schemes to be prepared and adopted by local authorities and to be approved by the Minister and sundry other relevant matters, by s. 9 (1) enacted that any person whose property is injuriously affected by the coming into operation of a planning scheme shall, if he makes a claim for the purpose within the time therein mentioned, be entitled to obtain compensation in respect thereof from the responsible authority. But this right is subject to the limitation contained in s. 10, which provides, by sub-s. (1), that where property is alleged to be injuriously affected by reason of any provisions contained in a planning scheme, no compensation shall be paid in respect thereof if or so far as the provisions are also contained in any public, general or local Act in force in the area or otherwise as therein mentioned and, by sub-s. (2) (which is the subsection relevant to this appeal and must be set out verbatim), as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&gt; Property shall not be deemed to be injuriously affected by reason of the coming into operation of any provisions inserted in a planning scheme, which prescribe the space about buildings or limit the number of buildings to be erected, or prescribe the height or character or user of buildings, or prescribe a standard of net annual value for buildings, and which the Ministry, having regard to the nature and situation of the land affected by the provisions, considers reasonable for the purpose:&#xA;&#xA;Development under the Act of 1931 made slow progress and was in due course supplemented by the Act of 1944. Section 1 (1) of that Act deems all land which was not the subject of a planning scheme under the earlier Act, or of a resolution to prepare and adopt such a scheme, to be subject to a resolution to prepare a planning scheme under the Act. Section 2 directs the Ministry to make a general interim development order with respect to land to which such a resolution applies, and provides that such an order may empower any local authority specified therein to permit the development of land in accordance with the provisions thereof. In accordance with the duty thus placed on it, the Ministry, on July 10, 1944, made the Planning (General Interim Development) Order (Northern Ireland), 1944 (S.R. &amp; O. 1944 No. 58), which empowered the appellants to grant permission for the development of land within the county borough of Belfast. I need refer no more to the Act of 1944 except to set out the section, i.e., s. 6, under which, as I have already said, the respondents made the claim for compensation now under review. That section provided, by sub-s. (4), so far as material, as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&gt; Where ... an interim development application is refused ... then, the applicant ... shall, if he makes a claim for the purpose be entitled to obtain from the local authority such compensation in respect of any injurious affection of his property by reason of the aforesaid decision as he would be entitled to obtain under the principal Act [the Act of 1931] if such injurious affection had been suffered as a consequence of the coming into operation of a planning scheme...&#xA;&#xA;The claim for compensation having been made and refused on the grounds that I have stated, a number of questions were raised before the arbitrator which led him without proceeding to an award to state a consultative case for the opinion of the court in which he posed two questions as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&#34;(i) Whether I am entitled to award compensation to the claimant for injurious affection of the said land.&#34;&#xA;&#xA;&#34;(ii) Whether the evidence of Mr. A. P. Fitzgerald is suffcient to satisfy the requirements of s. 10 (2) of the Planning and Housing Act (Northern Ireland), 1931.&#34;&#xA;&#xA;The second question must appear at the present stage of my narrative somewhat cryptic. It is, in my opinion, of a formal character, and I will defer consideration of it until I have disposed of the important matters that arise under the first question. These are, first, a question arising on the construction of the Act of 1944, viz., whether s. 6 (4) of that Act incorporates a reference to s. 10 (2) of the Act of 1831 as well as to the compensatory provisions of s. 9, and, secondly, whether s. 10(2) is a valid enactment having regard to the provisions of s. 5 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920. The far-reaching importance of the second question is obvious.&#xA;&#xA;My Lords, on the first of these questions I entertain no doubt, and I cannot state the answer to it in a manner more clear and comprehensive than the learned Lord Chief Justice (Lord MacDermott) has done. Section 6 (4) of the later Act does incorporate s. 10 (2) of the earlier Act. I will not occupy your Lordships&#39; time by further reference to it.&#xA;&#xA;On the second question, viz., the constitutional validity of s. 10 (2) of the Act of 1931, I must say something more. For, though I agree with much that the Lord Chief Justice has said on this topic, there comes a point at which I must with great respect diverge from him. The issue turns on the true meaning and effect of s. 5 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920. Subsection (1) of that section is as follows:&#xA;&#xA;&gt; In the exercise of their power to make laws under this Act neither the Parliament of Southern Ireland nor the Parliament of Northern Ireland shall make a law so as either directly or indirectly to establish or endow any religion, or prohibit or restrict the free exercise thereof, or give a preference, privilege, or advantage, or impose any disability or disadvantage, on account of religious belief or religious or ecclesiastical status, or make any religious belief or religious ceremony a condition of the validity of any marriage, or affect prejudicially the right of any child to attend a school receiving public money without attending the religious instruction at that school, or alter the constitution of any religious body except where the alteration is approved on behalf of the religious body by the governing body thereof, or divert from any religious denomination the fabric of cathedral churches, or, except for the purpose of roads, railways, lighting. water, or drainage works, or other works of public utility upon payment of compensation, any other property, or take any property without compensation.&#xA;&#xA;&gt; Any law made in contravention of the restrictions imposed by this subsection shall, so far as it contravenes those restrictions, be void.&#xA;&#xA;It was first urged on behalf of the appellants that the last five words of the first paragraph of this subsection referred only to the property of religious bodies or institutions. This point was decided against them twenty years ago in *O&#39;Neill v. Northern Ireland Road Transport Board*, and I do not doubt that that case was rightly decided. An argument founded on the historical genesis of these words, which was in any case of little weight, could not prevail against their plain meaning. Next, I must refer to an argument (though I am not clear which side could be assisted by it) that the words &#34;either directly or indirectly &#34; do not govern the last five words. But grammatically they clearly do, and I see no reason for not allowing grammatical laws to prevail. In any view, it is of no importance to this case.&#xA;&#xA;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canada-United States-Mexico Agreement, Article 14</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cusma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cusma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;article-148-expropriation-and-compensation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Article 14.8: Expropriation and Compensation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#article-148-expropriation-and-compensation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 No Party shall expropriate or nationalize a covered investment either directly or indirectly through measures equivalent to expropriation or nationalization (expropriation), except:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) for a public purpose;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) in a non-discriminatory manner;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(c) on payment of prompt, adequate, and effective compensation in accordance with paragraphs 2, 3, and 4; and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(d) in accordance with due process of law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;annex-14-6-expropriation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Annex 14-6 Expropriation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#annex-14-6-expropriation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Parties confirm their shared understanding that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canadian Pacific Railway Co. v Vancouver (City)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/cpr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  McLachlin C.J.C. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mclachlin-cjc-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over a century ago, in 1886, the provincial Crown granted the Canadian Pacific Railway Company (”CPR”) a corridor of land for the construction of a railway line from False Creek, in the City of Vancouver (”City”), south to Steveston, on Lulu Island (named after Miss Lulu Sweet, a young actress in the first theatrical company to visit British Columbia). It is this corridor of land, now known as the “Arbutus Corridor”, that lies at the heart of this appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expropriation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Remedies in nuisance are one legal tool used by property owners—with mixed success—to stop their neighbours from adversely affecting use and enjoyment of the owner&amp;rsquo;s land. Nuisance, in other words, is one means to exclude others from doing something that limits owners&amp;rsquo; freedom related to property. This means of exclusion, however, unavoidably limits the freedom of others to use their land as they choose. In these cases, the courts must choose not only whose rights should win out but also find some way to address the fundamental dilemma of conflicting freedoms inherent in legal liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expropriation Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/expropriation-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;statute&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;!--2(w) “fur-bearing animal” means beaver, muskrat, red squir- rel, mink, otter, skunk, weasel, fisher, marten, lynx, bobcat, cougar, fox, coyote, raccoon and any other non-domesticated animal which may be designated as a fur-bearing animal by the Governor in Coun- cil, and includes any part of such animal, but does not include bear or snowshoe hare;--&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3(1)(c) “expropriate” means the taking of land without the consent of the owner by an expropriating authority in the exercise of its statutory powers;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hodge v the Queen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/hodge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/hodge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;judgement-of-the-lords-of-the-judicial-committee-of-the-privy-council&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Judgement of the Lords of the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#judgement-of-the-lords-of-the-judicial-committee-of-the-privy-council&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Appellant, Archibald Hodge, the proprietor of a tavern known as the St. James Hotel, in the city of Toronto, and who, on the 7th May 1881, was the holder of a license for the retail of spirituous liquors in his tavern, and also licensed to keep a billiard saloon, was summoned before the Police Magistrate of Toronto, for a breach of the Resolutions of the License Commissioners of Toronto, and was convicted on evidence sufficient to sustain the conviction if the magistrate had authority in law to make it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House of Commons Debate (Rivers and Streams Bill)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/house-debates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/house-debates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mr-mccarthy-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Mr. McCarthy —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#mr-mccarthy-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the House rose at six o&amp;rsquo;clock, I was proceeding to consider that part of the Bill which deals with compensation. Perhaps I might first be permitted to state, however, what I understand to be the meaning of the word &amp;ldquo;compensation,&amp;rdquo; when applied to the sovereign right of expropriation. Now, I do not pretend to dispute, and I am quite willing to admit in the amplest possible manner, so far as my judgement goes, that this &lt;em&gt;Act&lt;/em&gt; of Parliament was, subject to one consideration, within the power of the Local Legislature. If the one consideration be overlooked there is power in the Local Legislature as in every other sovereign body&amp;ndash;and the Local Legislature is sovereign so far as its jurisdiction extends&amp;ndash;to expropriate property for public purposes. But, Sir, as I understand the doctrine of expropriation, as we call it, or as it is better known on the other side of the line, the exercise of its power of &lt;em&gt;eminent domain&lt;/em&gt;, there are two limitations to the exercise of that power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mariner Real Estate Ltd v Nova Scotia (Attorney General)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mariner/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mariner/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;cromwell-ja-glube-cjns-concurring-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Cromwell J.A. (Glube C.J.N.S. concurring) —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#cromwell-ja-glube-cjns-concurring-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I. Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#i-introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This case involves a collision of important interests. On one side, there are the interests of the respondents in the enjoyment of their privately owned land at Kingsburg Beach. On the other is the public interest in the protection and preservation of environmentally fragile and ecologically significant beach, dune and beach ridge resources. In the background of this case is the policy issue of how minutely government may control land without buying it. But in the foreground is the narrower issue of whether the stringent land use regulations applied by the Province to the respondents’ lands is an expropriation of them within the meaning of the &lt;em&gt;Expropriation Act&lt;/em&gt;, R.S.N.S. 1989, c. 156.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>McLaren v Caldwell et al</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mclaren/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/mclaren/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Background to the Case&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#background-to-the-case&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the nineteenth century, access to waterways in Upper Canada and elsewhere in the country became an integral part of the lumber industry and a primary means to bring timber from logging operations to sawmills and other points of market. From one perspective, these waterways were akin to other types of public infrastructure (like roads and railways) necessary for rapidly expanding natural resource extraction and, eventually,  industrialization. In 1847, provincial legislation was passed to help ensure access to waterways in Upper Canada by lumber workers. The legislation stated that:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metalclad Corporation v The United Mexican States</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/metalclad/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/metalclad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-tribunal-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Tribunal —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-tribunal-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;c-nafta-article-1110-expropriation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  C. NAFTA, Article 1110: Expropriation&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#c-nafta-article-1110-expropriation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;NAFTA Article 1110 provides that “[n]o party shall directly or indirectly … expropriate an investment … or take a measure tantamount to … expropriation … except: (a) for a public purpose; (b) on a non- discriminatory basis; (c) in accordance with due process of law and Article 1105(1); and (d) on payment of compensation …” “A measure” is defined in Article 201(1) as including “any law, regulation, procedure, requirement or practice”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pennsylvania Coal Co. v Mahon</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/pennsylvania-coal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/pennsylvania-coal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holmes-j-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Holmes J. —&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#holmes-j-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a bill in equity brought by the defendants in error to prevent the Pennsylvania Coal Company from mining under their property in such way as to remove the supports and cause a subsidence of the surface and of their house. The bill sets out a deed executed by the Coal Company in 1878, under which the plaintiffs claim. The deed conveys the surface, but, in express terms, reserves the right to remove all the coal under the same, and the grantee takes the premises with the risk, and waives all claim for damages that may arise from mining out the coal. But the plaintiffs say that, whatever may have been the Coal Company&amp;rsquo;s rights, they were taken away by an Act of Pennsylvania, approved May 27, 1921, P.L. 1198, commonly known there as the Kohler Act. The Court of Common Pleas found that, if not restrained, the defendant would cause the damage to prevent which the bill was brought, but denied an injunction, holding that the statute, if applied to this case, would be unconstitutional. On appeal, the Supreme Court of the State agreed that the defendant had contract and property rights protected by the Constitution of the United States, but held that the statute was a legitimate exercise of the police power, and directed a decree for the plaintiffs. A writ of error was granted bringing the case to this Court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perry v Clissold</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/perry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/perry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PRIVY COUNCIL&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perry Appellant; and Clissold and Others Respondents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On appeal from the High Court of Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;14 December 1906&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Lord Chancellor, The Earl of Halsbury, Lord Macnaghten, Lord Davey, Lord Robertson, Lord Atkinson, Sir Ford North, Sir Arthur Wilson.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The judgment of their Lordships was delivered by&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;lord-macnaghten-&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Lord Macnaghten –&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#lord-macnaghten-&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This was an appeal from a judgment of the High Court of Australia, dated the 20th of June 1904, reversing a judgment of the Supreme Court of New South Wales. It raised a question under the Lands for Public Purposes Acquisition Act 1880 (44 Vict. No. 16), now superseded by the Public Works Act 1900, which consolidates the law on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Riparian Rights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/water-rights/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/water-rights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;riparian owner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the owner of land bounding upon a river or other watercourse. The traditional presumption of English common law is that a riparian owner owns the bed of a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-navigable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; river or stream to the centre of the watercourse: &lt;em&gt;ad medium filum aquae&lt;/em&gt;. Consequently, a riparian owner who holds land on both sides of a river considered &amp;ldquo;non-navigable&amp;rdquo; owns the entire riverbed and has exclusive rights to the river&amp;rsquo;s use .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rivers and Streams Act</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/rivers-and-streams-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/casebook/governance/rivers-and-streams-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1. All persons shall, subject to the provisions in this Act contained, have, and are hereby declared always to have had, floating down during the spring, summer and autumn freshets, the right to, and may float and transmit saw-logs and all other timber of every kind, and all rafts and crafts, down all rivers, creeks and streams; and no person shall by felling trees or placing any other obstruction in or across any such river, creek or stream, prevent the passage thereof; and in case it may be necessary to remove any obstruction from such river, creek or stream, or construct any apron, dam, slide, gate-lock, boom, or other work therein or thereon, necessary to facilitate the floating and transmitting such saw-logs and other timber, rafts or crafts, down the same, then it shall be lawful for the person requiring so to float and transmit such saw-logs and other timber, rafts and crafts, and it is hereby declared always to have been lawful to remove such obstruction, and to construct such apron, dam, slide, gate-lock, boom or other work necessary for the purposes aforesaid, doing no unnecessary damage to the said river, creek or stream, or to the banks thereof.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
